The following is a conversation with Demis Hassabis, CEO and co-founder of DeepMind, a company
that has published and built some of the most incredible artificial intelligence systems
in the history of computing, including Alpha Zero that learned all by itself to play the game
of Go better than any human in the world and Alpha Fold 2 that solved protein folding.
Both tasks considered nearly impossible for a very long time.
Demis is widely considered to be one of the most brilliant and impactful humans
in the history of artificial intelligence and science and engineering in general.
This was truly an honor and a pleasure for me to finally sit down with him for this conversation
and I'm sure we will talk many times again in the future.
This is Luxembourg podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Demis Hassabis.
Let's start with a bit of a personal question.
Am I an AI program you wrote to interview people until I get good enough to interview you?
Well, I'd be impressed if you were. I'd be impressed by myself if you were.
I don't think we're quite up to that yet, but maybe you're from the future, Lex.
If you did, would you tell me? Is that a good thing to tell a language model that's tasked
with interviewing that it is, in fact, AI? Maybe we're in a kind of meta-turing test.
Probably it would be a good idea not to tell you, so it doesn't change your behavior, right?
This is a kind of vice and borough-gun-settity principle situation.
If I told you you behave differently, maybe that's what's happening with us, of course.
This is a benchmark from the future where they replay 2022 as a year before AI's were good enough.
Yet, and now we want to see, is it going to pass, exactly.
If I was such a program, would you be able to tell, do you think?
So, to the touring test question, you've talked about
the benchmark for solving intelligence. What would be the impressive thing?
You've talked about winning a Nobel Prize in ACES, the winning a Nobel Prize,
but I still return to the touring test as a compelling test. The spirit of the touring test is
a compelling test. Yeah, the touring test, of course, it's been unbelievably influential,
and Cheering's one of my all-time heroes. But I think if you look back at the 1950
papers, original paper, and read the original, you'll see, I don't think he meant it to be a
rigorous formal test. I think it was more like a thought experiment, almost a bit of philosophy
he was writing. If you look at the style of the paper, and you can see he didn't specify it very
rigorously. For example, he didn't specify the knowledge that the expert or judge would have,
not how much time would they have to investigate this. These are important parameters,
if you're going to make it a true formal test. By some measures, people claim the touring test
passed several decades ago. I remember someone claiming that with a very box-standard normal
logic model, because they pretended it was a kit. The judges thought that the machine was a child.
That would be very different from an expert AI person interrogating a machine and knowing
how it was built and so on. We should probably move away from that as a formal test and move more
towards a general test where we test the AI capabilities on a range of tasks and see if it
reaches human level or above performance on maybe thousands, perhaps even millions of tasks,
eventually, and cover the entire sort of cognitive space. I think for its time, it was an amazing
thought experiment, and also 1950s, obviously, it was barely the dawn of the computer age.
So of course, he only thought about text, and now we have a lot more different inputs.
So yeah, maybe the better thing to test is the generalizability, so across multiple tasks,
but I think it's also possible, as systems like God will show, that eventually that might
map right back to language. So you might be able to demonstrate your ability to generalize
across tasks by then communicating your ability to generalize across tasks, which is kind of what
we do through conversation anyway, when we jump around. Ultimately, what's in there in that
conversation is not just you moving around knowledge, it's you moving around like these
entirely different modalities of understanding that ultimately map to your ability to operate
successfully in all of these domains, which you can think of as tasks. Yeah, I think certainly
we as humans use language as our main generalization communication tool. So I think we end up
thinking in language and expressing our solutions in language. So it's going to be very powerful
mode in which to explain the system to explain what it's doing, but I don't think it's the only
modality that matters. So I think there's going to be a lot of, you know, there's a lot of different
ways to express capabilities other than just language. Yeah, visual, robotics, body language,
yeah, actions, the interactive aspect of all that, that's all part of it. But what's interesting
with Gato is that it's sort of pushing prediction to the maximum in terms of like, you know,
mapping arbitrary sequences to other sequences and sort of just predicting what's going to happen
next. So prediction seems to be fundamental to intelligence. And what you're predicting doesn't
so much matter. Yeah, it seems like you can generalize that quite well. So obviously, language
models predict the next word. Gato predicts potentially any action or any token. And it's just
the beginning really. So I'm most general agent. One could call it so far, but, you know, that
itself can be scaled up massively more than we've done so far. And obviously, we're in the
in the middle of doing that. But the big part of solving AGI is creating benchmarks that
help us get closer and closer sort of creating benchmarks that test the generalizability. And
it's just still interesting that this fellow Alan Turing was one of the first and probably
still one of the only people that was trying maybe philosophically, but was trying to formulate
a benchmark that could be followed. It is even though it's fuzzy, it's still sufficiently rigorous
the way you can run that test. And I still think something like the Turing test will end at the end
of the day be the thing that truly impresses other humans so that you can have a close friend
who's an AI system. And for that friend to be a good friend, they're going to have to be able to
play Starcraft. And they're going to have to do all of these tasks. Get you a beer so that
the robotics tasks play games with you. Use language, humor, all those kinds of things, but that
ultimately can blow down to language. It feels like not in terms of the AI community, but in terms
of the actual impact of general intelligence on the world, it feels like language will be the
place where truly shines. I think so because it's such an important kind of input output for us.
I think you're right. I think the Turing test, the philosophy behind it, which is the idea of
can a machine mimic the behaviors of a human. And I would say wider than just language and text,
then in terms of actions and everything else, creativity, all these things, then if it can
sort of match or exceed human cognitive capabilities, then I think we have a true intelligence.
So I felt from that perspective, you're right. I think he did formulate the right kind of setup.
I just I think there'll be a kind of humor in the AI systems, the future looking back to this
conversation and thinking about the Turing test and also thinking about by that time,
they would know which year they were finally able to sort of cross the threshold of human
level intelligence and think how funny it is that we humans were still confused about this whole
problem that's been long ago been solved. Well, hello to the AI agents of the future.
Anyway, so go back to your to your journey. When did you fall in love with programming first?
Well, it was pretty, it was pretty young age actually. So you know, I started off actually
games was my first love. So starting to play chess when I was around four years old and then
is actually with winnings from a chess competition that I managed to buy my first chess computer
when I was about eight years old. It was a ZX Spectrum, which was hugely popular in the UK at the time.
And it was an amazing machine because I think it trained a whole generation of programmers in
the UK because it was so accessible, you know, you literally switched it on and there was the
basic prompt and you could just get going and my parents didn't really know anything about
computers. But because it was my money from a chess competition, I could say I wanted to buy it.
And then, you know, I just went to bookstores, got books on programming and started typing in,
you know, the programming code and then of course, once you start doing that, you start adjusting
it and then making your own games. And that's when I fell in love with computers and realized that
they were a very magical device. In a way, I kind of, I don't want to be able to explain this at
the time, but I felt that they were sort of almost a magical extension of your mind. I always had
this feeling and I've always loved this about computers that you can set them off doing something,
some task for you. You can go to sleep, come back the next day and it's solved. You know, that feels
magical to me. So, I mean, all machines do that to some extent. They all enhance our natural
capabilities. Obviously, cars make us allow us to move faster than we can run, but this was a machine
to extend the mind. And then of course, AI is the ultimate expression of what a machine may be
able to do or learn. So, very naturally for me, that thought extended into AI quite quickly.
Remember the programming language that was first started and was especially special to the machine?
No, it was just the basic, I think it was just basic on the ZX Spectrum. I don't know what
specific form it was. And then later on, I got a Commodore Miga, which was a fantastic machine.
Now you're just showing off. So, yeah, well, lots of my friends had Atari STs and I managed to get
amigas. It was a bit more powerful and that was incredible and used to do programming in assembler
and also Amos basic, this specific form of basic. It was incredible actually. So, all my coding
skills. And when did you fall in love with AI? So, when did you first start to gain an understanding
that you can not just write programs that do some mathematical operations for you while you sleep,
but something that's a keen to bringing an entity to life, sort of a thing that can figure out
something more complicated than a simple mathematical operation? Yeah, so there was a few stages for
me all while I was very young. So, first of all, as I was trying to improve at playing chess,
I was captaining various English and junior chess teams and at the time when I was about,
you know, maybe 10, 11 years old, I was going to become a professional chess player. That was my
first thought. So, that dream was there to try to get to the highest level of chess. Yeah, so,
I was, you know, I got to, when I was about 12 years old, I got to Master Standard and I was
second highest rated player in the world to Judith Polga, who obviously ended up being an amazing
chess player and a world women's champion. And when I was trying to improve at chess, what you
do is you, obviously, first of all, you're trying to improve your own thinking processes. So,
that leads you to thinking about thinking, how is your brain coming up with these ideas?
Why is it making mistakes? How can you, how can you improve that thought process? But the second
thing is that you, it was just the beginning. This was like in the, in the early 80s, mid 80s of
chess computers. If you remember, they were physical balls, like the one we have in front of us,
and you pressed down the, you know, the squares. And I think Kasparov had a branded version of it
that I got. And you were, you know, used to, they're not as strong as they are today, but they were,
they were pretty strong and used to practice against them to try and improve your openings and
other things. And so, I remember, I think I probably got my first one, I was around 11 or 12,
and I remember thinking, this is amazing, you know, how, how someone programmed this, this chess
ball to play chess. And it was very formative book I bought, which was called the chess computer
handbook by David Levy. It came out in 1984 or something. So I must have got it when I was about
11, 12, and it explained fully how these chess programs were made. And I remember my first AI
program being a program, my Amiga, it couldn't, it wasn't powerful enough to play chess. I couldn't
write a whole chess program, but I wrote a program for it to play Othello, reverse it, sometimes called
I think in the US. And so a slightly simpler game than chess, but I used all of the principles
that chess programs had, alphabeta, search, all of that. And that was my first AI program,
I remember that very well, I was around 12 years old. So that, that brought me into AI. And then
the second part was later on, on as around 16, 17, and I was writing games professionally,
designing games, writing game called Theme Park, which had AI as a core gameplay component,
as part of the simulation. And it sold, you know, millions of copies around the world, and people
loved the way that the AI, even though is relatively simple, by today's AI standards, was reacting
to the way you as the player played it. So it was a called a sandbox game. So it was one of the first
types of games like that, along with SimCity, and it meant that every game you played was unique.
Is there something you could say just on a small tangent about really impressive AI
from a game design, human enjoyment perspective, really impressive AI that you've seen in games,
and maybe what does it take to create AI system? And how hard of a problem is that? So a million
questions will just as a brief tangent. Well, look, I think games have been significant in my
life for three reasons. So first of all, to I was playing them and training myself on games
when I was a kid, then I went through a phase of designing games and writing AI for games. So all
the games I professionally wrote had AI as a core component. And that was mostly in the in the 90s.
And the reason I was doing that in games industry was at the time the games industry, I think,
was the cutting edge of technology. So whether it was graphics with people like John Carmack and Quake
and those kind of things or AI, I think actually all the action was going on in games. And we
seen we're still reaping the benefits of that even with things like GPUs, which I find ironic was
obviously invented for graphics, computer graphics, but then turns out to be amazingly useful for AI.
It just turns out everything's a matrix multiplication appears in the whole world. So I think games at
the time had the most cutting edge AI. And a lot of the games I was involved in writing. So there
was a game called Black and White, which was one game I was involved with in the early stages of,
which I still think is the most impressive example of reinforcement learning in a computer game.
So in that game, you know, you trained a little pet animal and yeah, and it sort of learned
from how you were treating it. So if you treated it badly, then it became mean. And then it would
be mean to your villagers and your and your population, the sort of the little tribe that you were
running. But if you were kind to it, then it would be kind. And people fascinated by how that
worked. And so was I to be honest with the way it kind of developed. And especially the mapping
to good in evil. Yeah. It made you major realized made me realize that you can sort of in the way
in the choices you make can define the where you end up. And that means all of us are capable of the
good evil. It all matters in the different choices along the trajectory to those places that you
make as fascinating. I mean, games can do that for a soft good to you. And it's rare. It seems
rare. Yeah. Well, games are I think a unique medium because you as the player, you're not just
passively consuming the entertainment, right? You're actually actively involved as an agent.
So I think that's what makes it in some ways can be more visceral than other other mediums like,
you know, films and books. So the second. So that was, you know, designing AI in games. And then
the third use. I we've used of AI is in deep mind from the beginning, which is using games as
a testing ground for proving out AI algorithms and developing AI algorithms. And that was a that
was a sort of a core component of our vision at the start of deep mind was that we would use games
very heavily as our main testing ground certainly to begin with because it's super efficient to
use games. And also, you know, it's very easy to have metrics to see how well your systems
are improving and what direction your ideas are going in and whether you're making incremental
improvements. And because those games are often rooted in something that humans did for a long
time beforehand, there's already a strong set of rules like it's already a damn good benchmark.
Yes, it's really good for so many reasons because you've got you've got you've got clear measures
of how good humans can be at these things. And in some cases, like Go, we've been playing it for
thousands of years. And often they have scores or at least win conditions. So it's very easy for
award learning systems to get a reward. It's very easy to specify what that reward is.
And also at the end, it's easy to, you know, to test externally, you know, how strong is your
system by, of course, playing against, you know, the world's strongest players at those games.
So it's so good for so many reasons. And it's also very efficient to run potentially millions of
simulations in parallel on the cloud. So I think there's a huge reason why we were so successful
back in, you know, starting out 2010, how come we were able to progress so quickly because
we'd utilize games. And, you know, at the beginning of DeepMind, we also hired some amazing
game engineers who I knew from my previous lives in the games industry. And that helped the bootstraps
very quickly. And plus it's somehow super compelling, almost at a philosophical level of man versus
machine, over, over chessboard or a go board. And especially given that the entire history of AI
is defined by people saying it's going to be impossible to make a machine that beats a human being
in chess. And then once that happened, people were certain when I was coming up in AI that go
is not a game that can be solved because of the combinatorial complexity. It's just two. It's,
it's, you know, no matter how much more is law you have, compute is just never going to be able
to crack the game of go. And so then there's something compelling about facing sort of taking on
the impossibility of that task from the AI researcher perspective, engineer perspective. And then
as a human being, just observing this whole thing, your beliefs about where your thought was
impossible, being broken apart, it's, it's humbling to realize we're not as smart as we thought.
It's humbling to realize that the things we think are impossible now perhaps will be done
in the future. There's something really powerful about a game, AI system,
being a human being in a game that drives that message home for like millions, billions of people,
especially in the case of Go. Sure. Well, look, I think it's, I mean, it has been a fascinating journey.
And especially as I think about it from, I can understand it from both sides, both as the AI,
you know, creators of the AI, but also as a games player originally. So, you know, it was a,
it was a really interesting, you know, I mean, it was, it was a fantastic, but also somewhat bittersweet
moment. The alpha go match for me, seeing that and, and, and being obviously heavily, heavily
involved in that. But, you know, as you say, chess has been the, I mean, Kasparov, I think,
rightly called it the Drosophila of intelligence, right? So it's sort of, I love that phrase. And
I think he's right because chess has been hand in hand with AI from the beginning of the,
the whole field, right? So I think every AI practitioner starting with cheering in
Claude Shannon and all those, the sort of forefathers of the field, tried their hand at writing
a chess program. I've got original audition of Claude Shannon's first chess program. I think
it was 1949, the original sort of paper. And they all did that and cheering famously
wrote a chess program that, but all the computers around them were obviously too slow to run it.
So he had to run, he had to be the computer, right? So he literally, I think, spent two or
three days running his own program by hand with pencil and paper and playing, playing a friend of his
with his chess program. So, of course, deep blue was a huge moment, beating Kasparov.
But actually, when that happened, I remember that very, very vividly, of course, because it was,
you know, chess and computers and AI, all the things I loved and I was at college at the time.
But I remember coming away from that, being more impressed by Kasparov's mind than I was by
deep blue because here was Kasparov with his human mind. Not only could he play chess more or less
to the same level as this brute of a calculation machine, but of course Kasparov can do everything
else humans can do, right? A bike, talk many languages, do politics, all the rest of the amazing
things that Kasparov does. And so with the same brain and yet deep blue, brilliant as it was at chess,
it'd been hand coded for chess and actually had distilled the knowledge of chess grand masters
into into a cool program, but it couldn't do anything else. Like it couldn't even play a
strictly simpler game like Tic Tac Toe. So, something to me was missing from intelligence from
that system that we would regard as intelligence. And I think it was this idea of generality
and also learning. And that's what we should try to do with AlphaGo. Yeah, with AlphaGo and Alpha0,
Mu0, and then got all the things that we'll get into some parts of. There's just a fascinating
trajectory here. But let's just stick on chess briefly. On the human side of chess, you've proposed
that from a game design perspective, the thing that makes chess compelling as a game is that
there's a creative tension between a bishop and the knight. Can you explain this? First of all,
it's really interesting to think about what makes a game compelling. It makes it stick across centuries.
Yeah, I was sort of thinking about this and actually a lot of even amazing chess players don't
think about it necessarily from a game's designer point of view. So it's with my game design hat on
that I was thinking about this. Why is chess so compelling? And I think a critical reason is the
dynamicness of the different kind of chess positions you can have, whether they're closed or
open and other things, comes from the bishop and the knight. So if you think about how different
the capabilities of the bishop and knight are in terms of the way they move and then somehow
chess has evolved to balance those two capabilities more or less equally. So they're both roughly
worth three points each. So you think that dynamics is always there and then the rest of the rules
are kind of trying to stabilize the game. Well, maybe. I mean, it's sort of, I don't know,
as chicken and egg situation probably both came together, but the fact that it's got to this
beautiful equilibrium where you can have the bishop and knight. They're so different in power,
but so equal in value across the set of the universe of all positions, somehow they've been
balanced by humanity over hundreds of years. I think gives the game the creative tension
that you can swap the bishop and knights for a bishop for a knight and they're more or less
the worth the same, but now you aim for a different type of position. If you have the knight, you want
a closed position. If you have the bishop, you want an open position. So I think that creates a
lot of the creative tension in chess. So some kind of controlled creative tension. From an AI
perspective, do you think AI systems could venture design games that are optimally compelling to humans?
Well, that's an interesting question. Sometimes I get asked about AI and creativity and this
and the way I answer that is relevant to that question, which is that I think they're different levels
of creativity, one could say. So I think if we define creativity as coming up with something original,
right, that's useful for a purpose, then I think the kind of lowest level of creativity is like an
interpolation, so an averaging of all the examples you see. So maybe very basic AI system could say
you could have that. So you show it millions of pictures of cats and then you say give me an average
looking cat, right, generate me an average looking cat. I would call that interpolation. Then there's
extrapolation, which something like AlphaGo showed. So AlphaGo played millions of games of Go against
itself and then it came up with brilliant new ideas like move 37 in game two, brilliant motif
strategies in Go that no humans had ever thought of, even though we've played it for thousands of
years and professionally for hundreds of years. So that I call that extrapolation. But then that's
still there's still a level above that, which is, you know, you could call out of the box thinking
or true innovation, which is could you invent Go, right? Could you invent chess and not just come
up with a brilliant chess move or brilliant Go move, but can you can you actually invent chess
or something as good as chess or go? And I think one day AI could, but the what's missing is how would
you even specify that task to a program right now? And the way I would do it if if I was
best to telling a human to do it or games designer, a human game designer to do it is I would say
something like Go, I would say come up with a game that only takes five minutes to learn,
which Go does because it's got simple rules, but many lifetimes to master, right? Or impossible
to master in one lifetime because so deep and so complex. And then it's aesthetically beautiful
and also it can be completed in three or four hours of gameplay time, which is, you know,
useful for our, you know, in a human day. And so you might specify these side of high-level
concepts like that. And then, you know, with that and maybe a few other things, one could imagine
that Go satisfies those constraints. But the problem is is that we're not able to specify abstract
notions like that, high-level abstract notions like that yet to our AI systems. And I think
there's still something missing there in terms of high-level concepts or abstractions that they
truly understand and they're, you know, combinable and compositional. So for the moment,
I think AI is capable of doing interpolation and extrapolation, but not true invention.
So coming up with rulesets and optimizing with complicated objectives around those rulesets,
we can't currently do. But you could take a specific rule set and then run a kind of self-play
experiment to see how long just observe how an AI system from scratch learns how long is that
journey of learning. And maybe if it satisfies some of those other things you mentioned in terms
of quickness to learn so on and you could see a long journey to master for even an AI system,
then you could say that this is a promising game. But it would be nice to do almost like
alpha codes or programming rules. So generating rules that kind of that automate even that part
of the generation of rules. So I have thought about systems actually that I think would be amazing
in for a game's designer. If you could have a system that takes your game, plays it tens of
millions of times, maybe overnight, and then self-balances the rules better. So it tweaks the rules
and maybe the equations and the parameters so that the game is more balanced, the units in the game
or some of the rules could be tweaked. So it's a bit of like a giving a base set and then
allowing Monte Carlo treaser or something like that to sort of explore it. And I think that would
be super powerful tool actually for balancing, auto balancing a game, which usually takes thousands
of hours from hundreds of games, human games testers normally to to balance one game like
StarCraft, which is, you know, Blizzard are amazing at balancing their games, but it takes them
years and years and years. So one could imagine at some point when this stuff becomes
efficient enough to, you know, you might better do that like overnight.
Do you think a game that is optimal design by an AI system would look very much like a planet
Earth? So maybe, maybe it's only the sort of game I would love to make is, and I've tried,
you know, in my, in my games career, the games design career, you know, my first big game was
designing a theme park and amusement park, then with games like Republic, I tried to, you know,
have games where we design whole cities and, and allow you to play in. So, and of course,
people like Will Wright have written games like Sim Earth, trying to simulate the whole of Earth,
pretty tricky, but I say. Sim Earth, I haven't actually played that one. So what is it? Does
it incorporate a revolution? Yeah, it has a revolution and it sort of, it tries to,
it sort of treats it as an entire biosphere, but from quite high level.
So, it'd be nice to be able to sort of zoom in, zoom out. Exactly. Exactly. So obviously,
it couldn't do that. That was in the night. I think he wrote that in the 90s. So it couldn't,
you know, it wasn't, it wasn't able to do that. But that, that would be, obviously,
the ultimate sandbox game, of course. On that topic, do you think we're living in a simulation?
Yes. Well, so, okay. So I'm going to jump around from the absurdly philosophical to the
detective. Sure. Sure. Very, very happy to. So I think my answer to that question is a little
bit complex because there is simulation theory, which obviously Nick Bostrom I think famously
first proposed. And I don't quite believe it in that sense. So in the, in the sense that
are we in some sort of computer game or have our descendants somehow recreated
Earth in the, you know, 21st century and some for some kind of experimental reason.
I think that, but I do think that we that that we might be that the best way to understand physics
and the universe is from a computational perspective. So understanding it as an information
universe and actually information being the most fundamental unit of reality rather than matter
or energy. So physicists would say, you know, matter or energy, you know, E equals MC squared. These
are the things that are the fundamentals of the universe. I'd actually say information,
which of course itself can be, can specify energy or matter, right? Matter is actually just,
you know, we're, we're just out the way our bodies and the molecules in our body are arranged
as information. So I think information may be the most fundamental way to describe the universe
and therefore you could say we're in some sort of simulation because of that. But I don't, I do,
I'm not, I'm not really subscriber to the idea that, you know, these are sort of throw away
billions of simulations around. I think this is actually very critical and possibly unique
this simulation. Yes, but and you just mean treating the universe as a computer that's processing
and modifying information is a good way to solve the problems of physics of chemistry of biology
and perhaps of humanity and so on. Yes, I think understanding physics in terms of information
theory might be the best way to really understand what's going on here.
Yeah. From our understanding of a universal term machine, from our understanding of a computer,
do you think there's something outside of the capabilities of a computer that is present in
our universe? You have a disagreement with Roger Penroval. Yes. The nature of consciousness,
he thinks that consciousness is more than just a computation. Do you think all of it,
the whole shebang can be, can be a computation? Yeah, I've had many fascinating debates
with Roger Penro's and obviously he's famously and I read, you know, Empress in the New Mind and
and his books, his classical books and they were pretty influential in the 90s and he believes
that there's something more, something quantum that is needed to explain consciousness in the brain.
I think of what we're doing actually at DeepMind and what my career is being, we're almost like
Turing's champion, so we are pushing Turing machines or classical computation to the limits. What are
the limits of what classical computing can do? Now, and at the same time, I've also studied neuroscience
to see, and that's why I did my PhD in, was to see also to look at, you know, is there anything
quantum in the brain from a neuroscience or biological perspective? And so far, I think most
neuroscientists and most mainstream biologists and neuroscientists would say there's no evidence of
any quantum systems or effects in the brain. As far as we can see, it can be mostly explained by
classical, classical theories. So, and then so there's sort of the search from the biology side
and then at the same time, there's the raising of the water at the bar from what classical Turing
machines can do and including our new AI systems. And as you alluded to earlier, you know, I think AI,
especially in the last decade plus, has been a continual story now, surprising events and
surprising successes, knocking over one theory after another, what was thought to be impossible,
you know, from go to protein folding and so on. And so I think I would be very hesitant to bet
against how far the universal Turing machine and classical computation paradigm can go. And my
betting would be that all of certainly what's going on in our brain can probably be mimicked or
approximated on a classical machine, not requiring something metaphysical or quantum.
And we'll get there with some of the work with Alpha Fold, which I think begins the journey of
modeling this beautiful and complex world of biology. So you think all the magic of the human
mind comes from this just a few pounds of mush of biological computational mush that's akin
to some of the neural networks, not directly, but in spirit that deep mind has been working with.
Well, look, I think it's, you say it's a few, you know, of course, this is the, I think,
the biggest miracle of the universe is that it is just a few pounds of mush in our skulls. And yet
it's also our brains and the most complex objects in that we know of in the universe. So there's
something profoundly beautiful and amazing about our brains. And I think that it's an incredibly
incredible efficient machine and it's, you know, phenomenon basically. And I think that building AI,
one of the reasons I want to build AI and I've always wanted to is I think by building an
intelligent artifact like AI and then comparing it to the human mind, that will help us unlock
the uniqueness and the true secrets of the mind that we've always wondered about since the dawn
of history, like consciousness, dreaming, creativity, emotions, what are all these things, right?
We've we've wondered about them since since the dawn of humanity. And I think one of the reasons
and you know, I love philosophy and philosophy of mind is we found it difficult is there haven't
been the tools for us to really other than introspection to from very clever people in in history,
very clever philosophers, to really investigate this scientifically. But now suddenly we have a
polethril of tools. Firstly, we have all of the neuroscience tools, FMI machines, single cell
recording, all of this stuff. But we also have the ability computers and AI to build intelligent
systems. So I think that, you know, I think it is amazing what the human mind does. And and I'm kind
of in awe of it really. And I think it's amazing that without human minds, we're able to build
things like computers and actually even, you know, think and investigate about these questions.
I think that's also testament to the human mind. Yeah. The universe built the human mind that now
is building computers that help us understand both the universe and our own human mind. That's right.
This is like lid. I mean, I think that's one we, you know, one could say we are maybe we're the
mechanism by which the universe is going to try and understand itself. Yeah. It's beautiful.
So let's let's go to the basic building blocks of biology that I think is another angle
which you can start to understand the human mind, the human body, which is quite fascinating,
which is from the basic building blocks, start to simulate, start to model how from those
building blocks you can construct bigger and bigger, more complex systems, maybe one day the
entirety of the human biology. So here's another problem that thought to be impossible to solve,
which is protein folding and alpha fold or specific alpha fold two did just that. It's solved
protein folding. I think it's one of the biggest breakthroughs, certainly in the history of
structural biology, but in general, in science, maybe from a high level, what is it and how does
it work? And then we can ask some fascinating sure questions after sure. So maybe I to explain
it to people not familiar with protein folding is, you know, I first of all explain proteins,
which is, you know, proteins are essential to all life. Every function in your body depends
on proteins. Sometimes they call the workhorses of biology. And if you look into them and I,
you know, obviously as part of alpha fold, I've been researching proteins and and and structural
biology for the last few years, you know, they're amazing little bio nanomachines proteins,
they're incredible. If you actually watch little videos of how they work, animations of how they
work. And proteins are specified by their genetic sequence, called their amino acid sequence.
So you can think it with their genetic makeup. And then in the body, in nature, they when they
fold up into a 3D structure. So you can think of it as a string of beads and then they fold up
into a ball. Now the key thing is you want to know what that 3D structure is because the structure,
the 3D structure of a protein is what helps to determine what does it do, the function it does
in your body. And also if you're interested in drug drugs or disease, you need to understand that
3D structure because if you want to target something with a drug compound or about to block
something the protein is doing, you need to understand where it's going to bind on the surface of
the protein. So obviously, in order to do that, you need to understand the 3D structure.
So the structure is mapped to the function? The structure is mapped to the function and the
structure is obviously somehow specified by the amino acid sequence. And that's the, in
instance, the protein folding problem is, can you just from the amino acid sequence, the one
dimensional string of letters, can you immediately computationally predict the 3D structure?
Right. And this has been a grand challenge in biology for over 50 years. So I think it was first
articulated by Christian and Fienzen, a Nobel Prize winner in 1972 as part of his Nobel Prize
winning lecture. And he just speculated this should be possible to go from the amino acid sequence to
the 3D structure. But he didn't say how. So I've been described to me as equivalent to Fermat's
last theorem, but for biology. You should, as somebody that very well might win the Nobel
Prize in the future, but outside of that, you should do more of that kind of thing. In the margins,
just put random things, they'll take like 200 years to solve. Set people off at 200 years.
Should be possible. Exactly. And just don't give any attention. Exactly. I think everyone's
exactly should be, I'll have to remember that for future. So yeah, so he set off, you know,
with this one very way remark, just like Fermat, you know, he, he set off this whole 50-age
field, really, of computation of biology. And they had, you know, they got stuck. They hadn't
really got very far with doing this. And until now, until AlphaFull came along, this is done
experimentally, right, very painstakingly. So the rule of thumb is, and you have to crystallize
the protein, which is really difficult. Some proteins can't be crystallized like membrane proteins.
And then you have to use very expensive electron microscopes or x-ray crystallography machines,
really painstaking work to get the 3D structure and visualize the 3D structure.
So the rule of thumb in, in, in experimental biology is that it takes one PhD student,
their entire PhD to do one protein. And with AlphaFull 2, we were able to predict the 3D
structure in a matter of seconds. And so we were, you know, over Christmas, we did the whole human
proteome, or every protein in the human body, or 20,000 proteins. So the human proteomes,
like the equivalent of the human genome, but on protein space. And, and sort of revolutionize
really what a structural biologists can do. Because now, they don't have to worry about these painstaking
experimentals, you know, should they put all of that effort in or not, they can almost just look
up the structure of their proteins like a Google search. And so there's a data set on which it's
trained and how to map this amino acid season. First of all, it's incredible that approaching
this little chemical computer is able to do that computation itself in some kind of distributed
way and do it very quickly. That's a weird thing. And they evolved that way because, you know,
in the beginning, I mean, that's a great invention, just the protein itself.
Yes. I mean, and then there's, I think, probably a history of, like, they evolved
to have many of these proteins. And those proteins figure out how to be computers themselves.
So in such a way that you can create structures that can interact in complex areas with each other,
in order to form high-level functions. I mean, it's a weird system that they figured it out.
Well, for sure. I mean, we, you know, maybe we should talk about the origins of life, too,
but proteins themselves, I think, are magical and incredible, as I said, little bio-nana machines.
And actually, Leventhal, who is another scientist, a contemporary of Amphinson,
he coined this Leventhal, what became known as Leventhal's paradox, which is exactly what you're
saying. He calculated roughly a protein, an average protein, which is maybe 2,000 amino acids
based as long, is, is, can fold in maybe 10 to the power 300 different conformations.
So there's 10 to the power 300 different ways that protein could fold up. And yet somehow,
in nature, physics solves this, solves this in a matter of milliseconds. So proteins fold up in
your body, sometimes in fractions of a second. So physics is somehow solving that search problem.
And just to be clear, in many of these cases, maybe correctly if I'm wrong, there's often a unique
way for that sequence to form itself. So among that huge number of possibilities, it figures out
a way, how to stably, in some cases, there might be a dysfunction, which leads to a lot of the
disorders and stuff like that. But yes, most of the time it's a unique mapping and that unique
mapping is not obvious. No, exactly. Which is what the problem is. Exactly. So there's a unique
mapping usually in a healthy, if it's healthy. And as you say in disease, so for example,
Alzheimer's, one conjecture is that it's because of a misfolder protein, a protein that folds in
the wrong way, amyloid beta protein. And then because it folds in the wrong way, it gets tangled
up in your neurons. So it's super important to understand both healthy functioning and also
disease is to understand what these things are doing and how they're structuring. Of course,
the next step is sometimes proteins change shape when they interact with something. So they're not
just static necessarily in biology. Maybe you can give some interesting beautiful things to you
about these early days of alpha fold of of solving this problem because unlike games,
this is real physical systems that are less amenable to self-play type of mechanisms.
The size of the data set is smaller than you might otherwise like. You have to be very clever
about certain things. Is there something you could speak to what was very hard to solve and
what are some beautiful aspects about the solution? I would say alpha fold is the most complex and
also probably most meaningful system we've built so far. So it's been an amazing time actually in
the last two, three years to see that come through because as we talked about earlier, games is what
we started on, building things like alpha-go and alpha-zero. But really, the ultimate goal was to
not just to crack games, it was just to build, use them to bootstrap general learning systems,
we could then apply to real world challenges. Specifically, my passion is scientific challenges
like protein folding. And then alpha fold, of course, is our first big proof point of that.
And so in terms of the data and the amount of innovations that had to go into it,
it was more than 30 different component algorithms needed to be put together to crack the protein
folding. I think some of the big innovations were the kind of building in some hard coded constraints
around physics and evolutionary biology to constrain sort of things like the bond angles
in the protein and things like that, but not to impact the learning system. So still allowing
the system to be able to learn the physics itself from the examples that we had. And the
examples, as you say, they're only about 150,000 proteins, even after 40 years of experimental biology,
only around 150,000 proteins have been, the structures have been found out about. So that was our
training set, which is much less than normally we would like to use, but using various tricks,
things like self distillation. So actually using alpha fold predictions, some of the best predictions
that it thought was highly confident in, we put them back into the training set, right, to make the
training set bigger. That was critical to alpha fold working. So there was actually a huge number
of different innovations like that that were required to ultimately crack the problem. Alpha
fold one, what it produced was a histogram, so a kind of a matrix of the pairwise distances
between all of the molecules in the protein. And then there had to be a separate optimization
process to create the 3D structure. And what we did for alpha fold two is make it truly end-to-end.
So we went straight from the amino acid sequence of bases to the 3D structure directly without
going through this intermediate step. And in machine learning, what we've always found is that
the more end-to-end you can make it, the better the system. And it's probably because
we, you know, in the end, the system's better at learning what the constraints are than we are
as the human designers of specifying it. So anytime you can let it flow end-to-end and actually
just generate what it is you're really looking for. In this case, the 3D structure, you're better
off than having this intermediate step, which you then have to handcraft the next step for.
So it's better to let the gradients and the learning flow all the way through the system
from the end point, the end output you want to the inputs. So that's a good way to start
on a new problem. Handcraft, a bunch of stuff, add a bunch of manual constraints with a small
end-to-end learning piece or a small learning piece and grow that learning piece until it
consumes the whole thing. That's right. And so you can also see, you know, this is a bit of a method
we've developed over doing many sort of successful outfits. We call them Alpha X projects, right?
And the easiest way to see that is the evolution of Alpha Go to Alpha Zero. So Alpha Go was a learning
system, but it was specifically trained to only play Go, right? So and what we wanted to do in
with first version of Alpha Go is just get to world champion performance no matter how we did it,
right? And then, and then of course Alpha Go Zero, we remove the need to use human games as a
starting point, right? So it could just play against itself from random starting point from
the beginning. So that removed the need for human knowledge about Go. And then finally Alpha Zero
then generalized it so that any things we had in there, the system, including things like symmetry
of the Go board, were removed. So that Alpha Zero could play from scratch any two-player game,
and then Mu Zero, which is the final, that our latest version of that set of things,
was then extending it so that you didn't even have to give it the rules of the game. It would
learn that for itself. So it could also deal with computer games as well as board games.
So that line of Alpha Go, Alpha Go Zero, Mu Zero, that's the full trajectory of what you can take from
imitation learning to full self-supervised learning. Yeah. Exactly. And learning, learning the entire
structure of the environment you put in from scratch, right? And bootstrapping it through self-play
yourself. But the thing is, it would have been impossible, I think, or very hard for us to build
Alpha Zero or Mu Zero first out of the box. Even psychologically, because you have to
believe in yourself for a very long time, you're constantly dealing with doubt, because a lot of
people say that it's impossible. Exactly. So it was hard enough just to do Go as you were saying,
everyone thought that was impossible, or at least a decade away from when we, when we did it in back
in 2015, 2014, 2016. And so, yes, it would have been psychologically probably very difficult,
as well as the fact that, of course, we learned a lot by building Alpha Go first.
Right? So I think this is why I call AI an engineering science. It's one of the most
fascinating science disciplines, but it's also an engineering science in the sense that,
unlike natural sciences, the phenomenon you're studying doesn't exist out in nature. You have to
build it first. So you have to build the artifact first, and then you can study how and pull it apart
and how it works. This is tough to ask you this question because you probably will say it's everything,
but let's try, let's try to think through this, because you're in a very interesting position,
where deep mind is a place of some of the most brilliant ideas in the history of AI,
but it's also a place of brilliant engineering. So how much of solving intelligence, this big goal
for deep mind? How much of it is science? How much is engineering? So how much is the algorithms?
How much is the data? How much is the hardware compute infrastructure? How much is it the software
compute infrastructure? What else is there? How much is the human infrastructure?
And just the humans interacting in certain kinds of ways, in all the space of all those ideas,
how much is maybe philosophy? What's the key? If you were to look back, if we go forward
to 100 years and look back, what was the key thing that solved intelligence? Is that ideas?
I think it's a combination. I first of all, of course, it's a combination of all those things,
but the ratios of them changed over time. So even in the last 12 years, we started deep
mind in 2010, which is hard to imagine now, because 2010, it's only 12 short years ago,
but nobody was talking about AI. I don't know if you remember back to your MIT days. No one was
talking about it. I did a post-doc at MIT back around then, and it was sort of thought of as,
well, look, we know AI doesn't work. We tried this hard in the 90s at places like MIT,
mostly losing, using logic systems and old-fashioned sort of good old-fashioned AI. We would call
it now. People like Minsky and Patrick Winston, and you know all these characters, right? And
used to debate a few of them, and they used to think I was mad, thinking about that some new
advance could be done with learning systems. I was actually pleased to hear that, because at
least you know you're on a unique track at that point, right? Even if all of your professors
are telling you you're mad. And of course, in industry, we couldn't get, you know,
it was difficult to get two cents together, and which is hard to imagine now as well,
given that it's the biggest sort of buzzword in VCs and fundraising's easy and all these kind
of things today. So back in 2010, it was very difficult. And the reason we started then,
and Shane and I used to discuss what were the sort of founding tenants of DeepMind,
and it was various things. One was algorithmic advances. So Deep Learning, you know, Jeff Hinton and
Coa just had just sort of invented that in academia, but no one in industry knew about it. We
love reinforcement learning. We thought that could be scaled up, but also understanding about
the human brain had advanced quite a lot in the decade prior with FMRI machines and other things.
So we could get some good hints about architectures and algorithms and sort of representations maybe
that the brain uses. So as at a systems level, not at a implementation level. And then the other
big things were compute and GPUs, right? So we could see a compute was going to be really useful
and it got to a place where it become commoditized mostly through the games industry,
and that could be taken advantage of. And then the final thing was also mathematical and theoretical
definitions of intelligence. So things like AIXI, which Shane worked on with his supervisor,
Marcus Huto, which is sort of theoretical proof really of universal intelligence, which is actually
a reinforcement learning system in the limit. I mean, it seems infinite compute and infinite
memory in the way, you know, like a Turing machine proof. But I was also waiting to see something
like that too, to, you know, like Turing machines and computation theory that people like Turing
and Shannon came up with, underpins modern computer science. You know, I was waiting for a theory
like that to sort of underpin a GI research. So when I met Shane and saw he was working on something
like that, you know, that to me was a sort of final piece of the jigsaw. So in the early days,
I would say that ideas were the most important, you know, for us, it was deeply enforcement learning,
scaling up deep learning. Of course, we've seen transformers. So huge leaps, I would say, you know,
three or four from, if you think from 2010 till now, huge evolution, things like AlphaGo.
And maybe there's a few more still needed. But as we get closer to AI, a GI, I think engineering
becomes more and more important and data because scale and of course, the recent, you know, results
of GPT-3 and all the big language models and large models, including our ones, has shown that
scale is and large models are clearly going to be a necessary, but perhaps not sufficient part of
an AGI solution. And throughout that, like you said, and I'd like to give you a big thank you,
you're one of the pioneers in this is sticking by ideas like reinforcement learning that this can
actually work, given actually limited success in the past, and also, which we still don't know,
but proudly having the best researchers in the world and talking about solving intelligence.
So talking about whatever you call it, AGI or something like this, that speaking of MIT,
that's just something that you wouldn't bring up. Not maybe you did in like 40, 50 years ago,
but that was AI was a place where you do tinkering, very small scale, not very ambitious projects,
and maybe the biggest ambitious projects were in the space of robotics and doing like the DARPA
challenge, but the task of solving intelligence and believing you can. That's really,
really powerful. So in order for engineering to do its work, to have great engineers build great
systems, you have to have that belief that threads throughout the whole thing that you can actually
solve some of these impossible challenges. Yeah, that's right. And back in 2010, our mission
statement and still is today, it was used to be solving step one, solve intelligence,
step two, use it to solve everything else. So if you can imagine pitching that to a VC in 2010,
you know, the kind of looks we got, we managed to, you know, find a few kooky people to back us,
but it was, it was tricky. And I got to the point where we wouldn't mention it to any of our
professors, because they were just I-roll and think we, you know, committed career suicide. And,
and, and, you know, so it was, there's a lot of things that we had to do, but we always believed it.
And one reason, you know, by the way, one reason we, I believe, I've always believed in reinforcement
learning is that that, if you look at neuroscience, that is the way that the, you know,
primate brain learns. One of the main mechanisms is the dopamine system,
implement some form of TD learning, as very famous result in the late 90s, where they saw this in
monkeys. And, and as, you know, probably getting prediction error. So, you know, again, in the
limit, this is, this is what I think you can use neuroscience for is, is, you know, any,
and mathematics. You, when you're, when you're doing something as ambitious as trying to solve
intelligence, and you're, you know, it's blue sky research, no one knows how to do it. You, you,
you need to use any evidence or any source of information you can to help guide you in the right
direction, or give you confidence you're going in the right direction. So, so that, that was one
reason we pushed so hard on that. And that's, and it's just going back to your early question
about organization. The other big thing that I think we innovated with at DeepMind to encourage
invention and, and, and, and innovation was the multidisciplinary organization we built,
and we still have today. So, DeepMind originally was a confluence of the, of the most cutting
edge knowledge in neuroscience with machine learning, engineering, and mathematics, right,
and, and gaming. And then since then we've built that out even further. So, we have philosophers
here and, and, by, you know, ethicists, but also other types of scientists, physicists, and so on.
And that's what brings together. I tried to build a sort of, um, new type of Bell labs,
but in its golden era, right? And, and a new expression of that, um, to try and, uh, foster
this incredible sort of innovation machine. So, talking about the humans in the machine,
DeepMind itself is a learning machine with a lot of amazing human minds in it, um, coming together
to try and build these, uh, learning systems. If we return to the big ambitious dream of
AlphaFold, that maybe the early steps, uh, very long journey in, um, in biology,
do you think the same kind of approach can use to predict the structure and function of
more complex biological systems? So, multi-protein interaction, and then, I mean, you can go out from
there. Yeah. Just simulating bigger and bigger systems that eventually simulate something like
the human brain or the human body, just the big mush, the mess of the beautiful resilient
mess of biology. Do you see that as a long-term vision? I do. And I think, um, you know,
if you think about what are the things, top things I wanted to apply AI to, once we had powerful
enough systems, biology and curing diseases and understanding biology, uh, was right up there,
you know, top of my list. That's one of the reasons I personally pushed that myself and with AlphaFold.
But I think AlphaFold, uh, amazing as it is, is just the beginning, um, and, and, and I hope it's
an evidence of, uh, what could be done with computational methods. So, um, you know, AlphaFold solved
this, this huge problem of, of the structure of proteins, but biology is dynamic. So really,
what I imagine from here, and we're working on all these things now, is protein protein interaction,
uh, protein ligand binding. So, uh, reacting with molecules, um, then you want to get built up
to pathways and then pinch eventually a virtual cell. That's my dream, uh, maybe in the next 10
years. And I've been talking actually to a lot of biologists, friends of mine, Paul Nurse, who runs
the quick institute, amazing biologist, nervous prize-winning biologists. We've been discussing for
20 years now, virtual cells. Could you build a virtual simulation of a cell? And if you could,
that would be incredible for biology and disease discovery because you could do loads of experiments
on the virtual cell and then only at the last stage validate it in the wet lab. So you could,
you know, that in terms of the search space of discovering new drugs, you know, takes 10 years
roughly to go from, uh, to, to go from a, you know, identifying a target to, uh, having a drug
candidate. Um, maybe that could be shortened to, you know, by an order of magnitude with, if you could
do most of that, that, that work in silico. So in order to get to a virtual cell, we have to build up,
uh, understanding of different parts of biology and the interactions. And, and, um, so we, you know,
we, every, every few years we talk about this with, we, I talked about this with Paul, and then
finally, last year after AlphaFold, I said, now's the time we can finally go for it. And, and AlphaFold
was the first proof point that this might be possible. Uh, and he's very exciting. We have some
collaborations with his, with his lab, and they're just across the road actually from us,
as a, you know, wonderful being here in Kings Cross with the quick institute across the road.
And, um, and I think the next steps, you know, I think there's going to be some amazing
advances in biology built on top of things like AlphaFold. Uh, we're already seeing that with
the community doing that after we've open sourced it and released it. Um, and, uh, you know,
I often, I often say that I think, uh, if you think of, uh, mathematics is the perfect
description language for physics. Uh, I think AI might be end up being the perfect description
language for biology because, um, biology is so messy, it's so emergent, so dynamic and complex.
Um, I think I find it very hard to believe we'll ever get to something as elegant as Newton's
laws of motions to describe a cell, right? It's just too complicated. Um, so I think AI is the
right tool for that. So you have to, um, you have to start at the basic building blocks
and use AI to run the simulation for how those building blocks. So have a very strong way to
do prediction of what given these building blocks, what kind of biology, how the, the function
and the evolution of that biological system. It's almost like a cellular automata. You have to run,
you can't analyze it from a high level. You have to take the basic ingredients, figure out the
rules and let it run. But in this case, the rules are very difficult to figure out. Yes,
yes. Learn them. That's exactly it. So it's, the biology is too complicated to figure out the
rules. It's, it's too emergent, too dynamic, say, compared to a physics system, like the motion
of a planet, right? And, and so you have to learn the rules. And that's exactly the type of systems
that we're building. So you, you mentioned you've open sourced Alpha Fold and even the data involved
to me personally, also really happy and a big thank you for open sourcing, Majoko,
the physics simulation engine that's, um, that's often used for robotics research and so on.
So I think that's a pretty gangster move. Uh, so what, what's the, what's, I mean, this, uh,
very few companies or people do that kind of thing. What's the philosophy behind that?
You know, it's a case by case basis. And in both those cases, we felt that was the maximum benefit
to humanity to do that. And, and the scientific community, in one case, the robotics, uh, physics
community with Majoko. So we purchased it. Open four. Yes, we purchased it for the express
principle to open sourced. So, um, so, uh, you know, I hope people appreciate that. It's great
to hear that, that you do. And then the second thing was, and mostly we did it because the person
building it, who's, uh, uh, would not able, was not able to cope with supporting it anymore,
because it was, it got too big for him. It's amazing professor, uh, who, who built it in the first
place. So we helped him out with that. And then with Alpha Fold is even bigger, I would say.
And I think in that case, we decided that there were so many downstream applications of Alpha
Fold, um, that we couldn't possibly even imagine what they all were. So the best way to accelerate,
drug discovery and also fundamental research would be to, to, um, give all that data away and,
and, and the, and the, and the system itself. Um, you know, it's been so gratifying to see what
people have done that within just one year, which is a short amount of time in science. And, uh,
it's been used by over 500,000 researchers have used it. We think that's almost every
biologist in the world. I think there's roughly 500,000 biologists in the world, professional
biologists have used it to, to look at their, um, proteins of interest. Um, we see an amazing
fundamental research done. So, uh, a couple of weeks ago, front cover, there was a whole special
issue of science, including the front cover, which had the nuclear poor complex on it, which is
one of the biggest proteins in the body, the nuclear poor complexes, a protein that governs
all the nutrients going in and out of your cell nucleus. So they're, they're like,
they will halt gateways that open and close to let things go in and out of your cell nucleus.
So they're really important. Um, but they're huge because they're massive doughnut rings,
shaped things. And they've been looking to try and figure out that structure for decades.
And they have lots of, you know, experimental data, but it's too low resolution. There's bits
missing. And they were able to, like a giant Lego jigsaw puzzle, use alpha fold predictions
plus experimental data and combined those two independent sources of information, uh,
actually four different groups around the world were able to put it together. The set, uh,
more or less simultaneously using alpha fold predictions. So that's been amazing to see.
And pretty much every farmer company, every drug company executive I spoken to has said that
their teams are using alpha fold to accelerate whatever drugs, uh, uh, uh, they're, they're trying
to discover. So I think the knock on effect has been enormous in terms of, uh, uh, the impact
that alpha fold has made. And it's probably bringing in, it's creating biologists. It's bringing
more people into the field, um, but both on the excitement and both on the technical skills involved
in, um, it's almost like, uh, a gateway drug to biology. Yes, it is. And the end goal,
computational people involved too, hopefully. And, and I think for us, you know, the next stage,
as I said, you know, in future, we have to have other considerations too. We're building on top
of alpha fold and these other ideas I discussed with you about protein, protein interactions and,
and genomics and other things. And not everything will be open so some of it will,
we'll do commercially because that will be the best way to actually get the most resources and
impact behind it. In other ways, some other projects will do non-profit style. Um, and also,
we have to consider for future things as well, safety and ethics as well, like, but, you know,
synthetic biology, there are, you know, there is dual use. And we have to think about that as well
with alpha fold. We, you know, we consulted with 30 different bioethicists and, and other people
expert in this field to make sure it was safe before, um, we released it. So there'll be other
considerations in future. But for right now, you know, I think alpha fold is a kind of a gift from
us to, to, to the scientific community. So I'm pretty sure that something like alpha fold
would be part of Nobel prizes in the future. But us humans, of course, are horrible with
credit assignment. So we'll, of course, give it to the humans. Do you think there will be a day
when AI system can't be denied that it earned that Nobel prize? Do you think we'll see then
21st century? It depends what type of AI's we end up building, right? Whether they're, um,
you know, goal seeking agents who specifies the goals, uh, who comes up with the hypotheses,
who, you know, who determines which problems to tackle, right? So I think it's about it.
Announcement. Yes, it's an out of the results exactly as part of it. Um, so I think right now, of course,
it's, it's, it's, it's, it's amazing human ingenuity that's behind these systems. And then the
system, in my opinion, is just a tool, you know, be a bit like saying with Galileo and his telescope,
you know, the ingenuity that the credits should go to the telescope. I mean, it's clearly Galileo
building the tool, which he then uses. So I still see that in the same way today, even though
these tools learn for themselves, um, there, I think of, I think of things like Alpha Fold and
that the things we're building as the ultimate tools for science and for, for acquiring new knowledge
to help us as scientists acquire new knowledge. I think one day they will come a point where
an AI system may solve or come up with something like general relativity off its own bat,
not just by averaging everything on the internet or averaging everything on PubMed,
although that will be interesting to see what that would come up with. Um, so that to me is a bit
like our earlier debate about creativity, you know, inventing go rather than just coming up with a
good go move. And, um, so I think, uh, solving, I think to, to, you know, if we wanted to give it the
credit of like a Nobel type of thing, then it would need to invent go, uh, and sort of invent that
new conjecture out of the blue, um, rather than being specified by the, the, the human scientists or
the human creators. So I think right now that's, it's definitely just a tool. Although it is
interesting how far you get by averaging everything on the internet, like you said, because,
you know, a lot of people do see science as you're always standing on the shoulders of giants.
And the question is, how much are you really reaching up above the shoulders of giants?
Maybe it's just assimilating different kinds of results of the past with ultimately this new
perspective that gives you this breakthrough idea, but that idea may not be novel in the way
there can be already discovered in the internet. Maybe the Nobel prizes of the next 100 years
are already all there on the internet to be discovered. They, they could be. They could be. I mean,
I think, um, this is one of the big mysteries, I think is that, uh, uh, I, first of all, I believe
a lot of the big new breakthroughs that are going to come in the next few decades and even in the
last decade are going to come at the intersection between different subject areas where, um,
there'll be some new connection that's found between what seemingly were disparate areas.
And one can even think of deep mind, as I said earlier, as a sort of interdisciplinary between
neuroscience ideas and AI engineering ideas originally. And so, um, so I think there's that.
And then one of the things we can't imagine today is, and one of the reasons I think people,
we were so surprised by how well large models worked is that actually it's very hard for our
human minds, our limited human minds to understand what it would be like to read the whole internet.
Right. I think we can do a thought experiment. And I used to do this of like, well,
what if I read the whole Wikipedia, uh, what would I know? And I think our minds can just about
comprehend maybe what that would be like, but the whole internet is beyond comprehension.
So I think we just don't understand what it would be like to be able to hold all of that in
mind potentially, right? And then, uh, active at once. And then maybe what are the connections
that are available there? So I think no doubt there are huge things to be discovered just like that.
But I do think there is this other type of creativity of true spark of new knowledge,
new idea never thought before about can't be averaged from things that are known. Um, that really,
of course, everything come, you know, nobody creates in a vacuum. So there must be clues
somewhere, but just a unique way of putting those things together. I think some of the greatest
scientists in history have displayed that, I would say, although it's very hard to know going back
to their time, what was exactly known, uh, when they came up with those things. Although I, uh,
you're making me really think because just the thought experiment of deeply knowing 100 Wikipedia
pages, I don't think I can, um, I've been really impressed by Wikipedia for, for technical topics.
Yeah. So if you know 100 pages or 1000 pages, I don't think we can vision truly comprehend what's
what kind of intelligence that is. Yeah. It's a pretty powerful tell. If you know how to use that
and integrate that information correctly. Yes. I think you can go really far. Yeah. You can probably
construct thought experiments based on that, like, simulate different ideas. So if this is true,
let me run this thought experiment that maybe this is true. It's not really invention. It's like,
just taking literally the knowledge and using it to construct a very basic simulation of the world.
I mean, some argue it's romantic in part, but Einstein would do the same kind of things with
a thought experiment. Yeah. You one could imagine doing that systematically across millions of
Wikipedia pages, plus PubMed, all these things. I think there are many, many things to be discovered
like that that hugely useful. You know, you could imagine, and I want us to do some of these things
in material science, like room temperature superconductors is something on my list one day that I'd
like to like, you know, have an AI system to help build better optimize batteries. All of these
sort of mechanical things. I think a systematic sort of search could be guided by a model,
could be could be extremely powerful. So speaking of which, you have a paper on nuclear fusion.
Magnetic control of talking about plasma is the deeper enforcement learning. So you,
you're seeking to solve nuclear fusion with deep RL. So it's doing control of high temperature
plasma. Can you explain this work and can AI eventually solve nuclear fusion? It's been very
fun last year or two and very productive because we've been taking off a lot of my dream projects,
if you like, of things that I've collected over the years of areas of science that I would like to,
I think, could be very transformative if we helped accelerate and really interesting problems,
scientific challenges in of themselves. This is energy. So energy, yes, exactly. So energy and
climate. So we talked about disease and biology as being one of the biggest places I think AI
can help with. I think energy and climate is another one. So maybe they would be my top two.
And fusion is one one area I think AI can help with. Now fusion has many challenges,
mostly physics, material science, and engineering challenges as well to build these massive fusion
reactors and contain the plasma. And what we try to do, and whenever we go into a new field to
apply our systems is we look for, we talk to domain experts, we try and find the best people in
the world to collaborate with. In this case, in fusion, we collaborated with EPFL in Switzerland,
the Swiss Technical Institute, who are amazing. They have a test reactor. They were willing to
let us use, which, you know, I double checked with the team, we were going to use carefully and
safely. I was impressed. They managed to persuade them to let us use it. And so it's an amazing
test reactor they have there. And they try all sort of pretty crazy experiments on it.
And what we tend to look at is, if we go into a new domain like fusion, what are all the
bottleneck problems, like thinking from first principles, you know, what are all the bottleneck
problems that are still stopping fusion working today? And then we look at, we get a fusion expert
to tell us. And then we look at those bottlenecks and we look at the ones which ones are amenable
to our AI methods today. And we'll be interesting from a research perspective, from our point of
view, from an AI point of view. And that would address one of their bottlenecks. And in this case,
plasma control was perfect. So, you know, the plasma, it's a million degrees Celsius,
something like that's hotter than the sun. And there's obviously no material that can contain it.
So they have to be containing these magnetic, very powerful, superconducting magnetic fields.
But the problem is plasma is pretty unstable, as you imagine. You're kind of holding a mini sun,
mini star in a reactor. So, you know, you kind of want to predict ahead of time what the plasma
is going to do. So you can move the magnetic field within a few milliseconds, you know, to basically
contain what it's going to do next. So it seems like a perfect problem if you think of it for
like a reinforcement learning prediction problem. So, you know, you got controller, you're going
to move the magnetic field. And until we came along, you know, they were doing with traditional
operational research type of controllers, which are kind of handcrafted. And the problem is,
of course, they can't react in the moment to something the plasma is doing. They have to be
hard coded. And again, knowing that that's normally our go-to solution is we would like to learn
that instead. And they also had a simulator of these plasma. So there were lots of criteria
that matched what we like to use. So can AI eventually solve nuclear fusion?
Well, so we, with this problem, and we published it in a NaturePay Plus year, we held the fusion,
that we held the plasma in a specific shape. So actually, it's almost like carving the plasma
into different shapes and control and hold it there for a record amount of time. So that's one
of the problems of fusion sort of solved. So have a controller that's able to, no matter the shape,
contain it. Yeah, contain it and hold it in structure. And there's different shapes that are
better for the energy productions called droplets and so on. So that was huge. And now we're looking,
we're talking to lots of fusion startups to see what's the next pump we can tackle in the fusion
area. So another fascinating place in a paper title, pushing the frontiers of
density functionals by solving the fractional electron problem. So you're taking on modeling
and simulating the quantum mechanical behavior of electrons. Yes.
Can you explain this work and can AI model and simulate arbitrary quantum mechanical systems
in the future? Yeah, so this is another problem I've had my eye on for, you know, decade or more,
which is sort of simulating the properties of electrons. If you can do that, you can basically
describe how elements and materials and substances work. So it's kind of like fundamental if you
want to advance material science. And we have Schrodinger's equation and then we have approximations
to that density functional theory. These things are famous. And people try and write approximations
to these to these functionals and kind of come up with descriptions of the electron clouds,
where they're going to go, how they're going to interact when you put two elements together.
And what we try to do is learn a simulation, learn a functional that will describe more chemistry,
types of chemistry. So until now, you know, you can run expensive simulations, but then you can only
simulate very small molecules, very simple molecules. We would like to simulate large materials.
And so today there's no way of doing that. And we're building up towards building
functional that approximate Schrodinger's equation and then allow you to describe what the
electrons are doing. And all material sort of science and material properties are governed by
the electrons and how they interact. So have a good summarization of the simulation
through the functional. But one that is still close to what the actual simulation will come
up with. So what, how difficult is that task? What's involved in that task? Is it running those
complicated simulations and learning the task of mapping from the initial conditions and the
parameters of the simulation, learning what the functional would be? Yeah. So it's pretty tricky.
And we've done it with, you know, the nice thing is we, there are, we can run a lot of the simulations
that the molecular dynamic simulations on our compute clusters. And so that generates a lot of
data. So in this case, the data is generated. So we like those sort of systems and that's why we
use games. It's simulator, generator data. And we can kind of create as much of it as we want,
really. And just let's leave some, you know, if any, computers are free in the cloud, we just run,
we run some of these calculations, right? Compute cluster calculations.
I like the free compute terms used up on quantum mechanics. Yeah, quantum mechanics, exactly,
simulations and protein simulations and other things. And so, and so, you know, when you're not
searching on YouTube for video, cat videos, we're using those computers usefully and quantum
chemistry, the idea. Fine. And, and, and pretty good use. And then, yeah, and then all of that
computational data that's generated, we can then try and learn the functionals from that,
which of course are way more efficient. Once we learn the functional, then, um, running those
simulations would be. Do you think one day AI may allow us to do something like, basically,
crack open physics, so do something like travel fast in the speed of light? My ultimate aim is
always being with AI is, um, the reason I am personally working on AI for my whole life is to
build a tool to help us understand the universe. So, I wanted to, and that means physics, really,
and the nature of reality. So, um, uh, I don't think we have systems that are capable of doing that
yet, but when we get towards AGI, I think, um, that's one of the first things I think we should apply
AGI to. I would like to test the limits of physics and our knowledge of physics. There's so many
things we don't know. This is one thing I find fascinating about science and, you know,
as a huge proponent of the scientific method as being one of the greatest ideas humanity's ever
had and allowed us to progress with our knowledge. But I think as a true scientist, I think what you
find is the more you find out, uh, the more you realize we don't know. And, and I always think
that it's surprising that more people don't aren't troubled, you know, every night I think about
all these things we interact with all the time that we have no idea how they work. Time,
consciousness, gravity, life, we can't, I mean, these are all the fundamental things of nature.
I think the way we don't really know what they are. To live life, we, uh, pin certain assumptions
on them and kind of treat our assumptions as if they're a fact. Yeah. That allows us to sort of
box them off somehow. Yeah, box them off somehow. But your, the reality is when you think of time,
you should remind yourself, you should put it off the, uh, take it off the shelf and realize like,
no, we have a bunch of assumptions. There's still a lot of, there's even not a lot of debate. There's
a lot of uncertainty about exactly what is time. Uh, is there an error of time? You know, there's,
there's a lot of other questions that you can't just make assumptions about. And maybe,
AI allows you to, um, not put anything on the shelf. Yeah. Well, I make any, uh, hard assumptions
and really open it up and see what exactly I think we should be truly open minded about that. And, uh,
exactly that not be dogmatic to a particular theory. Um, it'll also allow us to build better tools,
experimental tools eventually that can then test certain theories that may not be testable today
about as things about like what we spoke about at the beginning about the computational
and nature of the universe. How one might, if that was true, how one might go about testing that,
right? And, and how much, uh, you know, there are people who've conjectured people like, uh,
Scott Aronson and others about, uh, you know, how much information can a specific
plank unit of space and time contain, right? So one might be able to think about testing those ideas.
If you had, um, AI helping you build some new exquisite, uh, uh, experimental tools. This is
what I imagine, you know, many decades from now will be able to do. And what kind of questions
could be answered to running a simulation of them? So that there's a bunch of physics simulations
you can imagine that could be run in an, uh, so some kind of efficient way, much like you're doing
in the quantum simulation work. And perhaps even the origin of life. So figuring out how going
even back before the work of alpha fold begins of how this whole whole thing, um, emerges from a
rock. Yes. From a static thing. Would you, would you, do you think AI will allow us to, is that
something you have your eye on? It's trying to understand the origin of life. First of all,
yourself, would, would you think, um, how the heck did life origin and earth? Yeah. Well,
maybe we'll come to that in a second, but I think the ultimate use of AI is to kind of use it
to accelerate science to the maximum. So I, um, think of it a little bit like the tree of all knowledge.
If you imagine that's all the knowledge there is in the universe to attain. And, uh, we sort of
barely scratched the surface of that so far. And even though, you know, we've, we've, we've done
pretty well since the enlightenment, right, as humanity. And I think AI will turbocharge all of
that like we've seen without a fold. And I want to explore as much of that tree of knowledge as
it's possible to do. And, um, and I think that involves AI helping us with, with, with understanding
or finding patterns, um, but also potentially designing and building new tools, experimental tools.
So I think that's all, uh, and also running simulations and learning simulations. All of that,
we're already, we're sort of doing it at a, at a, at a, at a, you know, baby steps level here.
But I can imagine that in, in, in the decades to come as, uh, you know, what's the full flourishing
of, of that line of thinking? It's going to be truly incredible, I would say.
If I visualize this tree of knowledge, something tells me that that knowledge for,
tree of knowledge for humans is much smaller. In the set of all possible trees of knowledge,
it's actually quite small, giving our cognitive limitations, um, limited cognitive capabilities
that even with the, with the tools we build, we still won't be able to understand a lot of things.
And that's perhaps what non-human systems may be able to reach farther, not just as tools, but
in themselves understanding something that they can bring back. Yeah, it could well be.
So I mean, there's so many things that, that, that, that, that are sort of encapsulated in what
you just said there. I think, first of all, um, there's, there's two different things that's like,
what do we understand today? Yeah. What could the human mind understand? And what is the
totality of what is there to be understood, right? And so there's three, you know, you can think
of them as three larger, larger trees or exploring more branches of that tree. And I, I think with AI,
we're going to explore that whole lot. Now, the question is, is, you know, if you think about
what is the totality of what could be understood, um, there may be some fundamental physics reasons
why certain things can't be understood, like what's outside a simulation or outside the universe.
Maybe it's not understandable from within the universe. Um, so that's there may be some hard
constraints like that, you know, could be smaller constraints like, um, we think of space time
as fundamental. Our human brains are really used to this idea of a three dimensional world with time.
Right. Maybe, but our tools could go beyond that. Yeah. They wouldn't have that limitation
necessarily. They could think in 11 dimensions, 12 dimensions, whatever is needed. But, um,
we could still maybe understand that in several different ways. The example I always give is,
um, when I, you know, play Gary Kasparov for speed chess or we've talked about chess and these kind
of things, um, you know, he, if you, if you, if you're reasonably good at chess, you can, um,
you can't come up with the move Gary comes up with in his move, but he can explain it to you.
And you can understand and you can understand post-hoc the reasoning. Yeah. So, so I think there's a,
there's an even further level of like, well, maybe you couldn't have invented that thing,
but, but using, like, going back to using language again, perhaps you can understand and appreciate
that. Same way, like, you can appreciate, you know, Vivaldi or Mozart or something without,
you can appreciate the beauty of that without, um, being able to, to construct it yourself,
right? And then the music yourself. So I think we see this in all forms of life. So it'll be that
times, you know, a million, but it would, you can imagine also one sign of intelligence is the
ability to explain things clearly and simply, right? You know, people I rich refine another one
of my all-time heroes used to say that, right? If you can't, you know, if you can explain it
something simply, then that's a, that's the best sign, a complex topic simply. Then that's one
of the best signs of you understanding it. Yeah. So, um, I can see myself talking trash from
the AI system in that way. Yes. It gets frustrated how dumb I am in trying to explain something to me.
I was like, well, that means you're not intelligent because if you were intelligent,
you'd be able to explain it simply. Yeah. Of course, you know, there's, there's also the other
option. Of course, we couldn't enhance ourselves and, and without devices, we, we are already sort of
symbiotic without compute devices, right? Without phones and other things and, you know,
this stuff like neural link and accepture that could be, could, could advance that further.
So, I think there's lots of, lots of really amazing possibilities that I could foresee from here.
Well, let me ask you some wild questions. So, out there looking for friends, do you think there's
a lot of alien civilizations out there? So, I guess there's also goes back to your origin of
live question, too, because I think that that's key. My personal opinion, looking at all this and,
you know, it's one of my hobbies, physics, I guess. So, so I, you know, it's something I think
about a lot and talk to a lot of experts on and, and, and read a lot of books on. And I think
my feeling currently is that, that we are alone. I think that's the most likely scenario,
given what, what evidence we have. So, um, and the reasoning is, I think that,
you know, we've tried since things like sety program. And I guess since the dawning of the,
the space age, we've, you know, had telescopes, open radio telescopes and other things. And if you think
about, um, and tried to detect signals. Now, if you think about the evolution of humans on earth,
we could have easily been, um, a million years ahead of our time now or a million years behind.
Right. Easily with just some slightly different quirk thing happening hundreds of thousands years ago.
You know, things could have been slightly different. If the B2 would hit the dinosaurs a million years
earlier, maybe things would have evolved. Uh, we'd be a million years ahead of where we are now.
So what that means is, if you imagine where humanity will be in a few hundred years, let alone a
million years, especially if we hopefully, um, keep, you know, solve things like climate change and
other things. And we continue to flourish. Um, and we build things like AI and we do space traveling
and all of the stuff that, that, that humans have dreamed of forever, right? And sci-fi has talked
about forever. Um, we will be spreading across the stars, right? And Voin Neumann famously calculated,
you know, it would only take about a million years if you sent out Voin Neumann probes to the nearest,
you know, the nearest, uh, other solar systems. And, and then they built, all they did was build
two more versions themselves and set those two out to the next nearest systems. Uh, you,
you know, within a million years, I think you would have one of these probes in every system in the
galaxy. So it's not actually a cosmological time. That's actually a very short amount of time.
So, and, and, you know, we people like Dyson have thought about constructing Dyson spheres
around stars to collect all the energy coming out of the star. You know, that, there would be
constructions like that would be visible across space, um, probably even across a galaxy.
So, uh, and then, you know, if you think about all of our radio, television, uh,
emissions that have gone out since, since the, you know, 30s and 40s, um, imagine a million years of
that. And now hundreds of civilizations doing that. When we opened our ears at the point we got
technologically sophisticated enough in the space age, we should have heard a cacophony of voices,
we should have joined that cacophony of voices. And what, what we did, we opened our ears and we
heard nothing. And many people who argue that there are aliens would say, well, we haven't really
done exhaustive search yet. And maybe we're looking in the wrong bands and, and we've got the
wrong devices. And we wouldn't notice what an alien form was like to be so different to what we're
used to. But, you know, I don't, I don't really buy that. That it shouldn't be as difficult as
that. Like we, I think we've searched enough that if it were everywhere, it should be everywhere.
We should see Dyson spheres being put up. Suns blinking in and out. You know, there should be
a lot of evidence for those things. And then there are other people argue, well, the sort of
safari view of like, well, we're a primitive species still because we're not space-faring
yet. And, and we're, you know, there's some kind of globe, like universal rule, not to interfere,
your Star Trek rule. But like, look, look, we can't even coordinate humans to deal with climate change.
And we're one species. What, what is the chance that of all of these different human civilizations,
you know, alien civilizations, they would have the same priorities and, and, and, and agree or
across the, you know, these kind of matters. And even if that was true, and we were in some sort
of safari for our own good, to me, that's not much different from the simulation hypothesis.
Because what does it mean, the simulation hypothesis? I think in its most fundamental level,
it means what we're seeing is not quite reality, right? It's something, there's something more
deeper underlying it, maybe computational. Now, if we were in a, if we were in a sort of safari
park and everything we were seeing was a hologram and it was projected by the aliens or whatever,
that to me is not much different than thinking we're inside of another universe. Because we still
can't see true reality, right? I mean, there's, there's other explanations. It could be that
the way their communicating is just fundamentally different. That we're too dumb to understand
the much better methods of communication they have. It could be, I mean, it's a silly to say, but
our own thoughts could be the methods by which they're communicating. Like, the place for which
are ideas, writers talk about this, like the muse. Yeah. The, it sounds like very kind of wild,
but it could be thoughts. It could be some interactions with our mind that we think are
originating from us is actually something that is coming from other life forms elsewhere.
Consciousness itself might be that. It could be, but I don't see any sensible argument to the why,
why would all of the alien species be in this way? Yeah, some of them will be more primitive.
They would be close to our level. You know, there would, there should be a whole sort of
normal distribution of these things, right? Some would be aggressive, some would be, but,
you know, curious others would be very stoical and philosophical. Because, you know, maybe there
are a million years older than us, but it's not, it shouldn't be like, what, I mean, one,
one alien civilization might be like that, communicating thoughts and others, but I don't see why,
you know, potentially the hundreds there should be would be uniform in this way, right?
It could be a violent dictatorship that the people, the alien civilizations that
become successful become, gain the ability to be destructive, an order magnitude more destructive.
But of course, the sad thought, well, either humans are very special. We took a lot of leaps
that arrived at what it means to be human. There's a question there, which was the hardest,
which was the most special, but also if others have reached this level, and maybe many others have
reached this level, the great filter that's prevented them from going farther to becoming a
multi-planetary species or reaching out into the stars. And those are really important questions
for us, whether, whether there's other alien civilizations that there are not. This is very
useful for us to think about. If we destroy ourselves, how will we do it? And how easy is it to do?
Yeah. Well, these are big questions, and I've thought about these a lot, but the interesting
thing is that if we're alone, that's somewhat comforting from the great filter perspective,
because it probably means the great filters will be passed us. And I'm pretty sure they are. So
going back to your origin of life question, there are some incredible things that no one knows
how happened. Obviously, the first life form from chemical soup, that seems pretty hard, but I
would guess the multicellular, I wouldn't be that surprised if we saw single cells,
sort of life forms elsewhere, bacteria type things. But multicellular life seems incredibly hard,
that step of capturing mitochondria, and then using that as part of yourself when you've just
eaten it. Would you say that's the biggest, the most, like, if you had to choose one, sort of
hitchhiker's got a galaxy, one set in summary of like, oh, those clever creatures did this,
there would be the multicellular. I think that's probably the one that's the biggest. I mean,
there's a great book called The Ten Grand Infigrate Inventions of Evolution by Nick Lane,
and he speculates on ten of these, you know, what could be great filters. I think that's one.
I think the advent of intelligence, and conscious intelligence, and in order to just be able to
do science, and things like that, is huge as well. I mean, there's only evolved once as far as,
you know, in earth history. So that would be a later candidate, but there's certainly for
the early candidates, I think, multicellular life forms is huge. By the way, what it's interesting
to ask you, if you can hypothesize about what is the origin of intelligence, is it that we started
cooking meat over fire? Is it that we somehow figured out that we could be very powerful when we
started collaborating? So cooperation between our ancestors so that we can overthrow the alpha male.
What is it? Richard, I talked to Richard Ranham, who thinks we're all just beta males, who figured
out how to collaborate to defeat the one, the dictator, the authoritarian alpha male, that
controlled the tribe. Is there other explanation? Was there 2001's besides the type of monolith
that came down to earth? Well, I think all of those things you suggest are good candidates
fire and cooking, right? So that's clearly important for energy efficiency, cooking our meat,
and then being able to be more efficient about eating it and consuming the energy.
I think that's huge in then utilising fire and tools. I think you're right about the tribal
cooperation aspects and probably language as part of that, because probably that's what allowed
us to outcompete Neanderthals and perhaps less cooperative species. So that may be the case,
toolmaking, spears, axes, I think that let us, I mean, I think it's pretty clear now that humans
were responsible for a lot of the extinctions of megafauna, especially in the Americas,
when humans arrived. So you can imagine once you discover tool usage, how powerful that would
have been and how scary for animals. So I think all of those could have been explanations for it.
You know, the interesting thing is that it's a bit like general intelligence too, it's very costly
to begin with to have a brain, and especially a general purpose brain rather than a special
purpose one, because you might have energy at brains use, I think it's like 20% of the body's energy,
and it's massive. And you're thinking chess, one of the funny things that we used to say is
it's as much as a racing driver uses for a whole formula one race. You're just playing a game of,
you know, serious high level chess, which we know you wouldn't think, just sitting there,
because the brain's using so much energy. So in order for an animal and organism to justify that,
there has to be a huge payoff. And the problem with half a brain or half, you know,
intelligence say an IQs of, you know, of like a monkey brain, it's not clear you can justify
that evolutionary until you get to the human level brain. And so how do you do that jump? It's
very difficult, which is why I think it's only been done once, from the sort of specialized
brains that you see in animals, to this sort of general purpose, cheering powerful brains,
that humans have. And which allows us to invent the modern world. And you know, it takes a lot
to cross that barrier. And I think we've seen the same with AI systems, which is that maybe until
very recently, it's always been easier to craft a specific solution to a problem like chess,
than it has been to build a general learning system that can potentially do many things.
Because initially, that system will be way worse than less efficient than the specialized system.
So one of the interesting quirks of the human mind of this evolved system is that it appears
to be conscious. This thing that we don't quite understand, but it seems very, very special
is ability to have a subjective experience that it feels like something to eat a cookie,
the deliciousness of it or see a color and that kind of stuff. Do you think in order to solve
intelligence, we also need to solve consciousness along the way? Do you think AI systems need to
have consciousness in order to be truly intelligent? Yeah, we thought about this a lot actually.
And I think that my guess is that consciousness and intelligence are double dissociable.
So you can have one without the other both ways. And I think you can see that with consciousness
in that I think some animals pets, if you have a pet dog or something like that, you can see some
of the higher animals and dolphins, things like that are half self awareness and a very sociable
seem to dream. Those kinds of a lot of the traits one would regard as being kind of conscious
and self aware. But yet they're not that smart. So they're not that intelligent by,
by say IQ standards or something like that. Yeah, it's also possible that our understanding
of intelligence is flawed, like putting an IQ to it. Sure. Maybe the thing that a dog can do is
actually gone very far along the path of intelligence and we humans are just able to play chess and
maybe write poems. Right. But if we go back to the idea of AGI in general intelligence,
you know, dogs are very specialized, right? Most animals are pretty specialized. They can be
amazing at what they do, but they're like kind of elite sports sports people or something, right?
So they do one thing extremely well because their entire brain is optimized. They have somehow convinced
the entirety of the human population to feed them and service them. So in some way they're controlling.
Yes, exactly. Well, we co-evolved to some crazy degree, right? Including the way the dogs,
you know, even even wag their tails and twist their noses, right? We find we find inexorably cute.
But I think you can also see intelligence on the other side. So systems like artificial systems
that are amazingly smart at certain things like maybe playing go or in chess and other things,
but they don't feel at all in any shape or form conscious in the way that, you know, you do to
to me or I do to you. And I think actually building AGI is these intelligent constructs is one of
the best ways to explore the mystery of consciousness, to break it down because we're going to have
devices that are pretty smart at certain things or capable at certain things, but potentially won't
have any semblance of self-awareness or other things. And in fact, I would advocate if there's a
choice, building systems in the first place AGI systems that are not conscious to begin with
are just tools until we understand them better and the capabilities better.
So on that topic, just not as the sea of deep mind, just as a human being, let me ask you about
this one particular anecdotal evidence of the Google engineer who made a comment or believed
that there is some aspect of a language model, the Lambda language model that exhibited sentience.
So you said you believe there might be a responsibility to build systems that are not
sent yet. And this experience of a particular engineer, I think, I'd love to get your general
opinion on this kind of thing, but I think it will happen more and more and more, which not one
engineer is, but when people out there that don't have an engineer background start interacting
with increasingly intelligent systems, we anthropomorphize them. They start to have deep, impactful
interactions with us in a way that we miss them when they're gone. And we sure as heck feel like
they're living entities, self-aware entities, and maybe even we project sentience onto them.
So what's your thought about this particular system? Have you ever met a language model
that's sentient? No, no. What do you make of the case of when you kind of feel that there's
some elements of sentience to this system? Yeah, so this is an interesting question and
obviously a very fundamental one. So the first thing to say is I think that none of the systems
we have today, I would say even have one Iota of semblance of consciousness or sentience,
that's my personal feeling interacting with them every day. So I think this way premature to be
discussing what that engineer talked about. I think at the moment it's more of projection of
other way our own minds work, which is to see a sort of purpose and direction in almost anything
that we, our brains are trained to interpret agency, basically in things, even inanimate things
sometimes. And of course with a language system because language is so fundamental to intelligence
that's going to be easy for us to anthropomorphize that. I mean back in the day, even the first,
the dumbest sort of template chatbots ever, Eliza and the yolk of the original chatbots back in the
60s, fooled some people under certain circumstances, right? It pretended to be a psychologist, so just
basically rabbit back to you, the same question you asked it back to you. And some people believe
that. So I don't think we can, this is why I think the chewing test is a little bit flawed as a
formal test because it depends on the sophistication of the of the judge, whether or not they are
qualified to make that distinction. So I think we should talk to, you know, the top philosophers
about this, people like Daniel Dennett and David Charmers and others who've obviously thought
deeply about consciousness. Of course, consciousness itself hasn't been well, there's no agreed definition.
If I was to, you know, speculate about that, you know, I kind of, the, the working definition,
I like is it's the way information feels when, you know, it gets processed. I think maybe Max
Tecmar came up with that. I like that idea. I don't know if it helps us get towards any more
operational thing, but it's, it's, I think it's a nice way of viewing it. I think we can obviously
see from neuroscience certain prerequisites that require, like self awareness, I think is necessary,
but not sufficient component, this idea of a self and other and set of coherent preferences
that the coherent over time, you know, these things are maybe memory. These things are probably
needed for a sentient or conscious being. But the reason, the difficult thing I think for us,
when we get, and I think this is a really interesting philosophical debate, is when we get closer to
AGI and, you know, and, and, and much more powerful systems than we have today, how are we going
to make this judgment? And one way, which is the cheering test is sort of a behavioral judgment,
is, is the system exhibiting all the behaviors that a human sentient or a sentient being would,
would, would exhibit? Is it answering the right questions? Is it saying the right things? Is it
indistinguishable from a human, and so on? But I think there's a second thing that makes us,
as humans, regard each other as sentient, right? Why do we, why do we think this? And I debated
this with Daniel Dennett. And I think there's a second reason that's over, often overlooked,
which is that we're running on the same substrate, right? So if we're exhibiting the same behavior,
more or less, as humans, and we're running on the same, you know, carbon-based biological substrate,
the squishy, you know, few pounds of flesh in our skulls, then the most parsimonious, I think,
explanation is that you're feeling the same thing as I'm feeling, right? But we will never have
that second part, the substrate equivalence with a machine, right? So we will have to only judge
based on the behavior. And I think the substrate equivalence is a critical part of why we make
assumptions that we're conscious. And in fact, even with animals, high level animals, why we think
they might be, because they're exhibiting some of the behaviors we would expect from a sentient
animal. And we know they're made of the same things biological neurons. So we're going to have to
come up with explanations or models of the gap between substrate differences between machines
and humans to get anywhere beyond the behavioral. But to me, sort of the practical question is
very interesting and very important. When you have millions, perhaps billions of people believing
that you have a sentient AI, believing what that Google engineer believed, which I just see as an
obvious, very near term future thing. Certainly on the path to AGI, how does that change the world?
What's the responsibility of the AI system to help those millions of people? And also what's the
ethical thing? Because you can, you can make a lot of people happy by creating a meaningful deep
experience with a system that's faking it before it makes it. Yeah. And I don't,
are we the right, who is to say, what's the right thing to do? Should AI always be tools?
Like, why, why are we constraining AI's to always be tools as opposed to friends?
Yeah. I think, well, I mean, these are, you know, fantastic questions and also critical ones.
And we've been thinking about this since the start of DeepMind and before that, because we plan
for success and, you know, how, how, you know, however, remote that looked like back in 2010.
And we've always had sort of these ethical considerations as fundamental at DeepMind.
And my current thinking on the language models is and large models is they're not ready,
we don't understand them well enough yet. And, you know, in terms of analysis tools and,
and guardrails, what they can and can't do and so on to deploy them at scale, because I think,
you know, there are big still ethical questions like should an AI system always announce that it is
an AI system to begin with, probably yes. What do you do about answering those philosophical
questions about the feelings people may have about AI systems perhaps incorrectly attributed?
So I think there's a whole bunch of research that needs to be done first to responsibly,
before we're, you know, you can responsibly deploy these systems at scale. That would be at least
be my current position. Over time, I'm very confident we'll have those tools like interpretability
questions and analysis questions. And then with the ethical quandary, you know, I think there,
it's important to look beyond just science. That's why I think philosophy, social sciences,
even theology, other things like that come into it where what it, you know, arts and humanities,
what what what does it mean to be human and the spirit of being human and to enhance that
and the human condition, right? And allow us to experience things we could never experience before
and improve the overall human condition and humanity overall, you know, get radical abundance,
solve many scientific problem solved disease. So this is the era I think this is the amazing
era I think we're heading into if we do it right. But we've got to be careful. We've already seen
with things like social media how dual use technologies can be misused by firstly, by by bad
you, you know, people, bad actors or naive actors or crazy actors, right? So that's that set of
just the common or garden use, you know, misuse of existing dual use technology. And then,
of course, there's an additional thing that has to be overcome with AI that eventually it may
have its own agency. So it could be good or bad in it in it in it itself. So I think these
questions have to be approached very carefully using the scientific method, I would say, in terms
of hypothesis generation, careful control testing, not live AB testing out in the world because
with powerful dual technologies like AI, if something goes wrong, it may cause, you know, a lot
of harm before you can fix it. It's not like a, you know, an imaging app or game app where,
you know, if it if something goes wrong, it's relatively easy to fix and the harm is relatively small.
So I think it comes with, you know, the usual cliche of like with a lot of power comes a lot
of responsibility. And I think that's the case here with things like AI given the enormous
opportunity in front of us. And I think we need a lot of voices and as many inputs into things like
the design of the systems and the values they should have and what goals should they be put to,
I think as wide a group of voices as possible beyond just the technologist is needed to input
into that and to have a say in that, especially when it comes to deployment of these systems,
which is when the rubber really hits the road, it really affects the general person in the street
rather than fundamental research. And that's why I say, I think as a first step, it would be better
if we have the choice to build these systems as tools to give, and I'm not saying that it should
never, they should never go beyond tools because of course the potential is there for it to go
way beyond just tools. But I think that would be a good first step in order for us to, you know,
allow us to carefully experiment and understand what these things can do. So the leap between tool,
the sentient entity being as long as you take very care of us. Yes. Let me ask a dark personal
question. So you're one of the most brilliant people in the AI community, you also want
on the most kind. And if I may say sort of loved people in the community, that said,
creation of a super intelligent AI system would be one of the most powerful things in the world,
tools or otherwise. And again, as the old saying goes, power corrupts and absolute power corrupts,
absolutely. You are likely to be one of the people. I would say probably the most likely person
to be in the control of such a system. Do you think about the corrupting nature of power when
you talk about these kinds of systems that as all dictators and people have caused atrocities
in the past always think they're doing good. But they don't do good because the powers polluted
their mind about what is good and what is evil. Do you think about this stuff? Are we just
focused on language model? No, I think about them all the time. And, you know, I think
what are the defences against that? I think one thing is to remain very grounded and sort of humble,
no matter what you do or achieve. And I try to do that. I might, you know, my best friends are
still my set of friends from my undergraduate Cambridge days, my family's, you know, and friends
are very important. I've always, I think trying to be a multi-disciplinary person, it helps to keep
you humble because no matter how good you are at one topic, someone will be better than you at that.
And always relearning a new topic again from scratch is a new field is very humbling, right? So
for me, that's been biology over the last five years. You know, huge area topic and it's been,
and I just love doing that, but it helps to keep you grounded, like you can keep you open-minded.
And then the other important thing is to have a really good, amazing set of people around you at
your company or your organization who are also very ethical and grounded themselves and help
to keep you that way. And then ultimately, just to answer your question, I hope we're going to be
a big part of birthing AI and that being the greatest benefit to humanity of any tool or technology
ever and getting us into a world of radical abundance and curing diseases and solving many of the
big challenges we have in front of us and then ultimately, you know, help the ultimate flourishing
of humanity to travel the stars and find those aliens if they are there. And if they're not there,
find out why they're not there, what is going on here in the universe? This is all to come,
and that's what I've always dreamed about. But I don't think, I think AI is too big an idea,
it's not going to be, there'll be a certain set of pioneers who get there first. I hope that
we're in the vanguard so we can influence how that goes. And I think it matters who builds,
which cultures they come from and what values they have, the builders of AI systems. Because I
think even though the AI systems are going to learn for itself most of its knowledge,
there'll be a residue in the system of the culture and the values of the creators of that system.
And there's interesting questions to discuss about that geopolitically, you know, different cultures
as we're in a more fragmented world than ever. Unfortunately, I think in terms of global cooperation,
we see that in things like climate where we can't seem to get our act together globally to
cooperate on these pressing matters. I hope that will change over time. Perhaps, you know,
if we get to an era of radical abundance, we don't have to be so competitive anymore. Maybe we
can be more cooperative if resources aren't so scarce. It's true that in terms of power corrupting
and leading to destructive things, it seems that some of the atrocities of the past happen when
there's a significant constraint on resources. I think that's the first thing. I don't think
that's enough. I think scarcity is one thing that's led to competition, you know, sort of zero
sum game thinking. I would like us to all be in a positive some world. And I think for that,
you have to remove scarcity. I don't think that's enough, unfortunately, to get well-peace because
there's also other corrupting things like wanting power over people and this kind of stuff, which
is not necessarily satisfied by just abundance, but I think it will help. But I think ultimately,
AI is not going to be run by any one person or one organization. I think it should belong to the
world, belong to humanity. And I think there'll be many ways this will happen. And ultimately,
everybody should have a say in that. Do you have advice for young people in high school and
college? Maybe if they're interested in AI or interesting having a big impact on the world,
what they should do to have a career, they can be proud of or to have a life that can be proud of.
I love giving talks to the next generation. What I say to them is actually two things. I think the
most important things to learn about and to find out about when you're young is what are your true
passions, is first of all, as two things. One is find your true passions. And I think you can do
that by the way to do that is to explore as many things as possible when you're young and you
have the time and you can take those risks. I would also encourage people to look at the finding
the connections between things in a unique way. I think that's a really great way to find a
passion. Second thing I would say advises know yourself. So spend a lot of time understanding
how you work best. Like what are the optimal times to work? What are the optimal ways that you
study? How do you deal with pressure? Test yourself in various scenarios and try and improve your
weaknesses. But also find out what your unique skills and strengths are and then hone those.
So then that's what will be your super value in the world later on. And if you can then combine
those two things and find passions that you're genuinely excited about that intersect with what
your unique strong skills are, then you're you know, you're onto something incredible and you know,
I think you can make a huge difference in the world. So let me ask about know yourself. This is fun.
This is fun. Quick questions about day in the life. The perfect day. The perfect product of
day in life with demos has helped. Yeah. Maybe, maybe these days, you're, there's a lot involved.
So maybe slightly younger demos. Yeah. When you could focus on a single project, maybe. How early
do you wake up? Are you night owl? Do you wake up early in the morning? What are some interesting
habits? How many dozens of cups of coffees do you drink a day? What's the computer that you use?
What's the setup? How many screens? What kind of keyboard are we talking? EMAX VIM or we're talking
something more modern? There's a bunch of those questions. So maybe day in the life. What's the
perfect day involved? Well, these days it's quite different from say 10, 20 years ago. Back 10, 20
years ago, it would have been, you know, a whole day of research, individual research or programming,
doing some experiment, neuroscience computer science experiment, reading lots of research papers,
and then perhaps at night time, you know, reading science fiction books or playing some games.
But lots of focus, so like a deep focused work on whether it's programming or reading research papers.
Yes. So that would be lots of deep, you know, focus work. These days, for the last sort of,
I guess, you know, five to 10 years, I've actually got quite a structure that works very well for
me now, which is that I'm a night complete night owl always have been. So I optimize for that.
So, you know, I basically do a normal day's work, get into work about 11 o'clock and sort of do
work to about seven in the office. And I will arrange back to back meetings for the entire time
of that. And with as many, as many people as possible. So that's my collaboration, management,
part of the day. Then I go home, spend time with the family and friends, have dinner, relax a
little bit. And then I start a second day of work. I call it my second day of work around 10 p.m.
11 p.m. And that's the time until about the small hours of the morning, four, five in the morning,
where I will do my thinking and reading a research, writing research papers. Sadly,
don't have time to code anymore, but it's not efficient to do that these days, given the amount
of time I have. But that's when I do, you know, maybe do the long kind of stretches of thinking
and planning. And then probably, you know, using, using email or other things, I would set,
I would fire off a lot of things to my team to deal with the next morning. So I actually
thinking about this overnight, we should go for this project or arrange this meeting the next day.
When you think it through a problem, are you talking about sheet of paper or the pen pen? Is there some
it depends structure? Yeah, I like process. I'm still like pencil and paper best for working out things. But
these days, it's just so efficient to read research papers just on the screen. I still often print
them out, actually, I still prefer to mark out things. And I find it goes into the brain quick
better and sticks in the brain better when you're, you're still using physical pen and pencil and
paper. So you take notes with the, I have lots of notes, electronic ones and also, um,
whole stacks of notebooks that I use at home, yeah. On some of these most challenging next steps,
for example, stuff none of us know about that you're working on, you're thinking, there's some
deep thinking required there, right? Like, what is the right problem? What is the right approach?
Because you're going to have to invest a huge amount of time for the whole team. They're going
to have to pursue this thing. What's the right way to do it? Is RL going to work here or not?
Yes. What's the right thing to try? What's the right benchmark to you? Do you need to construct
the benchmark from scratch? All those kinds of things. Yes. So I think of all those kind of things
in the nighttime phase, but also much more. I find, I've always found the quiet hours of the morning
when everyone's asleep. It's super quiet outside. I love that time. It's the golden hours,
between one and three in the morning, put some music on, some inspiring music on, and then think
these deep thoughts. That's when I would read my philosophy books and spinozers, my recent
favorite can, all these things. I read about a great scientist of history, how they did things,
how they thought things. That's when you do all your creative thinking. It's good. I think people
recommend you do your creative thinking in one block. The way I organize the day, that way I don't
get interrupted, because obviously no one else is up at those times. I can go, it says, I can
get super deep and super into flow. The other nice thing about doing it nighttime-wise is if I'm
really onto something or I've got really deep into something, I can choose to extend it,
and I'll go into six in the morning, whatever. Then I'll just pay for it the next day,
because I'll be a bit tired and I won't be my best, but that's fine. I can decide, looking at my
schedule the next day, and given where I'm at with this particular thought or creative idea,
that I'm going to pay that cost the next day. I think that's more flexible than morning people
who do that. They get up at four in the morning. They can also do those golden hours then,
but then their schedule day starts at breakfast, AAM, whatever they have their first meeting.
Then it's hard, you have to reschedule day if you and flow. That could be true. That's a special
threat of thoughts that you're too passionate about. This is where some of the greatest ideas could
potentially come is when you just lose yourself late. For the meetings, you're loading in really
hard problems in a very short amount of time, so you have to do some first principles thinking
here. What's the problem? What's the state of things? What's the right next step? You have to get
really good at context-witching, which is one of the hardest things, because especially as we do
so many things, if you include all the scientific things, we do scientific fields we're working in.
These are entire complex fields in themselves, and you have to keep up to abreast of that.
But I enjoy it. I've always been a generalist in a way, and that's actually what happened with my
games career after chess. One of the reasons I stopped playing chess was because I got into
computers, but also I started realizing there were many other great games out there to play too.
I've always been that way in client multidisciplinary, and there's too many interesting things in
the world to spend all your time just on one thing. You mentioned Spinoza. I've got to ask the big,
ridiculously big question about life. What do you think is the meaning of this whole thing?
Why are we humans here? You've already mentioned that perhaps the universe created us.
Is that why you think we're here to understand how the universe is?
I think my answer to that would be, at least the life I'm living is to gain and understand
knowledge, to gain knowledge and understand the universe. That's what I think.
I can't see any higher purpose than that if you think back to the classical Greeks,
the virtue of gaining knowledge. I think it's one of the few true virtues is to understand
the world around us and the context and humanity better. I think if you do that, you become more
compassionate and more understanding yourself and more tolerant, and all these other things
may flow from that. To me, understanding the nature of reality, that is the biggest question.
What is going on here is sometimes the colloquial way I say. What is really going on here?
It's so mysterious. I feel like we're in some huge puzzle. The world is also seems to be the
universe seems to be structured in a way. Why is it structured in a way that science is even
possible? The scientific method works. Things are repeatable. It feels like it's almost structured
in a way to be conducive to gaining knowledge. Why should computers be even possible? Isn't that
amazing that computational or electronic devices can be possible? They're made of sand,
our most common element that we have, silicon on the Earth's crust. They could have been made
of diamond or something. We would have only had one computer. A lot of things are slightly
suspicious to me. This puzzle, what it takes to design a game that's really fun to play for
prolonged periods of time. It does seem like this puzzle you mentioned, the more you learn about it,
the more you realize how little you know. It humbles you, but excites you by the possibility of
learning more. One heck of a puzzle we got going on here. I mentioned of all the people in the
world, you're very likely to be the one who creates the AGI system that achieves human level
intelligence and goes beyond it. If you got a chance in very well, you could be the person that
goes into the room with the system and have a conversation. Maybe you only get to ask one question.
If you do, what question would you ask her? I would probably ask, what is the true nature of
reality? I think that's the question. I don't know if I don't understand the answer, because maybe
it would be 42 or something like that, but that's the question I would ask.
And then there'll be a deep sigh from the systems like, all right, how do I explain to the
system? All right, let me, I don't have time to explain. Maybe I'll draw you a picture. It is,
I mean, how do you even begin to answer that question? Well, I think it would,
what would you think the answer could possibly look like? I think it could, it could start looking
like more fundamental explanations of physics would be the beginning. You know,
it's more careful specification of that, taking you walking us through by the hand as to what
one would do to maybe prove those things out. Maybe giving you glimpses of what things you
totally missed in the physics of today. Exactly. Here's glimpses of, no, like there's a much
much more elaborate world or a much simpler world or something.
A much deeper, maybe simpler explanation of things, right? Then the standard model of physics,
which we know doesn't work, but we still keep adding to. So, and that's how I think the beginning
of an exploration would look. And it would start encompassing many of the mysteries that we have
wondered about for thousands of years, like, you know, consciousness, dreaming, life and gravity,
all of these things. Yeah, giving us glimpses of explanations for those things. Yeah.
Well, Dennis, you're one of the special human beings in this giant puzzle of ours.
And it's a huge honor that you would take a pause from the bigger puzzle to solve this small
puzzle of a conversation with me today. It's truly an honor and a pleasure. Thank you so much.
Thank you so much. We really enjoyed it. Thanks, Dex.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Dennisus Hobbes.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, let me leave you with some words from Edgar Dextra.
Computer science is no more about computers than astronomy is about telescopes.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.