Remember George Washington? You know how he died? Well-meaning physicians bled him to death,
and this was the most important patient in the country, maybe in the history of the country,
and we bled him to death trying to help him. So when you're actually inflating the money supply
at 7% but you're calling it 2% because you want to help the economy, you're literally bleeding
the free market to death. But the sad fact is George Washington went along with it because he
thought that they were going to do him good, and the majority of the society, most companies,
most conventional thinkers, you know, the working class, they go along with this because they think
that someone has their best interests at mind, and the people that are bleeding them to death
believe, they believe that prescription because their mental models are just so defective.
The following is a conversation with Michael Saylor, one of the most prominent and brilliant
Bitcoin proponents in the world. He is the CEO of MicroStrategy, founder of Saylor Academy,
graduate of MIT, and Michael is one of the most fascinating and rigorous thinkers I've ever gotten
a chance to explore ideas with. He can effortlessly zoom out to the big perspectives of human
civilization and human history, and zoom back in to the technical details of blockchains, markets,
governments, and financial systems. This is the Lex Friedman podcast. To support it,
please check out our sponsors in the description. And now, dear friends, here's Michael Saylor.
Here's Michael Saylor. Let's start with a big question of truth and wisdom. When advanced humans
or aliens or AI systems, let's say five to ten centuries from now, look back at Earth on this
early 21st century, how much do you think they would say we understood about money and economics,
or even about engineering, science, life, death, meaning, intelligence, consciousness, all the big
interesting questions? I think they would probably give us a
B-minus on engineering, on all the engineering things, the hard sciences.
A passing grade. Like we're doing okay. We're working our way through rockets and jets and
electric cars and electricity transport systems and nuclear power and space flight and the like.
And if you look at the walls that grace the great court at MIT, it's full of all the great thinkers
and they're all pretty admirable. If you could be with Newton or Gauss or Madame Curie or Einstein,
you would respect them. I would say they'd give us a D-minus on economics.
Like an F-plus or a D-minus. You have an optimistic vision. First of all,
optimistic vision of engineering, because everybody you've listed, not everybody,
but most people you've listed, it's just over the past couple of centuries. And maybe it stretches
a little farther back, but mostly all the cool stuff we've done in engineering is the past couple
of centuries. I mean, Archimedes had his virtues. I studied the history of science at MIT,
and I also studied aerospace engineering. And so I clearly have a bias in favor of science.
And if I look at the past 10,000 years and I consider all of the philosophy and the politics
and their impact on the human condition, I think it's a wash for every politician that came up with
a good idea. Another politician came up with a bad idea. And it's not clear to me that most of
the political and philosophical contributions to the human race and the human conditions
have advanced so much. I mean, we're still taking guidance and admiring Aristotle and Plato and
Seneca and the like. And on the other hand, if you think about what has made the human condition
better, fire, water, harnessing of wind energy, try to row across an ocean, right? Not easy.
And for people who are just listening or watching, there's a beautiful sexy ship from
16th, 17th century?
This is a 19th century handmade model of a 17th century sailing ship, which is of the type that
the Dutch East India's company used to sail the world and trade. So that was made, you know,
the original is made sometime in the 1600s. And then this model is made in the 19th
century by individuals.
So both the model and the ship itself is engineering at its best. And just imagine,
just like rockets flying out to space, how much hope this filled people with exploring the unknown,
going into the mystery. Both the entrepreneurs and the business people and the engineers and
just humans, what's out there? What's out there to be discovered?
Yeah, the metaphor of human beings leaving shore or sailing across the horizon,
risking their lives in pursuit of a better life is an incredibly powerful one.
In 1900, I suppose the average life expectancy is 50. During the Revolutionary War, you know,
while our founding fathers were fighting to establish, you know, life, liberty, pursuit
of happiness, the Constitution, average life expectancy of like 32, something between 32 and
36. So all the sound and the fury doesn't make you live past 32, but what does, right? Antibiotics.
Conquest of infectious diseases. If we understand the science of infectious disease, you know,
sterilizing a knife and harnessing antibiotics gets you from 50 to 70. And that happened fast,
right? That happens from 1900 to 1950 or something like that. And I think if you look at the human
condition, you ever get on one of those rowing machines where they actually keep track of your
watts output when you're on that? Yeah.
Yeah, it's like 200 is a lot. Okay, 200 is a lot. So a kilowatt hour is like all the energy that a
trained athlete can deliver in a day. And probably not 1% of the people in the world could deliver
a kilowatt hour in a day. And the commercial value of a kilowatt hour, the retail value,
is 11 cents today. And the wholesale value is 2 cents. And so you have to look at the contribution
of politicians and philosophers and economists to the human condition. And it's like at best
a wash one way or the other. And then if you look at the contribution of John D. Rockefeller
when he delivered you a barrel of oil, the energy in oil, liquid energy, or the contribution of
Tesla as we deliver electricity. And what's the impact on the human condition if I have
electric power, if I have chemical power, if I have wind energy, if I can actually set up a
reservoir, create a dam, spin a turbine, and generate energy from a hydraulic source?
That's extraordinary, right? And so our ability to cross the ocean, our ability to grow food,
our ability to live, it's technology that gets the human race from a brutal life where life
expectancy is 30 to a world where life expectancy is 80. You gave a D-minus to the economists.
So are they too like the politicians to wash in terms of there's good ideas and bad ideas and
that tiny delta between good and bad is how you squeak past the F-plus onto the D-minus territory?
RL I think most economic ideas are bad ideas. Take us back to MIT and you want to solve a fluid
dynamics problem. Design the shape of the hull of that ship. Or you want to design an airfoil,
a wing. Or if you want to design an engine or a nozzle in a rocket ship, you wouldn't do it with
simple arithmetic. You wouldn't do it with a scalar. There's not a single number, right? It's
vector math. Computational fluid dynamics is n-dimensional, higher-level math, complicated
stuff. So when an economist says the inflation rate is 2%, that's a scalar. And when an economist
says it's not a problem to print more money because the velocity of the money is very low,
the monetary velocity is low, that's another scalar. Okay, so the truth of the matter is
inflation is not a scalar. Inflation is an n-dimensional vector. Money velocity is not
a scalar. Saying what's the velocity of money, oh, it's slow or it's fast, it ignores the question
of what medium is the money moving through. In the same way that what's the speed of sound?
Okay, well, what is sound, right? Sound is a compression wave, it's energy moving through
a medium, but the speed is different. So for example, the speed of sound through air is
different than the speed of sound through water. And sound moves faster through water. It moves
faster through a solid and it moves faster through a stiffer solid. So there isn't one.
TG What is the fundamental problem with the way economists reduce the world down to a model?
Is it too simple or is it just even the first principles of constructing the model is wrong?
RL I think that the fundamental problem is if you see the world as a scalar, you simply pick
the one number which is, which supports whatever you want to do and you ignore the universe of
other consequences from your behavior. TG In general, I don't know if you've heard of,
like Eric Weisen has been talking about this with gauge theory. So different kinds of approaches
from the physics world, from the mathematical world to extend past this scalar view of economics.
So gauge theory is one way that comes from physics. Do you find that a way of exploring economics
interesting? So outside of cryptocurrency, outside of the actual technologies and so on,
just analysis of how economics works, do you find that interesting?
RL Yeah, I think that if we're going to want to really make any scientific progress in economics,
we have to apply much, much more computationally intensive and richer forms of mathematics.
TG So simulation, perhaps? Or...
RL Yeah, you know, when I was at MIT, I studied system dynamics. You know, they taught it at the
Sloan School. It was developed by Jay Forrester, who was an extraordinary computer scientist.
And when we've created models of economic behavior, they were all multi-dimensional
nonlinear models. So if you want to describe how anything works in the real world, you have to
start with the concept of feedback. If I double the price of something, demand will fall and
attempts to create supply will increase, and there will be a delay before the capacity increases.
There'll be an instant demand change, and there'll be rippling effects throughout every other segment
of the economy downstream and upstream of such a thing. So it's kind of common sense,
but most economics, most classical economics, is always, you know, taught with linear models,
you know, fairly simplistic linear models. And oftentimes, I'm really shocked today
that the entire mainstream dialogue of economics has been captured by scale or arithmetic.
For example, if you read, you know, read any article in the New York Times or the Wall Street
Journal, right, they just refer to it, there's an inflation number or the CPI or the inflation rate
is X. And if you look at all the historic studies of the impact of inflation, generally, they're
all based upon the idea that inflation equals CPI, and then they try to extrapolate from that,
and you just get nowhere with it. So at the very least, we should be considering inflation
and other economics concepts as a nonlinear dynamical system. So nonlinearity and also just
embracing the full complexity of just how the variables interact, maybe through simulation,
maybe some have some interesting models around that.
Wouldn't it be refreshing if somebody for once published a table of the change in price of every
product, every service, and every asset in every place over time?
You said table, some of that also is the task of visualization,
how to extract from this complex set of numbers patterns that somehow indicate something
fundamental about what's happening. So like, summarization of data is still important,
perhaps summarization not down to a single scale of value, but looking at that whole sea of numbers,
you have to find patterns, like what is inflation in a particular sector, what is maybe a change
over time, maybe different geographical regions, you know, things of that nature. I think that's
kind of, I don't know even what that task is. You could look at machine learning, you can look
at AI with that perspective, which is like, how do you represent what's happening efficiently,
as efficiently as possible? That's never going to be a single number, but it might be a compressed
model that captures something beautiful, something fundamental about what's happening.
SF. It's an opportunity, for sure. If we take, for example, during the pandemic,
the response of the political apparatus was to lower interest rates to zero and to start
buying assets, in essence printing money, and the defense was there's no inflation.
But of course, you had one part of the economy where it was locked down, so it was illegal to
buy anything. It was either illegal or it was impractical, so it would be impossible for demand
to manifest, so of course there is no inflation. On the other hand, there was instantaneous,
immediate inflation in another part of the economy. For example, you lower the interest
rates to zero. At one point, we saw the swap rate on a 30-year note go to 72 basis points.
That means that the value of a long-dated bond immediately inflates, so the bond market had
hyperinflation within minutes of these financial decisions. The asset market had hyperinflation.
We had what you call a K-shape recovery, what we affectionately call a K-shape recovery. Main Street
shut down, Wall Street recovered all within six weeks. The inflation was in the assets,
like in the stocks, in the bonds. If you look today, you see that typical house,
according to the Case-Schiller Index today, is up 19.2% year over year. If you're a first-time home
buyer, the inflation rate is 19%. The formal CPI announced a 7.9%. You can pretty much create any
inflation rate you want by constructing a market basket, a weighted basket of products or services
or assets that yield you the answer. I think that the fundamental failing of economists is,
first of all, they don't really have a term for asset inflation, right?
What's an asset? What's asset hyperinflation? You mentioned bond market swap rate and asset
is where the majority of the hyperinflation happened. What's inflation? What's hyperinflation
and what's an asset? What's an asset market? I'm going to ask so many dumb questions.
In the conventional economic world, you would treat inflation as the rate of increase in price
of a market basket of consumer products defined by a government agency.
So they have like traditional things that a regular consumer would be buying.
The government selects like toilet paper, food, toaster, electronics, all that kind of stuff. And
it's like a representative basket of goods that lead to a content existence on this earth for
regular consumer. They define a synthetic metric, right? I mean, I'm going to say you should have
a thousand square foot apartment and you should have a used car and you should eat, you know,
three hamburgers a week. Now, ten years go by and the apartment costs more, I could adjust the
market basket via, you know, they call them hedonic adjustments. I could decide that it
used to be in 1970 to a thousand square feet, but in the year 2020, you only need 700 square
feet because we've miniaturized televisions and we've got more efficient electric appliances
because things have collapsed into the iPhone. You just don't need as much space. So now I,
you know, it may be that the apartment costs 50% more, but after the hedonic adjustment,
there is no inflation because I just downgraded the expectation of what a normal person should
have. So the synthetic nature of the metric allows for manipulation by people in power.
RL. Pretty much. I guess my criticism of economists is rather than embracing inflation
based upon its fundamental idea, which is the rate at which the price of things go up, right?
They've been captured by mainstream conventional thinking to immediately equate inflation to
the government-issued CPI or government-issued PCE or government-issued PPI measure, which was never
the rate at which things go up. It's simply the rate at which a synthetic basket of products and
services the government wishes to track go up. Now, the problem with that is two big things.
One thing is the government gets to create the market basket and so they keep changing what's
in the basket over time. So, I mean, if I said three years ago, you should go see 10 concerts
a year and the concert tickets now cost $200 each. Now it's $2,000 a year to go see concerts.
Now I'm in charge of calculating inflation. So I redefine, you know, your entertainment quota for
the year to be eight Netflix streaming concerts. And now they don't cost $2,000. They cost nothing
and there is no inflation, but you don't get your concerts, right? So the problem starts with
continually changing the definition of the market basket. But in my opinion, that's not the biggest
problem. The more egregious problem is the fundamental idea that assets aren't products
or services. Assets can't be inflated. What's an asset?
A house, a share of Apple stock, a bond, a Bitcoin is an asset or a Picasso painting.
Not a consumable good, not an apple that you can eat.
Right. If I throw away an asset, then I'm not on the hook to track the inflation rate for it. So
what happens if I change the policy such that, let's take the classic example, a million dollar
bond at a 5% interest rate gives you $50,000 a year in risk-free income. You might retire on
$50,000 a year in a low cost jurisdiction. So the cost of social security or early retirement is
$1 million when the interest rate is 5%. During the crisis of March of 2020, the interest rate
went on a 10-year bond, went to 50 basis points. So now the cost of that bond is $10 million.
The cost of social security went from a million dollars to $10 million. So if you wanted to work
your entire life, save money, and then retire risk-free and live happily ever after on a $50,000
salary, live in on a beach in Mexico, wherever you wanted to go, you had hyperinflation. The cost of
your aspiration increased by a factor of 10 over the course of some amount of time. In fact, in
that case, that was over the course of about 12 years. As the inflation rate ground down, the
asset traded up. But the conventional view is, oh, that's not a problem because it's good that
assets, it's good that the bond is highly priced because we own the bond. Or what's the problem
with the inflation rate in housing being 19%? It's an awful problem for a 22-year-old that's starting
their first job, that's saving money to buy a house. But it would be characterized as a benefit
to society by a conventional economist who would say, well, housing asset values are higher because
of interest rate fluctuation, and now the economy has got more wealth. And so that's viewed as a
benefit. So what's being missed here? The suffering of the average person or the struggle, the
suffering, the pain of the average person, like metrics that captured that within the economic
system. Is it when you talk about- One way to say it is a conventional view of inflation as CPI
understates the human misery that's inflicted upon the working class and on mainstream companies
by the political class. And so it's a massive shift of wealth from the working class to the
property class. It's a massive shift of power from the free market to the centrally governed
or the controlled market. It's a massive shift of power from the people to the government.
And maybe one more illustrative point here, Alexis, is what do you think the inflation
rate's been for the past 100 years? Oh, you're talking about the scalar again?
If you took a survey of everybody on the street and you asked them what do they think inflation
was? What is it? You remember when Jerome Powell said our target's 2% but we're not there? If you
go around the corner, I have posted the deed to this house sold in 1930. Okay. And the number
on that deed is $100,000, 1930. And if you go on Zillow and you get the Z estimate-
Is it higher than that? No.
$30,500,000. So that's 92 years, 1930 or 2022, and in 92 years we've had 305x increase in price
of the house. Now, if you actually back calculate, you come to a conclusion that the inflation rate
was approximately 6.5% a year every year for 92 years. Okay. And there's nobody in government,
no conventional economists that would ever admit to an inflation rate of 7% a year in the US dollar
over the last century. Now, if you dig deeper, one guy that's done a great job working on this
is Seyfettin Amos who wrote the book The Bitcoin Standard. And he notes that on average, it looks
like the inflation rate and the money supply is about 7% a year all the way up to the year 2020.
If you look at the S&P index, which is a market basket of scarce desirable stocks,
it returned about 10%. If you talk to 10% a year for 100 years, the money supply is expanding at
7% a hundred years. If you actually talk to economists or you look at the economy and you
ask the question, how fast does the economy grow in its entirety year over year? Generally about
two to 3%. Like the sum total impact of all this technology and human ingenuity might get you a
two and a half, 3% improvement a year. As measured by GDP. Are you okay with that?
I'm not sure I'd go that far yet, but I would just say that if you had the human race doing stuff,
and if you ask the question, how much more efficiently will we do the stuff next year
than this year? Or what's the value of all of our innovations and inventions and investments
in the past 12 months? You'd be hard pressed to say we get 2% better. Typical investor thinks
they're 10% better every year. So if you look at what's going on, really, when you're holding a
million dollars of stocks and you're getting a 10% gain a year, you really get a 7% expansion
of the money supply. You're getting a two or 3% gain under best circumstances. And another way to
say that is if the money supply stopped expanding at 7% a year, the S&P yield might be 3% and not
10%. It probably should be. Now, that gets you to start to ask a bunch of other fundamental
questions. Like if I borrow a billion dollars and pay 3% interest and the money supply expands
at 7% to 10% a year, and I ended up making a 10% return on a billion dollar investment,
paying 3% interest, is that fair? And who suffered so that I could do that? Because in an environment
where you're just inflating the money supply and you're holding the assets constant, it stands the
reason that the price of all the assets is going to appreciate somewhat proportional to the money
supply. And the difference in asset appreciations is going to be a function of the scarce desirable
quality of the assets. And to what extent can I make more of them? And to what extent are they
truly limited in supply? Yeah. So we'll get to a lot of the words you said there, the scarcity
and so connected to how limited they are and the value of those assets. But you also said,
so the expansion of the money supply, which is put another way is printing money. And so is that
always bad, the expansion of the money supply? Just to put some terms on the table so we understand
them. You nonchalantly say it's always on average expanding every year, the money supply is expanding
every year by 7%. That's a bad thing? That's universally a bad thing? It's awful. I guess to
be precise, it's the currency. I would say money is monetary energy or economic energy.
And the economic energy has to find its way into a medium. So if you want to move it rapidly as a
medium of exchange has to find its way into currency. But the money can also flow into
property, like a house or gold. If the money flows into property, it'll probably hold its value much
better if the money flows into currency, right? If you had put $100,000 in this house, you would
have 305X return over 92 years. But if you had put the money, $100,000 in a safe deposit box and
buried it in the basement, you would have lost 99.7% of your wealth over the same time period.
So the expansion of the currency creates a massive inefficiency in the society, what I'll call an
adiabatic lapse. What we're doing is we're bleeding the civilization to death, right?
What's the adiabatic, what's that word?
Adiabatic lapse.
Adiabatic.
Right? In aerospace engineering, you want to solve any problem, they start with the phrase,
assume an adiabatic system. And what that means is a closed system. So I've got a container
and in that container, no air leaves and no air enters, no energy exits or enters,
so it's a closed system.
So you got the closed system lapse.
Okay. Okay. I'm going to use a-
There's a leak in the ship.
I'm going to use a physical metaphor for you because you're the jujitsu, right? Like you've
got 10 pints of blood in your body. And so before your next workout, I'm going to take one pint from
you. Now you're going to go exercise, but you've lost 10% of your blood. Okay? You're not going to
perform as well. It takes about one month for your body to replace the red blood platelets.
So what if I tell you every month you got to show up and I'm going to bleed you?
Yeah.
Okay. So if I'm draining the energy, I'm draining the blood from your body, you can't perform.
If you, adiabatic lapse is when you go up an altitude, every thousand feet, you lose three
degrees. You go 50,000 feet, you're 150 degrees colder than sea level. That's why you look at
your instruments and instead of 80 degrees, you're minus 70 degrees. Why is the temperature falling?
Temperature is falling because it's not a closed system. It's an open system. As the air expands,
the density falls, right? The energy per cubic whatever falls and therefore the temperature
falls, right? The heat's falling out of the solution. So when you're inflating,
let's say you're inflating the currency supply by 6%, you're sucking 6% of the energy
out of the fluid that the economy is using to function.
So the currency, this kind of ocean of currency, that's a nice way for the economy to function.
It's the most kind of, it's being inefficient when you expand the money supply, but it's
the liquid. I'm trying to find the right kind of adjective here. It's how you do transactions
at a scale of billions. Currency is the asset we use to move monetary energy around and you
could use the dollar or you could use the peso or you could use the bolivar. Selling houses and
buying houses is much more inefficient. Or like you can't transact between billions of people
with houses. Yeah. Properties don't make such good mediums of exchange. They make better stores
of value and they have utility value if it's a ship or a house or a plane or a bushel of corn,
right? Can I zoom out just for, can we zoom out? Keep zooming out until we reach the origin of
human civilization, but on the way, ask, you gave economists a D minus. I'm not even going to ask
what you give to governments. Do you think their failure, economists and government failure is
malevolence or incompetence? I think policymakers are well-intentioned, but generally all government
policy is inflationary. It's inflammatory and inflationary. So what I mean by that is
when you have a policy pursuing supply chain independence, if you have an energy policy,
if you have a labor policy, if you have a trade policy, if you have any kind of foreign policy,
a domestic policy, a manufacturing policy, every one of these, a medical policy, every one of these
policies interferes with the free market and generally prevents some rational actor from doing
it in a cheaper, more efficient way. So when you layer them on top of each other, they all have to
be paid for. If you want to shut down the entire economy for a year, you have to pay for it,
right? If you want to fight a war, you have to pay for it, right? If you don't want to use oil
or natural gas, you have to pay for it. If you don't want to manufacture semiconductors in China
and you want to manufacture them in the US, you got to pay for it. If I rebuild the entire supply
chain in Pennsylvania and I hire a bunch of employees and then I unionize the employees,
then not only am I, I idle the factory in the Far East, it goes to 50% capacity. So
whatever it sells, it has to raise the price on. And then I drive up the cost of labor for every
other manufacturer in the US because I'm competing against them, right? I'm changing that condition. So
everything gets less efficient, everything gets more expensive. And of course, the government
couldn't really pay for its policies and its wars with taxes. We didn't pay for World War I with tax.
We didn't pay for World War II with tax. We didn't pay for Vietnam with tax. In fact,
when you trace this, what you realize is the government never pays for all of its policies
with taxes. Because it's too painful to ask to raise the taxes to truly transparently pay for
the things you're doing with taxes, with taxpayer money, because they feel the pain. That's one
interpretation or it's just too transparent. If people understood the true cost-
Of war, they wouldn't want to go to war.
If you were told that you would lose 95% of your assets, you know, and 90% of everything you will
be ever will be taken from you, you might reprioritize your thought about a given policy
and you might not vote for that politician. But you're still saying incompetence,
not malevolence. So fundamentally, government creates a bureaucracy of incompetence,
is kind of how you look at it. I think a lack of humility, like if people
had more humility, then they would realize- Humility about how little they know,
how little they understand about the function of complex systems.
There's a phrase from Quanese to his movie Unforgiven, where he says,
a man's got to know his limitations. I think that a lot of people overestimate
what they can accomplish and experience. Experience in life causes you to re-evaluate that.
So I mean, I've done a lot of things in my life and generally, my mistakes were always
my good ideas that I enthusiastically pursued to the detriment of my great ideas that required
150% of my attention to prosper. So I think people pursue too many good ideas. They all
sound good, but there's just a limit to what you can accomplish. And everybody underestimates
the challenges of implementing an idea. And they always overestimate the benefits
of the pursuit of that. And so I think it's an overconfidence that causes an overexuberance
in pursuit of policies. And as the ambition of the government expands, so must the currency supply.
I could say the money supply, but let's say the currency supply.
You can triple the number of pesos in the economy, but it doesn't triple the amount of
manufacturing capacity in the said economy. And it doesn't triple the amount of assets
in the economy, it just triples the pesos. So as you increase the currency supply,
then the price of all those scarce desirable things will tend to go up rapidly.
And the confidence of all of the institutions, the corporations, and the individual actors
and trading partners will collapse.
LW. If we take a tangent on a tangent, and we will return soon to the big human civilization question.
So if government naturally wants to buy stuff it can't afford,
what's the best form of government? Anarchism, libertarianism. So not even,
there's not even armies, there's no borders, that's anarchism.
RL. The least.
LW. The smallest possible. The smallest possible.
RL. The best government would be the least, and the debate will be over that.
LW. When you think about this stuff, do you think about, okay, government is the way it is. I,
as a person that can generate great ideas, how do I operate in this world? Or do you also think
about the big picture, if we start a new civilization somewhere on Mars, do you think
about what's the ultimate form of government? What's at least a promising thing to try?
RL. You know, I have laser eyes on my profile on Twitter, Lex.
LW. What does that mean?
RL. And the significance of laser eyes is to focus on the thing that can make a difference.
And if I look at the civilization, I would say half the problems in the civilization
are due to the fact that our understanding of economics and money is defective.
Half. 50%. I don't know, it's worth $500 trillion worth of problems. Like, money represents all the
economic energy in the civilization, and it kind of equates to all the products, all the services,
and all the assets that we have and we're ever gonna have. So that's half. The other half of
the problems in the civilization are medical and military and political and philosophical
and natural. And I think that there are a lot of different solutions to all those problems,
and they are all honorable professions, and they all merit a lifetime of consideration
for the specialists in all those areas. I think that what I could offer that's constructive is
inflation is completely misunderstood. It's a much bigger problem than we understand it to be.
We need to introduce engineering and science techniques into economics if we want to further
the human condition. All government policy is inflationary. And another pernicious myth
is inflation is always and everywhere a monetary phenomena. A famous quote by Milton Friedman,
I believe, it's like, it's a monetary phenomena, that is inflation comes from expanding the
currency supply. It's a nice phrase, and it's oftentimes quoted by people that are anti-inflation,
but again, it just signifies a lack of appreciation of what the issue is.
If I had a currency which was completely non-inflationary, if I never printed another
dollar, and if I eliminated fractional reserve banking from the face of the earth,
we'd still have inflation. And we have inflation as long as we have government that is capable of
pursuing any kind of policies that are in themself inflationary, and generally they all are.
So in general, inflationary is the big characteristic of human nature that
government's collection of groups that have power over others and allocate other people's resources
will try to intentionally or not hide the costs of those allocations. Like in some
some tricky ways, whatever the options are available. Hiding the cost is like the tertiary
thing. The primary goal is the government will attempt to do good. That's the primary problem?
They will attempt to do good, and they will do good imperfectly, and they will create oftentimes
as much damage, more damage than the good they do. Most government policy will be iatrogenic.
It will create more harm than good in the pursuit of it, but it is what it is.
The secondary issue is they will unintentionally pay for it by expanding the currency supply
without realizing that they're actually paying for it in a suboptimal fashion.
They'll collapse their own currencies while they attempt to do good. The tertiary issue is
they will mismeasure how badly they're collapsing the currency. So for example, if you go to the
Bureau of Labor Statistics and look at the numbers printed by the Fed, they'll say,
oh, it looks like the dollar has lost 95% of its purchasing power over 100 years. Okay,
they sort of fess up that there's a problem, but they make it 95% loss over 100 years. What they
don't do is realize it's a 99.7% loss over 80 years. So they will mismeasure just the horrific
extent of the monetary policy in pursuit of the foreign policy and the domestic policy,
which they overestimate their budget and their means to accomplish their ends, and they
underestimate the cost. And they're oblivious to the horrific damage that they do to the
civilization because the mental models that they use that are conventionally taught are wrong,
right? The mental model that, like, it's okay, we can print all this money because the velocity of
the money is low, right? Because money velocity is a scalar and inflation is the scalar, and we
don't see 2% inflation yet and the money velocity is low, and so it's okay if we print trillions of
dollars. Well, the money velocity was immediate, right? The velocity of money through the crypto
economy is 10,000 times faster than the velocity of money through the consumer economy, right? I
think Nick pointed out when you spoke to him, he said it takes two months for a credit card
transaction to settle, right? So you want to spend a million dollars in the consumer economy,
you can move it six times a year. You put a million dollars into gold, gold will sit in a
vault for a decade, okay? So the velocity of money through gold is 0.1. You put the money in the stock
market and you can trade it once a week, the settlement is T plus 2, maybe you get to 2 to
1 leverage. You might get to a money velocity of 100 a year in the stock market. You put your money
into the crypto economy and these people are settling every four hours. And if you're offshore,
they're trading with 20x leverage. So if you settle every day and you trade with 20x leverage,
you just went to 7,000. So the velocity of the money varies. I think the politicians,
they don't really understand inflation and they don't understand economics, but you can't blame
them because the economists don't understand economics. Because if they did, they would be
creating multivariate computer simulations where they actually put in the price of every piece of
housing in every city in the world, the full array of foods, and the full array of products,
and the full array of assets. And then on a monthly basis, they would publish all those
results. And that's a high bandwidth requirement. And I think that people don't really want to
embrace it. And also, the most pernicious thing, there's that phrase, you can't tell people what
to think, but you can tell them what to think about. The most pernicious thing is, I get you
to misunderstand the phenomena so that even when it's happening to you, you don't appreciate that
it's a bad thing and you think it's a good thing. So if housing prices are going up 20% year over
year and I say, this is great for the American public because most of them are homeowners,
then I have misrepresented a phenomena. Inflation is 20%, not 7%. And then I have misrepresented it
as being a positive rather than a negative. And people will stare at it and you could even show
them their house on fire and they would perceive it as being great because it's warming them up
and they're going to save on their heat cost. It does seem that the cruder the model, whether
it's economics or their psychology, the easier it is to weave whatever the heck narrative you want
and not in a malicious way, but just like it's some kind of emergent phenomena, this narrative
thing that we tell ourselves. So you can tell any kind of story about inflation. Inflation is good,
inflation is bad. The cruder the model, the easier it is to tell a narrative about it.
So if you take an engineering approach, I feel like it becomes more and more difficult
to run away from a true deep understanding of the dynamics of the system.
I mean, honestly, if you went to a hundred people on the street and you asked them to define
inflation, how many would say it's a vector tracking the change in price of every product
service asset in the world over time? Not many. Now, if you went to them and you said,
do you think 2% inflation a year is good or bad? The majority would probably say,
well, I hear it's good. The majority of economists would say 2% inflation a year is good.
And of course, look at the ship next to us. What if I told you that the ship leaked 2% of its
volume every something, right? The ship is rotting 2% a year. That means the useful life of the ship
is 50 years. Now, ironically, that's true. Like a wooden ship had a 50 year to a hundred year life,
100 would be long, 50 years, not unlikely. So when we built ships out of wood, they had a useful
life of about 50 years and then they sunk, they rotted. There's nothing good about it, right? You
build a ship out of steel and it's zero as opposed to 2% degradation. And how much better is 0%
versus 2%? Well, 2% means you have a useful life of, it's half-life of 35 years. 2% is a half-life
of 35 years. That's basically the half-life of money and gold. If I store your life force in
gold, under perfect circumstances, you have a useful life of 35 years. 0% is a useful life of
forever. So 0% is immortal. 2% is 35 years average life expectancy. So the idea that you would think
the life expectancy of the currency and the civilization should be 35 years instead of
forever is kind of a silly notion. But the tragic notion is it was, you know, 7 into 7,
or 10 years. The money has had a half-life of 10 years, except for the fact that in weak societies
in Argentina or the like, the half-life of the money is three to four years, in Venezuela,
one year. So the United States dollar and the United States economic system was the most
successful economic system in the last 100 years in the world. We won every war. We were the world's
superpower. Our currency lost 99.7% of its value. And that means, horrifically, every other currency
lost everything. In essence, the other ones were 99.9%, except for most that were 100% because they
all completely failed. And you've got a mainstream economic community that thinks that inflation is
a number and 2% is desirable. It's kind of like, you know, remember George Washington? You know
how he died? Well-meaning physicians bled him to death. Okay, the last thing in the world you would
want to do to a sick person is bleed them, right? In the modern world, I think we understand that
oxygen is carried by the blood cells. And there's that triage phrase, what's the first thing you do
in an injury? Stop the bleeding. Single first thing, right? You show up after any accident,
I look at you, stop the bleeding because you're going to be dead in a matter of minutes if you
bleed out. So it strikes me as being ironic that orthodox conventional wisdom was bleed the patient
to death. And this was the most important patient in the country, maybe in the history of the
country, and we bled him to death trying to help him. So when you're actually inflating the money
supply at 7%, but you're calling it 2% because you want to help the economy, you're literally
bleeding the free market to death. But the sad fact is George Washington went along with it
because he thought that they were going to do him good. And the majority of the society,
most companies, most conventional thinkers, you know, the working class, they go along with this
because they think that someone has their best interests at mind and the people that are bleeding
them to death believe, they believe that prescription because their mental models are
just so defective. And their understanding of energy and engineering and the economics that
are at play is crippled by these mental models. But that's both the bug in the future of human
civilization, that ideas take hold, they unite us, we believe in them,
and we make a lot of cool stuff happen by, as an average, sort of, just the fact of the matter,
a lot of people believe the same thing, they get together, and they get some shit done because
they believe that thing. And then some ideas can be really bad and really destructive,
but on average, the ideas seem to be progressing in a direction of good. Let me just step back.
What the hell are we doing here, us humans on this earth? How do you think of humans? How special
are humans? How did human civilization originate on this earth? And what is this human project
that we're all taking on? You mentioned fire and water and apparently bleeding you to death is not
a good idea. I always thought you can get the demons out in that way, but that was a recent
invention. So what's this thing we're doing here? I think what distinguishes human beings from
all the other creatures on the earth is our ability to engineer. We're engineers, right?
To solve problems or just build incredible cool things? Engineering,
harnessing energy and technique to make the world a better place than you found it, right?
But from the point that we actually started to play with fire, right? That was a big leap forward.
Harnessing the power of kinetic energy and missiles, another step forward. Every city
built on water. Why water? Well, water is bringing energy, right? If you actually put a turbine
on a river or you capture a change in elevation of water, you've literally harnessed gravitational
energy. But water is also bringing you food. It's also giving you a cheap form of getting
rid of your waste. It's also giving you free transportation. You want to move one ton blocks
around. You want to move them in water. So I think, I mean, the human story is really the story
of engineering a better world. And the rise in the human condition is determined by those groups
of people, those civilizations that were best at harnessing energy, right? If you look, you know,
the Greek civilization, they built it around ports and seaports and water and created a trading
network. The Romans were really good at harnessing all sorts of engineering. I mean, the aqueducts are
a great example. If you go to any big city, you travel through cities and you see all these
people. If you go to any big city, you travel through cities in the Med, you find that, you
know, the carrying capacity of the city or the island is 5,000 people without running water.
And then if you can find a way to bring water to it, it increases by a factor of 10.
And so human flourishing is really only possible through that channeling of energy,
right? That eventually takes the form of air power, right? I mean, that ship, I mean, look
at the intricacy of those sails, right? I mean, it's just the model is intricate. Now, think about
all of the experimentation that took place to figure out how many sails to put on that ship and
how to rig them and how to repair them and how to operate them.
And it's thousands of lives spent thinking through all the tiny little details, all to increase the
efficiency of this, the effectiveness, the efficiency of this ship as it sails through
water. And we should also note there's a bunch of cannons on the side. So, obviously.
Another form of engineering, right? Energy harnessing with explosives.
To achieve what end? That's another discussion, exactly.
Suppose we're trying to get off the planet, right? I mean...
Well, there's a selection mechanism going on. So, natural selection,
this, whatever, however evolution works, it seems that one of the interesting inventions on earth
was the predator-prey dynamic, that you want to be the bigger fish.
That violence seems to serve a useful purpose if you look at earth as a whole. We, as humans,
now like to think of violence as really a bad thing. It seems to be one of the
amazing things about humans is we're ultimately tend towards cooperation.
We want to, we like peace. If you just look at history, we want things to be nice and calm and
but just wars break out every once in a while and lead to immense suffering and destruction
and so on. And they have a kind of, like, resetting the palette effect.
It's one that's full of just immeasurable human suffering, but it's like a way to start over.
We're quite the apex predator on the planet. And I googled something the other day,
you know, what's the most common form of mammal life on the earth?
By number of organisms?
Count.
By count.
And the answer that came back was human beings. I was shocked. I couldn't believe it, right? It
says, like, apparently, if we're just looking at mammals, the answer was human beings are the most
common, which was very interesting to me. I almost didn't believe it, but I was trying to, you know,
8 billion or so human beings. There's no other mammal that's got more than 8 billion.
If you walk through downtown Edinburgh and Scotland and you look up on this hill and this
castle up on the hill, you know, and you talk to people and the story is, oh, yeah, well, that was
a British castle before it was a Scottish castle, before it was a Pict castle, before it was a Roman
castle, before it was, you know, some other Celtic castle. Then they found 13 prehistoric castles
buried one under the other under the other. And you get the conclusion that 100,000 years ago,
somebody showed up and grabbed the high point, the apex of the city, and they built a stronghold
there and they flourished and their family flourished and their tribe flourished until
someone came along and knocked them off the hill. And it's been a nonstop, never-ending fight
by the aggressive, most powerful entity, family, organization, municipality, tribe, whatever.
All for the hill.
For that one hill going back since time immemorial. And, you know, you scratch your head and you
think it seems like it's like just this never-ending wheel.
But doesn't that lead, if you just, all kinds of metrics, that seems to improve the quality
of our cannons and ships as a result. Like, it seems that war, just like your laser eyes,
focuses the mind on the engineering tasks.
It is that. And it does remind you that the winner is always the most powerful.
And we throw that phrase out, but no one thinks about what that phrase means. Like,
who's the most powerful or the, you know, or the most powerful side one, but they don't think
about it. And they think about power, energy delivered in a period of time. And then you think
a guy with a spear is more powerful than someone with their fist and someone with a bow and arrow
is more powerful than the person with the spear. And then you realize that somebody with bronze
is more powerful than without, and steel is more powerful than bronze. And if you look
at the Romans, you know, they persevered, you know, with artillery and they could stand
off from 800 meters and blast you to smithereens, right? You know, you study the history of the
Balearic slingers, right? And, you know, you think we invented bullets, but they invented
bullets to put in slings thousands of years ago. They could have stood off 500 meters and put a
hole in your head, right? And so there was never a time when humanity wasn't vying to come up with
an asymmetric form of projecting their own power via technology.
And absolute power is when a leader is able to control a large amount of humans, they're
facing the same direction, working in the same direction to leverage energy.
The most organized society wins.
Yeah.
When the Romans were dominating everybody, they were the most organized civilization
in Europe. And as long as they stayed organized, they dominated. And at some point they over
expanded and got disorganized and they collapsed. And I guess you could say that, you know,
the struggle of the human condition, it catalyzes the development of new technologies one after the
other. It penalizes anybody that rejects ocean power, right? Gets penalized, you reject artillery,
you get penalized, you reject atomic power, you get penalized. If you reject digital power,
cyber power, you get penalized. And the underlying control of the property keeps shifting,
property keeps shifting hands from, you know, one institution or one government to another
based upon how rationally they're able to channel that energy and how well organized
or coordinated they are.
Well, that's a really interesting thing about both the human mind and governments
that they, once they get a few good, and companies, once they get a few good ideas,
they seem to stick with them. They reject new ideas. It's almost whether that's emergent or
however that evolved, it seems to have a really interesting effect because when you're young,
you fight for the new ideas. You push them through, then a few of us humans find success,
then we get complacent, we take over the world using that new idea, and then the new young
person with the better new idea challenges you and you, as opposed to pivoting, you stick
with the old and lose because of it. And that's how empires collapse. And it's just both at
the individual level that happens when two academics fighting about ideas or something
like that. And at the human civilization level, governments, they hold on to the ideas of old.
It's fascinating.
An ever persistent theme in the history of science is the paradigm shift. And the paradigms
shift when the old guard dies and a new generation arrives, or the paradigm shifts when there's a
war, and everyone that disagrees with the idea of aviation finds bombs dropping on their head,
or everyone that disagrees with whatever your technology is, has a rude awakening. And
if they totally disagree, their society collapses and they're replaced by that new thing.
A lot of the engineering you talked about had to do with ships and cannons and leveraging
water. What about this whole digital thing that's happening, been happening over the past century?
Is that still engineering in your mind? You're starting to operate in these bits of information.
I think there's two big ideas. The first wave of ideas were digital information.
And that was the internet wave been running since 1990 or so, for 30 years. And the second
wave is digital energy. So if I look at digital information, this idea that we want to digitally
transform a book, I'm going to dematerialize every book in this room into bits, and then I'm going to
deliver a copy of the entire library to a billion people, and I'm going to do it for pretty much
de minimis electricity. If I can dematerialize music, books, education, entertainment, maps,
right? That is an incredibly exothermic transaction. It's a crystallization when we
collapse into a lower energy state as a civilization, and we give off massive
amounts of energy. If you look at what Carnegie did, the richest man in the world created libraries
everywhere at the time, and he gave away his entire fortune. And now we can give a better
library to every six-year-old for nothing. And so what's the value of giving a million books to
eight billion people? That's the explosion in prosperity that comes from digital transformation.
And when we do it with maps, I transform the map, I put it into a car, you get in the car,
and the car drives you where you want to go with the map. And how much better is that than
a Rand McNally atlas right here? It's like a million times better. So the first wave
of digital transformation was the dematerialization of all of these informational things which are
non-conservative. I could take Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, played for by the best orchestra in
Germany, and I could give it to a billion people and they could play it a thousand times each at
less than the cost of the one performance, right? So I deliver culture and education and education
and intelligence and insight to the entire civilization over digital rails. And the
consequences of the human race are first order, generally good, right? The world is a better
place, it drives growth, and you create these trillion dollar entities like Apple and Amazon
and Facebook and Google and Microsoft, right? That is the first wave. The second wave...
I do mind, I'm sorry to interrupt, but that first wave, it feels like the impact that's positive,
you said the first order impact is generally positive, it feels like it's positive in a way
that nothing else in history has been positive. And then we may not actually truly be able to
understand the orders of magnitude of increase in productivity, in just progress of human
civilization, until we look back centuries from now. It just feels, or maybe I'm, like just
looking at the impact of Wikipedia, the giving access to basic wisdom or basic knowledge and
then perhaps wisdom to billions of people. If you can just linger on that for a second. What's
your sense of the impact of that?
You know, I would say if you're a technologist philosopher,
the impact of a technology is so much greater on the civilization and the human condition
than a non-technology that is almost not worth your trouble to bother trying to fix things
a conventional way. So let's take an example. I have a foundation, the Saylor Academy, and the
Saylor Academy gives away free education, free college education to anybody on Earth that wants
it. And we've had more than a million students. And if you go and you take the physics class,
the lecturers were by the same physics lecturer that taught me physics at MIT. Except when I was
at MIT, the cost of the first four weeks of MIT would have drained my family's life, collective
life savings for the first last hundred years. Like a hundred years worth of my father, my
grandfather, my great-grandfather, they saved every penny they had after a hundred years. They
could have paid for one week or two weeks of MIT, but they didn't. They didn't. They didn't.
Two weeks of MIT, that's how fiendishly expensive and inefficient it was. So I went on scholarship.
I was lucky to have a scholarship. But on the other hand, I sat in the back of the
801 lecture hall, and I was like right up in the rafters. It's an awful experience on these
uncomfortable wooden benches, and you can barely see the blackboard. And you got to be there
synchronously. And the stuff we upload, you can start it and stop it and watch it on your iPad
or watch it on your computer and rewind it multiple times and sit in a comfortable chair,
and you can do it from anywhere on earth, and it's absolutely free. So I think about this,
and I think you want to improve the human condition. You need people with postgraduate
level education. You need PhDs. And I know this sounds kind of elitist, but you want to cure
cancer, and you want to go to the stars, fusion drive. We need new propulsion. We need extraordinary
breakthroughs in every area of basic science, be it biology or propulsion or material science or
computer science. You're not doing that with an undergraduate degree. You're certainly not doing
it with a high school education, but the cost of a PhD is like a million bucks. There's like 10
million PhDs in the world if you check it out. There's 8 billion people in the world. How many
people could get a PhD or would want to? Maybe not 8 billion, but a billion? 500 million? Let's just
say 500 million to a billion. How do you go from 10 million to a billion highly educated people,
all of them specializing in, and I don't have to tell you how many different fields of human
endeavor there are. I mean, your life is interviewing these experts, and there's so many,
right? It's amazing. So how do I give a multi-million dollar education to a billion
people? And there's two choices. You can either endow a scholarship, in which case you pay $75,000
a year. Okay, $75,000. Let's pay a million dollars a person. I can do it that way.
Even if you had a trillion dollars, if you had $10 trillion to throw at the problem,
and we've just thrown $10 trillion at certain problems, you don't solve the problem, right?
If I put $10 trillion on the table and I said educate everybody, give them all a PhD,
you still wouldn't solve the problem. Harvard University can't educate 18,000 people
simultaneously, or 87,000, or 800,000, or 8 million. So you have to dematerialize the
professor and dematerialize the experience. So you put it all as streaming, on-demand,
computer-generated education, and you create simulations where you need to create simulations,
and you upload it. It's like the human condition is being held back by 500,000 well-meaning
average algebra teachers. I love them. I mean, please don't take offense if you're an algebra
teacher, but instead of 500,000 algebra teachers going through the same motion over and over again,
what you need is like one, or five, or 10 really good algebra teachers, and they need to do it a
billion times a day, or a billion times a year for free. And if we do that, there's no reason
why you can't give infinite education, certainly in science, technology, engineering, and math,
right? Infinite education to everybody with no constraint. And I think the same is true,
right? With just about every other thing. If you want to bring joy to the world, you need digital
music. If you want to bring enlightenment to the world, you need digital education. If you want to
bring anything of consequence in the world, you got to digitally transform it, and then you got
to manufacture it something like a hundred times more efficiently as a start, but a million times
more efficiently is probably, you know, that's hopeful. Maybe you have a chance. And if you look
at all of these space endeavors and everything we're thinking about getting to Mars, getting off
the planet, getting to other worlds, number one thing you got to do is you got to make a
fundamental breakthrough in an engine. People dreamed about flying for thousands of years,
but until the internal combustion engine, you didn't have enough, you know, enough energy,
enough power in a light enough package in order to solve the problem. And the human race has all
sorts of those fundamental engines and materials and techniques that we need to master. And each
one of them is a lifetime of experimentation of someone capable of making a seminal contribution
to the body of human knowledge. There's certain problems like education that could be solved
through this process of dematerialization. And by the way, to give props to the 500k algebra teachers,
when I look at YouTube, for example, one possible approach is each one of those 500,000 teachers
probably had days and moments of brilliance. And if they had the ability to contribute to
in the natural selection process, like the market of education where the best ones rise up,
that's a really interesting way, which is like the best day of your life, the best lesson you've ever
taught could be found and sort of broadcast to billions of people. So all of those kinds of ideas
can be made real in the digital world. Now traveling across planets, you still can't solve
that problem with dematerialization. What you could solve potentially is dematerializing the
human brain where you can transfer, like you don't need to have astronauts on the ship.
You can have a floppy disk carrying a human brain.
Touching on those points, you'd love for the 500,000 algebra teachers to become 500,000
math specialists, and maybe they clump into 50,000 specialties as teams and they all pursue
50,000 new problems and they put their algebra teaching on autopilot. That's the same as when
I give you 11 cents worth of electricity and you don't have to row a boat eight hours a day before
you can eat. It would be a lot better that you would pay for your food in the first eight seconds
of your day and then you could start thinking about other things, right? With regard to
technology, one thing that I learned studying technology when you look at S curves is
until you start the S curve, you don't know whether you're a hundred years from viability,
a thousand years from viability, or a few months from viability.
Isn't that fun? That's so fun. The early part of the S curve is so fun because you don't know.
In 1900, you could have got any number of learned academics to give you 10,000 reasons why
humans will never fly, right? And in 1903, the Wright brothers flew and by 1969,
we're walking on the moon. So the advance that we made in that field was extraordinary,
but for the hundred years and 200 years before, they were just back and forth and nobody was
close. And that's the happy part. The happy part is we went from flying 20 miles an hour or whatever
to flying 25,000 miles an hour in 66 years. The unhappy part is I studied aeronautical
engineering at MIT in the 80s. And in the 80s, we had Gulfstream aircraft, we had Boeing 737s,
we had the Space Shuttle. And you fast forward 40 years and we pretty much had the same exact
aircraft. The efficiency of the engines was 20, 30% more, right? We slammed into a brick wall
around 69 to 75. Like in fact, the Global Express, the Gulfstream, these were all engineered
in the 70s, some in the 60s. The fuselage silhouette of a Gulfstream of a G5 was the
same shape as a G4, is the same shape as a G3, is the same shape as a G2. And that's because they
were afraid to change the shape for 40 years because they worked it out in a wind tunnel,
they knew it worked. And when they finally decided to change the shape, it was like a
$10 billion exercise with modern supercomputers and computational fluid dynamics.
Why was it so hard? What is that wall made of that you slammed into?
The right question is so why does a guy that went to MIT that got an aeronautical engineering degree
spend his career in software? Like why is it that I never a day in my life,
you know, with the exception of some Air Force Reserve work, I never got paid to be
an aeronautical engineer and I worked in software engineering my entire career.
Maybe software engineering is the new aeronautical engineering in some way.
Maybe, like, maybe you hit fundamental walls uncertain until you have to return to it centuries
later. Or no?
The National Gallery of Art was endowed by a very rich man,
Andrew Mellon, and you know how he made his money? Aluminum. Okay? And so,
and you know what kind of airplanes you can create without aluminum? Nothing. Nothing, right?
So it's a materials problem.
Okay, so 1900, we made massive advances in metallurgy, right? I mean, that was US steel.
That was iron to steel, aluminum, massive fortunes were created because this was a massive technical
advance. And then we also had the internal combustion engine and, you know, the story of
Ford and General Motors and Daimler Chrysler and the like is informed by that. So you have no jet
engines, no rocket motors, no internal combustion engines, you have no aviation. But even if you had
those engines, if you were trying to build those things with steel, no chance. You had to have
aluminum. So there's like two pretty basic technologies. And once you have those two
technologies, stuff happens very fast. So tell me the last big advance in like jet engines,
there hasn't been one. Like there has the last big advance in rocket engines. Has it been one?
The big advances in spaceship design from what I can see are in the control systems,
the gyros and the ability to land, right, in a stable fashion. That's pretty amazing,
landing a rocket.
Also in the, at least according to Elon and so on, the manufacture of the more efficient
and less expensive manufacture of rockets. So like it's a production, whatever that you call
that discipline of at scale manufacture, at scale production, so factory work. But it's not 10X.
I mean, maybe it's 10X over a period of a few decades.
When we figure out how to operate a spaceship, you know, on the water in your water bottle for
a year. Right? Now, then you've got a breakthrough. So the bottom line is propulsion, propellant,
propulsion technology, propellants and the materials technology, they were critical to
getting on that aviation S-curve. And then we slammed into a wall in the 70s. And the Boeing
747, the Global Express, the Gulfstream, these things were the space shuttle. They were all
pretty much reflective of that. And then we kind of, then we stopped. And at that point,
you have to switch to a new S-curve. So the next equivalent to the internal combustion engine was
the CPU. And the next aluminum equivalent was silicon. So when we actually started developing
CPUs, the transistor gave way to CPUs. And if you look at the power, right, the bandwidth that we
had on computers and Moore's law, right, what if the efficiency of jet engines had doubled
every three years, right, in the last 40 years, where we'd be right now, right. So I think that
if you're a business person, if you're looking for commercially viable application of your mind,
then you have to find that S-curve. And ideally, you have to find it in the first five, six, ten
years. But people always miss this. Let's take Google Glass, right? Google Glass was an idea
2013. The year is 2022. And people were quite sure this was going to be a big thing.
And it could have been at the beginning of the S-curve.
But fundamentally, we didn't really have an effective mechanism. I mean, people getting
vertigo and they're, you know.
But you didn't know that at the beginning of the S-curve, right? I mean, maybe some people
had a deep intuition about the fundamentals of augmented reality. But you don't know that.
You don't have those. You're looking through the fog. You don't know.
So the point is, we're year zero in 2013, and we're still year zero in 2022 on that augmented
reality. And when somebody puts out a set of glasses that you can wear comfortably without
getting vertigo, right, without any disorientation that managed to have the stability and the
bandwidth necessary to sync with the real world, you'll be in year one. And from that
point, you'll have a 70-year or some interesting future until you slam into a limit to growth.
And then it'll slow down. And this is the story of a lot of things, right? I mean, John
D. Rockefeller got in the oil business in the 1860s. And the oil business as we understood
it, you know, became fairly mature, you know, by the 1920s, the 30s. And then it actually
stayed that way until we got to fracking, which was like seven years later, and then
it burst forward. So...
The interesting story about Moore's law, though, is that you get this, like, constant burst
of S curves on top of S curves on top of S curves. It's like the moment you start slowing
down, or almost ahead of you slowing down, you come up with another innovation, another
innovation. So Moore's law doesn't seem to happen in every technological advancement.
It seems like you only get a couple of S curves and then you're done for a bit. So I wonder
what the pressures there are that resulted in such success over several decades and still
going.
Humility dictates that nobody knows when the S curve kicks off and you could be 20 years
early or 100 years early. Leonardo da Vinci, you know, they were Michelangelo, they were
designing flying machines hundreds and hundreds of years ago. So humility says you're not
quite sure when it's when you really hit that commercial viability. And it also dictates
you don't know when it ends. Like, when will the party stop? When will Moore's law stop
and we'll get to the point where they're exponentially diminishing returns on silicon
performance? And just like we got exponentially diminishing returns on jet engines, you know,
and it just takes an exponential increase in effort to make it 10% better. But while
you're in the middle of it, then you know you can do things. So the reason that the
digital revolution is so important is because the underlying platforms, the bandwidth of
and the performance of the components, and I said the components are the radio protocols,
mobile protocols, the batteries, the CPUs, and the displays, right? Those four components
are pretty critical. They're all critical in the creation of an iPhone. I wrote about
it in the book The Mobile Wave, and they catalyzed this entire mobile revolution. Because they
have advanced and continue to advance, they created the very fertile environment for all
these digital transformations. And the digital transformations themselves, right, they call
for creativity in their own, right? Like, I think the interesting thing about, let's
take digital maps, right? When you conceptualize something as a dematerialized map, right,
it becomes a map because I can put it on a display like an iPad, or I can put it in a
car like a Tesla. But if you really want to figure it out, you can't think like an engineer,
you need to think like a fantasy writer. Like, this is where it's useful if you studied,
if you read, played Dungeons and Dragons, and you read Lord of the Rings, and you
studied all the fantasy literature. Because when I dematerialize the map,
first I put 10 million pages of satellite imagery into the map, right? That's a simple
physical transform. But then I start to put telemetry into the map, and I keep track of
the traffic rates on the roads, and I tell you whether you'll be in a traffic jam if
you drive that way, and I tell you which way to drive. And then I start to get feedback
on where you're going, and I tell you the restaurant's closed, and people don't like
it anyway. And then I put an AI on top of it, and I have it drive your car for you.
And eventually, the implication of digital transformation of maps is, I get in a self
driving car, and I say, take me someplace cool where I can eat. Right? And how did you
get to that last step, right? It wasn't simple engineering. There's a bit of fantasy in there,
a bit of magic. Design, art, whatever the heck you call it. It's whatever, yeah, fantasy
injects magic into the engineering process. Imagination precedes great revolutions in
engineering. It's like imagining a world of what you can do with the display. How will
the interaction be? That's where Google Glass actually came in. Augmented reality, virtual
reality, people were playing in the space of sci-fi. Imagination.
They called a moan shot. They tried. It didn't work. But to their credit, they stopped trying,
right? And then there's new people. They keep dreaming. Dreamers all around us. I love those
dreamers. And most of them fail and suffer because of it. But some of them win Nobel
Prizes or become billionaires. Well, what I would say is, if half the civilization dropped
what they were doing tomorrow, and eagerly started working on launching a rocket to Alpha
Centauri, it might not be the best use of our resources. Because it's kind of like if half
of Athens in the year 500 BC eagerly started working on flying machines, if you went back
and you said, what advice would you give them? You would say, it's not going to work until
you get to aluminum. And you're not going to get to aluminum until you work out the
steel and certain other things. And you're not going to get to that until you work out
the calculus of variations and some metallurgy. And there's a dude, Newton, that won't come
along for quite a while. And he's going to give you the calculus to do it. And until
then, it's hopeless. So you might be better off to work on the aqueduct or to focus upon
sales or something. So if I look at this today, I say there's massive, profound
civilization advances to be made through digital transformation of information. And you can see
them. This is the story of today. This is not the story of today, right? It's 10 years old,
what we've been seeing. We're living through different manifestations of that story today,
too, though. Like social media, the effects of that is very interesting. Because ideas
spread even, you talk about velocity of money, the velocity of ideas keeps increasing. So like
Wikipedia is a passive store. It's a store of knowledge. Twitter is like a water hose or
something. It's like spraying you with knowledge, whether you want it or not. It's like social
media is just like this explosion of ideas. And then we pick them up. And then we try to
understand ourselves because the drama of it also plays with our human psyche. So sometimes
there's more ability for misinformation, for propaganda to take hold. So we get to learn
about ourselves. We get to learn about the technology that can decelerate the propaganda,
for example, all that kind of stuff. But like the reality is we're living, I feel like we're
living through a singularity in the digital information space. And we're not, we don't have
a great understanding of exactly how it's transforming our lives. This is where money is
useful as a metaphor for significance. Because if money is the economic energy of the
civilization, then something that's extraordinarily lucrative that's going to generate a monetary or
wealth increase is a way to increase the net energy in the civilization. And ultimately,
if we had 10 times as much of everything, we'd have a lot more free resources to pursue all of
our advanced scientific and mathematical and theoretical endeavors. So let's take Twitter.
Twitter is something that could be 10 times more valuable than it is. Twitter could be made 10 times
better. No, by the way, I should say that people should follow you on Twitter. Your
Twitter account is awesome. Thank you. It could be made 10 times better. Yeah. Yeah,
Twitter can be made 10 times better. If we take YouTube or take education,
we could generate a billion PhDs. And the question is, do you need any profound
breakthrough in materials or technology to do that? And the answer is not really.
Right. So if you want to, you could make Apple, Amazon, Facebook, Google, Twitter,
all these things better. The United States government, if they took 1% of the money they
spend on the Department of Education, and they simply poured it into digital education, and they
gave degrees to people that actually met those requirements, they could provide 100x as much
education for one one-hundredth of the cost, and they could do it with no new technology. That's a
marketing and political challenge. So I don't think every objective is equally practical. And I think
the benefit of being an engineer or thinking about practical achievements is when the government
pursues an impractical objective, or when anybody, an entrepreneur, not so bad with entrepreneur,
because they don't have that much money to waste. When a government pursues an impractical objective,
they squander trillions and trillions of dollars and achieve nothing. Whereas if they pursue a
practical objective, or if they simply get out of the way and do nothing, and they allow the free
market to pursue the practical objectives, then I think you can have profound impact on the human
civilization. And if I look at the world we're in today, I think that there are multi-trillion,
10, 20, 50 trillion dollars worth of opportunities in the digital information realm yet to be
obtained. But there's hundreds of trillions of dollars of opportunities in the digital energy
realm that not only are they not obtained, the majority of people don't even know what digital
energy is. Most of them would reject the concept. They're not looking for it. They're not expecting
to find it. It's inconceivable because it is a paradigm shift. But in fact, it's completely
practical. Right under our nose, it's staring at us, and it could make the entire civilization
work dramatically better in every respect. So you mentioned in the digital world, digital
information is one, digital energy is two, and the possible impact on the world and the set of
opportunities available in the digital energy space is much greater. So how do you think about
digital energy? What is it? So I'll start with Tesla. He had a very famous quote. He said,
if you want to understand the universe, think in terms of energy, vibration, and frequency. And
it gets you thinking about what is the universe. And of course, the universe is just all energy.
And then what is matter? Matter is low-frequency energy. And what are we? You know, we're
vibrating from, you know, ashes to ashes, dust to dust. I can turn a tree into light. I can turn
light back into a tree. If I consider the entire universe, and it's very important because we don't
really think this way. Let's take the New York disco model. If I walk into a nightclub, and
there's loud music blaring in New York City, what's really going on there? Right? If you
blast out 14 billion years ago, the universe is formed. Okay, that's a low-frequency thing,
the universe. Four and a half billion years ago, the sun, maybe the earth, are formed.
The continents are 400 million years old. The schist that New York City is on is some hundreds
of millions of years. But the Hudson River is only 20,000 years. There's a building that's
probably 50 years old. There's a company operating that disco or that club, which is five to 10 years
old. There's a person, a customer walking in there for an experience for a few hours.
There's music that's oscillating at some kilohertz, and then there's light.
And you have all forms of energy, all frequencies, right? All layered, all moving through different
medium. And how you perceive the world is the question of at what frequency do you want to
perceive the world? And I think that once you start to think that way, you're catalyzed to
think about what would digital energy look like? And why would I want it? And what is it? So,
why don't we just start right there? What is it? The most famous manifestation of digital energy
is Bitcoin. Bitcoin is a crypto asset. It's a crypto asset that has monetary value.
Can we just link on that? Bitcoin is a digital asset that has monetary value.
What is a digital asset? What is monetary? Why use those terms versus the words of
money and currency? Is there something interesting in that disambiguation of different terms?
I'd call it a crypto asset network. The goal is to create a billion dollar block of pure energy
in cyberspace, one that I could then move with no friction at the speed of light.
It's the equivalent to putting a million pounds in orbit. How do I actually launch
something into orbit? How do I launch something into cyberspace such that it moves friction-free?
And the solution is a decentralized proof-of-work network. Satoshi's solution was I'm going to
establish a protocol running on a distributed set of computers that will maintain a constant supply
of never more than 21 million Bitcoin subdividable by 100 million Satoshis each.
Transferable via transferring private keys. Now, the innovation is to create that in an ethical,
durable fashion. The ethical innovation is I want it to be property and not a security.
A bushel of corn, an acre of land, a stack of lumber, and a bar of gold and a Bitcoin
are all property. And that means they're all commonly occurring elements in the world. You
could call them commodities, but commodity is a little bit misleading, and I'll tell you why in a
second. But they're all distinguished by the fact that no one entity or person or government
controls them. If you have a barrel of oil, and you're in Ukraine versus Russia versus Saudi
Arabia versus the US, you have a barrel of oil, right? And it doesn't matter what the premier
in Japan or the mayor of Miami Beach thinks about your barrel of oil. They cannot wave their hand
and make it not a barrel of oil or a cord of wood, right? And so property is just a naturally
occurring element in the universe, right? And- Why use the word ethical? And sorry to- I may
interrupt occasionally. Why ethical assigned to property?
Because if it's a security, a security would be an example of a share of a stock,
or a crypto token controlled by a small team. And in the event that something is a security, because
some small group or some identifiable group can control its nature, character, or supply,
then it really only becomes ethical to promote it or sell it pursuant to fair disclosures.
So I give you maybe practical example. I'm the mayor of Chicago. I give a speech. My speech,
I say, I think everybody in Chicago should own their own farm and have chicken, a chicken in
the backyard and their own horse and an automobile. That's ethical. I give the same speech and I say,
I think everybody in Chicago should buy Twitter. I think everybody in Chicago should buy Twitter.
I give the same speech and I say, I think everybody in Chicago should buy Twitter stock,
sell their house or sell their cash and buy Twitter stock.
Is that ethical? Not really. But at that point, you've entered into a conflict of interest,
because what you're doing is you're promoting an asset, which is substantially controlled by
a small group of people, the board of directors or the CEO of the company. So if, you know,
how would you feel if the president of the United States said, I really think Americans should all
buy Apple stock, especially if you worked at Google. But you worked anywhere. You'd be like,
why isn't he saying buy mine? Right? A security is a proprietary asset in some way, shape, or form.
And the whole nature of securities law, it starts from this ancient,
ancient idea, thou shalt not lie, cheat, or steal. Okay? So if I'm going to sell you securities,
or I'm going to promote securities as a public figure or as an influencer or anybody else,
if I create my own yo-yo coin or Mikey coin, and then there's a million of them,
and I tell you that I think that it's a really good thing and Mikey coin will go up forever,
right? And everybody buys Mikey coin, and then I give 10 million to you and don't tell the public,
right? I've cheated them. Maybe if I have Mikey coin, and I think there's only 2 million Mikey
coin, and I swear to you, there's only 2 million, and then I get married, and I have three kids,
and my third kid is in the hospital, and my kid's going to die, and I have this ethical reason to
print 500,000 more Mikey coin, or else people are going to die, and everybody tells me it's fine.
You know, I've still abused, you know, the investor, right? It's an ethical challenge.
If you look at ethics laws everywhere in the world, they all boil down to having a clause
which says that if you're a public figure, you can't endorse any security. You can't endorse
something that would cause you to have a conflict of interest. So if you're a mayor, a governor,
a country, a public figure, an influencer, and you want to promote or promulgate or support
something using any public influence or funds or resources you may have, it needs to be property.
It can't be security. So it goes beyond that, right? I mean, like would the Chinese want to
support an American company, right? As soon as you look at what's in the best interest of the
human race, the civilization, you realize that if you want an ethical path forward, it needs to be
based on common property, which is fair. And the way you get to a common property is through an
open permissionless protocol. If it's not open, right, if it's proprietary, and I know what the
code says, and you don't know what the code says, that makes it a security. If it's not open,
it's a security. If it's permissioned, if you're not allowed on my network, or if you can be
censored or booted off my network, that also makes it a security. So when I talk about property,
I mean, the challenge here is how do I create something that's equivalent to a barrel of oil
in cyberspace? And that means it has to be a non-sovereign bearer instrument, open,
permissionless, not censorable, right? If I could do that, then I could deliver you 10,000
dematerialized barrels of oil, and you would take settlement of them. And you would know that you
have possession of that property, irregardless of the opinion of any politician or any company
or anybody else in the world. That's a really critical characteristic. And it actually is,
it's probably one of the fundamental things that makes Bitcoin special. Bitcoin isn't just
a crypto asset network. It's easy to create a crypto asset network. It's very hard to create
an ethical crypto asset network because you have to create one without any government or
corporation or investor exercising in-do influence to make it successful.
LR So open, permissionless, non-censorable.
So basically no way for you without explicitly saying so outsourcing control to somebody else.
So it's a kind of, you have full control. Even with the barrel of oil, what's the
difference between a barrel of oil and a Bitcoin to you? What is the, because you kind of mentioned
that both are property. You mentioned Russia and China and so on. Is it the ability of the
government to confiscate? In the end, governments can probably confiscate no matter what the asset
is, but you want to lessen the effort involved.
LR A barrel of oil is a bucket of physical
property, liquid property, and Bitcoin is a digital property.
LR But it's easier to confiscate a barrel of oil.
LR It's easier to confiscate things in the real world than things in cyberspace. Much easier.
LR So that's not universally true. Some things
in the digital space are actually easier to confiscate because just the nature of how things
move easily with information, right?
LR I think in the Bitcoin world, what we would
say is that Bitcoin is the most difficult property that the human race possesses or has yet invented
to confiscate. And that's by virtue of the fact that you could take possession of it via your
private key. So if you got your 12 seed phrases in your head, then that will be the highest
form of property right because I literally have to crack your head open and read your
mind to take it. It doesn't mean I couldn't extract it from you under duress, but it means
that it's harder than every other thing you might own. In fact, it's exponentially harder.
If you consider every other thing you might own, a car, a house, a share of stock, gold,
diamonds, property rights, intellectual property rights, movie rights, music rights, anything
imaginable, they would all be easier by orders and orders of magnitude to seize. So digital
property in the form of a set of private keys is by far the apex property of the human race.
In terms of ethics, I want to make one more point. It's like I might say to you, Lex,
I think Bitcoin is the best, most secure, most durable crypto asset network in the world is
going to go up forever and there's nothing better in the world. I might be right. I might be wrong.
But the point is because it's property, it's ethical for me to say that if I were to turn
around and say, Lex, I think the same about microstrategy stock, MSTR, that's a security.
If I'm wrong about that, I have civil liability or other liability because I could go to a board
meeting tomorrow and I could actually propose we issue a million more shares of microstrategy stock.
Whereas the thing that makes Bitcoin ethical for me to even promote is the knowledge that I can't
change it. If I knew that I could make it 42 million instead of 21 million and I had the button
back here, then I have a different degree of ethical responsibility. Now, I could tell you
your life will be better if you buy Bitcoin and it might not. You might go buy Bitcoin,
you might lose the keys and be bankrupt and your life ends and your life is not better because you
bought Bitcoin, right? But it wouldn't be my ethical liability any more than if I were to say,
Lex, I think you ought to get a farm. I think you should be a farmer. I think a chicken in
every pot, you should get a horse. I think you'd be better. I mean, these are all opinions expressed
about property, which may or may not be right, that you may or may not agree with. But in a legal
sense, if we read the law, if we understand securities law, and I would say most people
in the crypto industry, they didn't take companies public and so they're not really
focused on the securities law, they don't even know the securities law. If you focus on the
securities law, that would say you just can't legally sell this stuff to the general public
or promote it without a full set of continuing disclosures signed off on by a regulator. So
there's a fairly bright line there with regard to securities, but when you get to the secondary
issue, it's how do you actually build a world based on digital property if public figures
can't embrace it or endorse it? You see, so you're not going to build a better world based upon
Twitter stock, if that's your idea of property, because Twitter stock is a security and Twitter
stock is never going to be a non-sovereign bearer instrument in Russia, right, or in China, right?
It's not even legal in China, right? So it's not a global permissionless open thing. It will never
be trusted by the rest of the world and legally, it's impractical, but would you really want to
put $100 trillion worth of economic value on Twitter stock if there's a board of directors
and a CEO that could just get up and like take half of it tomorrow? The answer is no. So if you
want to build a better world based on digital energy, you need to start with constructing a
digital property and I'm using property here in the legal sense, but I would also go to the next
step and say property is low frequency money. So if I give you a million dollars and you want to
hold it for a decade, you might go buy a house with it, right? And the house is low frequency
money. You converted the million dollars of economic energy into a structure called a house.
Maybe after a decade, you might convert it back into energy. You might sell the house for currency
and it'll be more worth more or less depending upon the monetary climate.
The frequency means what here? How quickly it changes state?
How quickly does something vibrate? So if I transfer $10 from me to you for a drink
and then you turn around and you buy another, right? We're vibrating on a frequency of every
few hours, right? The energy is changing hands, but it's not likely that you sell and buy houses
every few hours, right? The frequency of a transaction in real estate is every 10 years,
every 10 years, every five years. It's a much lower frequency transaction.
So when you think about what's going on here, you have extremely low frequency things,
which we'll call property. Then you have mid frequency things. I'm going to call them money
or currency. And then you have high frequency and that's energy. And that's why I use the
illustration of you got the building, you got the light and you got the sound and they're all just
energy moving at different frequencies. Now, Bitcoin is magical and it is truly the innovation.
It's like a singularity because it represents the first time in the history of human race
that we managed to create a digital property properly understood. It's easy to create
something digital, right? Every coupon and every scan on Fortnite and Roblox and Apple TV credits
and all these things, they're all digital something, but they're securities, right?
Shares of stock are securities. Whenever anybody transfers, when you transfer money on PayPal or
Apple Pay, you're transferring an essence, a security or an IOU. And so transferring a bearer
instrument with final settlement in the internet domain or in cyberspace, that's a critical thing.
And anybody in the crypto world can do that. All the cryptos can do that. But what they can't do,
what 99% of them fail to do is be property. They're securities.
Well, there's a line there I'd like to explore a little further. For example,
what about when you, like Coinbase or something like that, when there's an exchange that you buy
Bitcoin is in, you start to move away from this kind of, some of the aspects that you said makes
up a property, which is this non-sensible and permissionless and open. So in order to achieve
the convenience, the effectiveness of the transfer of energy, you have to leverage some of these
places that remove the aspects of property. So I mean, maybe you can comment on that.
Let me give you a good model for that. If you think about the layer one of Bitcoin,
the layer one is the property settlement layer, and we're going to do 350,000 transactions or
less a day, 100 million transactions a year is the bandwidth on the layer one. And it would be an
ideal layer one to move a billion dollars from point A to point B with the massive security.
The role of the layer one is two things. One thing is I want to move a large sum of money
through space with security. I can move any amount of Bitcoin in a matter of minutes,
for dollars on layer one. The second important feature of the layer one is I need the money to
last forever. I need the money indestructible, immortal. So the bigger trick is not to move a
billion dollars from here to Tokyo. The big trick is to move a billion dollars from here to the year
2140. And that's what we want to solve with layer one. And the best real metaphor in New York City
would be the granite or the schist. What you want is a city block of bedrock. And how long has it
been there? Like millions of years it's been there. And how fast do you want it to move?
You don't. In fact, the single thing that's most important is that it not
deflect. If it deflects a foot in 100 years, it's too much. If it deflects an inch in 100 years,
you might not want that. So the layer one of Bitcoin is a foundation upon which you put weight.
How much weight can you put on it? You put a trillion, 10 trillion, 100 trillion, a quadrillion.
How much weight's on the bedrock in Manhattan, right? Think about 100-story buildings. So
that the real key there is the foundational asset needs to be there at all. So the fact that you can
create $100 trillion layer one that would stand for 100 years, that is the revolutionary breakthrough
first time. And the fact that it's ethical, right? It's ethical. And it's common property, global,
permissionless. Extremely unlikely that would happen. People tried 50 times. People tried
50 times before, and they all failed. They tried 15,000 times after, and they've all generally
failed. 98% have failed, and a couple have been less successful. But for the most part,
that's an extraordinary thing. Now-
Just really quickly pause, just to define some terms. If people don't know, layer one that
Michael's referring to is in general what people know of as the Bitcoin technology originally
defined, which is the blockchain. There's a consensus mechanism of proof of work, a low
number of transactions, but you can move a very large amount of money. The reason he's using the
term layer one is now that there's a lot of ideas of layer two technologies built on top of this
bedrock that allow you to move a much larger number of transactions, sort of higher frequency.
I don't know what terminology you want to use, but basically be able to use now something that is
based on Bitcoin to then buy stuff, be a consumer, to transfer money, to use it as currency.
Just to define some terms.
Yeah. So the layer one is the foundation for the entire cyber economy, and we don't want it to move
fast. What we want is immortality, immortal, incorruptible, indestructible, right? That's what
you want, integrity from the layer one. Now there's layer two and layer three, and layer
two I would define as an open, permissionless, non-custodial protocol that uses the underlying
layer one token as its gas fee.
So what's custodial mean and how does the different markets, like is lightning network?
So lightning network would be an example of a layer two, non-custodial. So the lightning
network will sit on top of layer one, it'll sit on top of Bitcoin, and what you want to do is
solve the problem of, it's well and fine, I don't want to move a billion dollars every day, what I
want to move is five dollars a billion times a day. So if I want to move five dollars a billion
times a day, I don't really need to put the entire trillion-dollar-a-day, billion-dollar-a-day
trillion dollars of assets at risk every time I move five dollars. All I really need to do is put
a hundred thousand dollars in a channel or a million dollars in a channel, and then I do
ten million transactions where I have a million dollars at risk. And of course it's kind of
simple, if I put, if I lower my security requirement by a factor of a million, I can
probably move the stuff a million times faster. And that's how lightning works. It's non-custodial
because there's no corporation or custodian or counterparty you're trusting. There's the risk
of moving through the channel. But lightning is an example of how I go from 350,000 transactions a day
to 350 million transactions a day. So on that layer too, you could move the bitcoin in seconds
for fractions of pennies. Now that's not the end-all be-all, because the truth is there are
a lot of open protocols. Lightning probably won't be the only one. There's an open market competition
of other permissionless open source protocols to do this work. And in theory, any other crypto
network that was deemed to be property, deemed to be non-security, you could also think of
as potentially a layer two to bitcoin, right? There's a debate about are there any and what
are they, and we can leave that for a later time. But why do you think of them as layer two,
as opposed to contending for layer one? Yeah, actually, if they're using their own token,
then they are a layer one. If you create an open protocol that uses the bitcoin token as the fee,
then it becomes a layer two. Bitcoin itself incentivizes its own transactions with its
own token, and that's what makes it layer one. Okay, what's layer three then?
Layer three is a custodial layer. So if you want to move bitcoin in milliseconds for free,
you move it through Binance or Coinbase or Cash App. So this is a very straightforward thing. I
mean, it seems pretty obvious when you think about it that there are going to be hundreds of thousands
of layer threes. There may be dozens of layer twos. I mean, Lightning is a one, but it's not
the only one. Anybody can invent something, right? And we can have this debate about custodial,
non-custodial. Don't you think there's a monopoly, monopolization possibilities at layer three?
So, you know, Coin, you mentioned Binance, Coinbase, what if they start to dominate,
and basically everybody's using them, practically speaking, and then it becomes too costly to
memorize the private key in your brain? I mean, or like the cold storage of layer one technology.
The idealists fear the layer threes because they think, and especially they detest,
they would detest it. There's almost like a layer four, by the way, if you want to.
A layer four would be, I've got bitcoin on an application, but I can't withdraw it.
So, I've got an application that's backed by bitcoin, but the bitcoin is sealed.
It's a proprietary example. And I'll give you an example of that. That would be like
Grayscale. If I own a share of GBTC, and so I own a security, actually, you know, you could own MSTR.
If you own a security or you own a product that has bitcoin embedded in it, you get the benefits
of bitcoin, but you don't have the ability to withdraw the asset.
So, you can have the security market at layer four? Am I understanding this correctly?
I don't know if I would say, not all securities are layer four, but anything that's a proprietary
product based upon, with bitcoin embedded in it, where you can't withdraw the bitcoin,
is another application of bitcoin.
So, if you think about different ways you can use this, you can either stay completely on the layer
one and use the base chain for your transactions, or you can limit yourself to layer one and layer
two lightning. And the purist would say, we stay there, get your bitcoin off the exchange.
But you could also go to the layer three. When Cash App supported bitcoin, they made it very easy
to buy it, and then they gave you the ability to withdraw. When PayPal, or I think Robinhood,
let you buy it, they wouldn't let you withdraw it, and there was a big community uproar,
and people want, they want these layer threes to make it possible to withdraw the bitcoin.
So, you can take it to your own private wallet and get it off the exchange.
I think the answer to the question of, well, is corruption possible? Is corruption as possible
in all human institutions and all governments everywhere? The difference between digital
property and physical property is, when you own a building in Los Angeles, and the city
politics turn against you, you can't move the building. And when you own a share of a security
that's like a US traded security, and you wish to move to some other country,
you can't take the security with you either. And when you own a bunch of gold and you try to get
through the airport, they might not let you take it. So, bitcoin is advantageous versus all those,
because you actually do have the option to withdraw your asset from the exchange.
And if you had bitcoin with Fidelity, and you had shares of stock with Fidelity, and if you had
bonds and sovereign debt with Fidelity, if you own some mutual funds and some other random limited
partnerships with Fidelity, none of those things can be removed from the custodian. But the bitcoin,
you can take off the exchange, you can remove from the custodian. So, there's a deterrent that's an
anti-corrupting element. And the phrase is an armed society is a polite society, right? Because you
have the optionality to withdraw all your assets from the crypto exchange, you can enforce fairness.
And at the point where you disagree with their policies, you can, within an hour, move your
assets to another counterparty or take personal custody of those assets. So, you can't move your
assets. And you don't have that option with most other forms of property. Maybe you don't have as
much optionality with any other form of property on Earth. And so, what makes digital property
distinct is the fact that it has the most optionality for custody. Now, coming back to
this digital energy issue, the real key point is the energy moves in milliseconds for free on layer
three's. It moves in seconds or less than seconds on layer two's. It moves in minutes on the layer
one. And I don't think it makes any sense to even think about trying to solve all three problems on
the layer one because it's impossible to achieve the security and the incorruptibility and immortality
if you try to build that much speed and that functionality and performance.
In fact, if you come back to the New York model, you really wanted a block of granite, a building,
and a company. That's what makes the economy, right? If I said to you, you're going to build
a building, but you can only have one company in it for the life of the building, it would be very
fragile, like very brittle. What company a hundred years ago is still relevant today? You want all
three layers because they all oscillate at different frequencies. And there's a tendency
to think, well, it's got to be this L1 or that L1, not really. And sometimes people think, well,
I don't really want any L3. But companies, it's not an even or, companies are better than crypto
asset networks at certain things. If you want complexity, you want to implement complexity,
you want to implement compliance or customer service, right? Companies do these things well,
right? We know you couldn't decentralize Apple or Netflix or even YouTube. The performance wouldn't
be there and the subtlety wouldn't be there. And you can't really legally decentralize certain
forms of banking and insurance because they will become illegal in the political jurisdiction they're
in. So unless you're a crypto anarchist and you believe in no companies and no nation states,
right? Which is just not very practical, not anytime soon. Once you allow that nation states
will continue and companies have a role, then the layered architecture follows and the free market
determines who wins. For example, there are layer threes that let you acquire Bitcoin and
withdraw Bitcoin. There are other applications that let you acquire it but not withdraw it.
And they don't get the same market share, but they might give you some other advantage.
There are certain layer threes like Jack Dorsey's cash app where they just incorporated lightning
and implementation of it. So that makes it more advantageous versus an application that doesn't
incorporate lightning. If you think about the big picture, the big picture is 8 billion people with
mobile phones served by 100 million companies doing billions of transactions an hour. And the
companies are settling with each other on the base layer in blocks of 80 million at a time.
And then the companies are trading with the consumers in proprietary layers like layer three.
And then on occasion, people are shuffling assets across custodians with lightning layer two because
you don't want to pay $5 to move $50. You want to pay a 20th of a penny to move $50.
And so all of these things create efficiency in the economy. And Lex, if you want to consider
how much efficiency, if you gave me a billion dollars in 20 years, I couldn't find a way to
trade with another company or a counterparty in Nigeria. Like no other company in the world
would. No amount of money. Give me $10 billion. I couldn't do it because you get shut down at the
banking level. You can't link up a bank in Nigeria with a bank in the US. You get shut down at this
credit card level because they don't have the credit card, so they won't clear. You get shut
down at the compliance FCPA level because you wouldn't be able to implement a system that
interfaced with somebody else's system if it's not in the right political jurisdiction.
On the other hand, three entrepreneurs in Nigeria on the weekend could create a website that would
trade in this lightning economy using open protocols without asking anybody's permission.
So you're talking about something that's like a million times cheaper, less friction and faster
to do it if you want to get money to move.
LW- What do you think that looks like so that now there's a war going on in Ukraine,
there's other wars, Yemen going out throughout the world, in this most difficult of states that a
nation can be in, which is at war, civil war or war with other nations. What's the role of Bitcoin
in this context?
FCPA- Bitcoin is a universal trust protocol, a universal energy protocol, if you will.
English is one. What I see is a bunch of fragmentation of applications. For example,
the Russian payment app is not going to work in Ukraine. The Ukraine payment app is not going to
work in Russia. The US payment apps won't work either of those places as far as I know.
And in Argentina, their payment app may not work in certain parts of Africa. So what you have is
different local economies where people spin up their own applications compliant
with their own local laws or in war zones not compliant but just spinning up.
LW- So how do you build something that's not compliant?
FCPA- What is the revolutionary act here when you don't agree with the government
or you want to free yourself from the constraint? So here's the thing, when a nation is really at
war, especially if it's an authoritarian regime, it's going to try to control the
public, lock everything down. The spread of information, how do you break through that?
Do you do the thing that you mentioned, which is you have to build another app essentially
that allows the flow of money outside the legal constraints placed on you by the government. So
basically break the law. Is that possible? LW- Metaphorically speaking, if you want to
break out of the constraints of your culture, you learn to speak English. For example, it's not
illegal to speak English or even if it is, right? It doesn't matter. But English works everywhere
in the world if you can speak it and then you can tap into a global commerce and intelligence
network. So Bitcoin is a language. So you learn to speak Bitcoin or you learn to speak lightning
and then you tap into that network in whatever manner you can.
FCPA- But the problem is it's still very difficult to move Bitcoin around in Russia and Ukraine now
during the war. And there was a sense to me that the cryptocurrency in general could be the savior
for helping people. There's millions of refugees that are moving all around. It's very, it's very
difficult to move money around in that space to help people.
LW- I think we're very early. Like, like we're very embryonic here. If you look at the-
FCPA- Who's we, sorry? We as a human civilization or we operating in the cryptocurrency space?
LW- I think the entire crypto economy is very embryonic and the human race's
adoption of it is embryonic. We're like one, 2% down that adoption curve.
If you take lightning, for example, the, you know, the first real commercial applications
of lightning are just in the last 12 months. So we're like year one, we might be approaching
year two of commercial lightning adoption. And if you look at lightning adoption,
lightning's not built into Coinbase, it's not built into Binance, it's not built into FTX.
It's, you know, Cash App just implemented the first implementation, but not all the features
are built into it. There's a few dozen, a dozen lightning wallets circulating out there.
So I think that, you know, we're probably going to be 36 months of software development
at the point that every Android phone and every iPhone has a Bitcoin wallet or crypto
wallet in it of sorts. That's a big deal. If Apple embraced lightning, that's a big deal.
LW- So the adoption is the thing, like in a war zone adoption, the people who struggle the most
in war are people who weren't doing that great before the war started. They don't have the
technological sophistication. The hackers and all those kinds of people will find a way.
LW- It's just regular people who are just struggling to make day by day living. And so
if the adoption permeates the entire culture, then you can start to move money around in the
digital space. What if from a psycho, if you can psychoanalyze Jack Dorsey for a second.
So he's one of the early adopters, or he's one of the people pushing the early adoption, this layer
three. So inside Cash App, what do you make of the man of this decision as a business owner,
as somebody playing in the space? Like what, why did he do it? And what does that mean for others
at the scale that might be doing the same? So incorporating lightning networking,
incorporating Bitcoin into their products.
LW- I think he's been pretty clear about this. He feels that Bitcoin is an instrument of economic
empowerment for billions of people that are unbanked and have no property rights in the world.
If you want to give an incorruptible bank to 8 billion people on the planet,
that's the same as asking the question, how do you give a full education through PhD to 8 billion
people on the planet? And the answer is a digital version of the 20th century thing running on a
mobile phone. And Bitcoin is a bank in cyberspace. It's run by incorruptible software and it's for
everybody on earth. So I think when Jack looks at it, he's very sensitive to the plight of everybody
in Africa. If you look at Africans, right, like you're going to give them banks, you're not going
to put a bank branch on every corner. That's an obscene waste of energy. You're not going to run
copper wires across the continent. That's an obscene waste of energy. You're not going to
give them gold and, you know. So how are you going to provide people with a decent life?
The metaphor I think is relevant here, the biological metaphor, lacks is type 1 diabetic.
If you're a type 1 diabetic, you can't form fat. And if you can't form fat,
then you can't store excess energy. So that means that, I mean, fat is the ultimate organic battery
and if you've got 30 pounds of it, you can go 60 days without eating. But if you can't generate
insulin, you can't form fat cells. And if you can't form fat cells and store energy,
then you can eat yourself to death. I mean, you will eat and you will die. You'll starve to death.
So the lack of property rights is like being a type 1 diabetic. And so if you look at most people
everywhere in the world, they don't have property rights, they don't have effective bank, and they
don't, and their currency is broken. Like what are the two things that in theory would serve
as the equivalent of an organic battery or an economic battery to civilization? It would be
I have a currency which holds its value and I can store it in a bank. So a risk-free currency
derivative. I pay you your money, you take your life savings, you put it in a bank, you save up
for your retirement, you'll have happily ever after. That's the American dream, right? That's
the idyllic situation. The real situation is there are no banks, you can't get a bank account,
so I give you your pay in currency and then I double the supply and I give it to my cousin
or I give it to whatever cause I want or I use it to buy weapons and then you find a loaf of bread
cost triple next month is what it costs and your life savings is worthless. And so in that
environment, everybody's ripped back to Stone Age barter. And the problem with that even Stone Age
barter is you're gonna carry your life savings on your back and what happens when the guy with the
machine gun points it at your head and just takes your life savings. So I think from Jack's point of
view, he thinks that life is, this is maybe too strong, but these are my words, life is hopeless
and Bitcoin is hope, right? Because it gives everyone an engineered monetary asset that's
a bearer instrument and it gives them a bank on their mobile phone and they don't have to
trust their government or another counterparty with their life force. So there's a secondary
thing I think he's interested in, which is the first thing is the human rights issue and the
second thing would be the friction to trade cross borders is so great, right? You're like AI,
so I'll give you a beautiful notion. Maybe one day there'll be an artificially intelligent
creature in cyberspace that is self-sufficient and rich. Can a robot own money or property?
How about can a Tesla car? Can I actually put enough money in a car for it to drive itself and
maintain itself forever? Or can I create an artificially intelligent creature in cyberspace
that is endowed such that it would live a thousand years and continue to do its job, right?
We have a word for that in the real world is institution, Harvard, Cambridge, Stanford,
right? There are institutions with endowments that go on in perpetuity, but what if I wanted
to perpetuate a software program? And with something like digital property with Bitcoin
and lightning, you could do it. And on the other hand, with banks and credit cards,
you couldn't, right? You couldn't ever. So you can create things that are beautiful
and lasting. And what's the difference in speed? Well, so I can either trade with everybody in
the world at the speed of light, friction-free in 24 hours writing a Python script, or I can
spend a hundred billion dollars to trade with a few million people in the world after it takes
them six months of application. The impedance is like a 10 million to one difference, right?
And the metaphors are literally like launching something in orbit versus almost orbit or vacuum
sealing something. Does it last forever and does it orbit forever or does it go up and come down
and burn up, right? And I think Jack is interested in putting freedom in orbit, right?
Putting freedom.
Putting freedom in orbit. And he said it many times, he said,
this is the internet needs a native currency, right? And no political construct or security
can be a native currency. You need a property and you need a property that can be moved a million
times a second. Can you oscillate it at 10 kilohertz or a hundred kilohertz? And the answer
is only if it's a pure digital construct, permissionless and open. And so I think he's
enthusiastic as the technologist and he's enthusiastic as the humanitarian. And what he's
doing is support both those areas. He's supporting the Bitcoin and the lightning protocol by building
them into his products, but he's also building the applications which you need at the cash app level
in order to commercialize and deliver the functionality and the compliance necessary.
And they're related.
And I should also say he's just a fascinating person. For a random reason that I couldn't
even explain if I tried, I met him a few days ago and gave him a great big hug in the middle
of nowhere. There was no explanation. He just appeared. That's a fascinating human. His
relationship with art, with the world, with human suffering, with technology is fascinating.
I don't know what his path looks like, but it's interesting that people like that exist.
And in part, I'm saddened that he no longer is involved with Twitter directly as a CEO because
I was hoping something inside Twitter would also integrate some of these ideas of what you're
calling digital energy to see how social networks, something I'm really interested in and passionate
about, could be transformed. Let me ask you just for educational purposes, can you please
explain to me what Web3 and the beef between Jack and Marc Andreessen is exactly? Did you see what
happened? Sorry to have you analyze Twitter like it's Shakespeare, but can you please explain to
me why there was any drama over this topic? First of all, Web3 is a term that's used to refer to
the part of the economy that's token financed. So if I'm launching an application and my idea
is to create a token along with the application and issue the token to the community so as to
finance the application and build support for it, I think that that's the most common interpretation
of Web3. There are other interpretations too. So I'm just going to refer to that one.
And I think the beef, in a nutshell, not articulated, but I'll articulate it, is
whether or not you should focus all your energy creating applications on top of an ethical digital
property like Bitcoin, or whether you should attempt to create a competitor to it, which
generally would be deemed as a security by the Bitcoin community. So I'm going to put on my
Bitcoin hat here. All the tokens, if it's driven by a venture capitalist, well, it's a security.
If there's a CEO and a CTO, it's a security. All these projects, they're companies. Foundations
are companies, right? If you call them a project or a foundation, it doesn't make it
not a security. They're all in essence collections of individuals that are issuing equity in the form
of a token. And if there's a pre-mine, an IPO, an ICO, a foundation, or any kind of protocol
where there's a group of engineers that have influence over it, then to a securities lawyer,
or to most Bitcoiners and definitely to anybody that's steeped in securities law, you look at it
and say, well, that passes the Howey test. It looks like a security. It should be sold to the
public pursuant to disclosures and regulations. And you're just ducking the IPO process,
right? And so now we get back to the ethical issue. The ethical issue is if you're trading it
as a commodity and representing it as a commodity while truthfully it's a security, then it's a
violation of ethics rules and it's probably illegal. Well, you keep leaning on this. Let
me push back on that part. Maybe you can educate me, but you keep leaning on this line of securities
law as if it would all do respect to lawyers, as if that line somehow defines what is and isn't
ethical. I think there's a lot of correlation as you've discussed, but I'd like to leave the line
aside. If the law calls something a security, it doesn't mean in my eyes that it is unethical. I
mean, there could be some technicalities and lawyers and people play games with this kind of
stuff all the time. But I take your bigger point that if there's a CEO, if there's a project lead,
that's fundamentally, well, that to you is fundamentally different than the structure of
Bitcoin. It's not that creating securities is unethical. I created a security. I took a company
public, right? That's not the unethical part. It's completely ethical to create securities.
You know, block is a security. All companies are securities. The unethical part is to
represent it as property when it's a security and to promote it or trade it as such.
This whole promotion, that's also a technical thing because what counts not as promotion
is a legal thing and you get in trouble for all these things, but that's the game that lawyers
play. There's an ethical thing here, which is like, what's right to promote and not, you know?
To me, propaganda is unethical, but it's usually not illegal.
If you roll the clock back 20 years,
right? All the boiler room pump and dump schemes were all about someone pitching a penny stock,
you know, selling Swampland in Florida. And if you roll the clock back forward 20 years
and I create my own company and I represent it as the same thing and I don't make the disclosures,
right? You're just one step removed from the boiler room scheme and that's what's distasteful
about it. There are ways to sell securities to the public, but there are expectations. Maybe
we could forget about whether the security laws are ethical or not, right? I will leave that alone.
We'll just start with the biblical definition of ethics. Don't lie, cheat or steal. So if I'm going
to sell something to you, I need to fully disclose what I'm selling to you, right? And that's a
matter of great debate right now. And so I think that that's part of the debate. But the other
part of the debate is whether or not we need more than one token. Like we need at least one,
right? We need at least one digital property because zero means there is no digital economy.
Yes. And by the way, you know, the conventional view of maximalists is they think there's only
one and everything else isn't. That's not the point I'm going to make. I would say we know
there is at least one digital property and that is Bitcoin. If you can create a truly decentralized,
non-custodial, you know, bearer instrument that is not under the control of any organization
that is fairly distributed, then you might create another or multiple and there may be others out
there. But I think that the frustration of a lot of people in the Bitcoin community, and I share
this with Jack, is we could create 100 trillion dollars of value in the real world simply by
building applications on top of Bitcoin as a foundation. And so continually trying to reinvent
the wheel and create competitive things is a massive waste of time and it's diversion of
human creativity. It's like we have an ethical good thing and now we're going to try to create
a third or a fourth one. Why? Well, let's talk about it. So first of all, I'm with you, but
let me ask you this interesting question because we talked about properties and securities. Let's
talk about conflict of interest. So you said you could advertise, you have a popular Twitter account.
It's hilarious and insightful. You do promote Bitcoin in a sense. I don't know if you would
say that. But do you think there's a conflict of interest in anyone who owns Bitcoin promoting
Bitcoin? Is it the same as you promoting the farming? I would say no, there's an interest.
I think that you can promote a property or an idea to the extent that you don't control it.
I think that the point at which you start to have a conflict of interest is when you're promoting
a proprietary product or a proprietary security. A security in general is a proprietary asset.
So for example, if you look at my Twitter, you will find that I make lots of statements about
Bitcoin. You won't ever see me making a statement that say microstrategy stock will go up forever.
I'm not promoting a security MSTR because at the end of the day, MSTR is a security. It is
proprietary. I have proprietary interest in it. I have a disproportionate amount of control
and influence on the direction. The control is the problem. The control is the problem
because you have interest in both. If Bitcoin is as successful as we're talking about,
you are very possibly can become the richest human on earth given how much you own in Bitcoin.
Right? The wealthiest, not the richest. I don't know what those words mean.
I would benefit economically.
You would benefit economically.
That's true.
So the reason that's not conflict of interest is because the word property,
that Bitcoin is an idea and Bitcoin is open.
It's because I don't own it. I don't control it. In essence, the ethical line here is could I print
myself 10 million more Bitcoin or not? Right?
Or can anyone, right? It's not just you. It's can anyone?
Because can you promote somebody else's? Yes, I guess you can.
Like if you can promote us, Apple, when you have no stake.
You could have a Twitter account where you promote oil or you promote camping or you promote
family values or promote, you know, a carnivore diet or promote the Iron Man, right?
You're not going to get wealthier if you promote camping because you can't own a stake.
You own a lot of Bitcoin. What is that? What is that? Don't you own the stake in the idea?
Yeah, I would grant you that.
But the lack of control is the fundamental ethical line that you just you don't have
all you are is you're a fan of the idea. You believe in the idea and the power of the idea.
Yeah, I think you can't take that idea away from others.
Let's come back to let me give you some maybe easier examples.
If you were the head of the Marine Corps, right? And someone came to you and said,
I created Marine coin and the twist on Marine coin is I want you to tell every Marine that
they'll get an extra Marine coin, you know, when they when they get their next stripe.
And then I'm going to give you, you know, I'm going to let you buy Marine coin now.
And then after you buy Marine coin, I want you to, like, promote it to them.
Right. At some point, if if you start to have a disproportional influence on it,
or if you're in a conversation with people with disproportionate influence becomes conflict of
interest, and it would make you profoundly uncomfortable, I think. Yeah. If the head of
the Marine Corps started promoting anything that looked like a security. Now, if the head of the
Marine Corps started promoting canoeing. You might think he's kind of wacky, like maybe,
like that's kind of a waste of time and distraction. So but but but to the extent that
that canoeing is not a security, not a problem unless you you know, ultimately,
the the issue of decentralization is really a critical one. So not having a head. So is it
something can Bitcoin be replicated? So the all the things that you're saying that make it a
property, can that be replicated? Have any other... I think it's possible to create other crypto
properties. Does it does the having a head, like of a project, a thing that limits its ability to
be a property? If you if you try to replicate a project? Is that the fundamental flaw?
Look, I think the real fundamental issue is you just never want it to change.
Like, like, if you really want something decentralized, you want a genetic template
that substantially is not going to change for a thousand years. So I think Satoshi said at one
point, he said the nature of the software is such that by version point one, its genetic code was
set. If if there was any development team that's continually changing it, you know, on a routine
basis, it becomes harder and harder to maintain its decentralization because now now there's the
issue of who's influencing the changes. So what you really want is is a very, very simple idea,
right? The simplest idea. I'm just going to keep track of who owns 21 million parts of energy.
And when someone proposes big functional upgrades, you almost don't you don't really want that
development to go on the base layer. You want that development to go on the layer threes because
now cash app has a proprietary set of functionality and it's a security. And if you're going to
promote the use of this thing, you're not going to you're not going to promote the layer three
security because that's a an edge to a given entity and you're trusting the counterparty,
you're going to promote the layer one or at most the layer two.
Okay, so one of the fascinating things about Bitcoin, and sorry to romanticize certain notions,
but Satoshi Nakamoto, that the founder is anonymous. Maybe you can speak to whether that's
useful, but also I just like the psychology of that to imagine that there's a human being that
was able to create something special and walk away. So first are you Satoshi Nakamoto?
I'm certain I'm not. No, actually, I, you know, I think the providence is really important. And
if I were to look at the highlighted points, I think having a founder that was anonymous or
synonymous is important. I think the founder disappearing is also important. I think that
the fact that the Satoshi coins never moved is also important. I think the the last thing that
is also important. I think the lack of an initial coin offering is also important. I think the lack
of a corporate sponsor is important. I think the fact that it traded for 15 months with no commercial
value was also important. You know, I think that the simplicity of the protocol is very important.
I think that the outcome of the block size wars is very important. And all of those things
add up to common property. They're all indicia, indicators of a digital property as opposed to
security. If there was a Satoshi sitting around sitting on top of $50 billion worth of Bitcoin,
it would I don't think it would cripple Bitcoin as property, but I think it would undermine
its digital property. And if I wanted to undermine a crypto asset network,
I would do the opposite of all those things. I would launch one myself. I would sell 25 percent
or 50 percent of the general public. I would keep some of the initial I would pre mine some stuff
or early mine it, you know, and I would keep an influence on it. Those are all the opposite
of what you would do in order to create common property. And so I see the entire story as Satoshi
giving a gift of digital property to the human race and disappearing.
Do you think it was one person? Do you have ideas of who it could be?
I don't care to speculate.
Okay. But do you think it was one person?
It was one person, maybe in conjunction with a bunch of others. I mean,
it might have been a group of people that were working together, but certainly there's a Satoshi.
I mean, it's just so fascinating to me that one person could be so brave and thoughtful. Or do
you think a lot of his accent, like the block size wars, the decision to make a block a certain size,
all all the things you mentioned led up to the characteristics that make Bitcoin property.
Do you think that's an accident or it was deeply thought through?
Like, how does this is almost like a history of science question.
I think people tried it for they tried 40 of them, right? I mean, I think there's a there's
a history of attempting to create something like this. And it was tried many, many times and,
and they failed for different reasons. And I think that it's like Prometheus tried to start a fire
47 times and maybe the 48th time it sparked. And that's how I see this. This is the first one that
sparked. And it sets a roadmap for us. And I think if you're looking for any one word that
characterizes it, it's fair, right? The whole point of the network is it's a fair launch,
a fair distribution. Like, yeah, I have Bitcoin, but I bought it. In fact, you know,
at this point, we've paid $4 billion of you real cash to buy it. If I was sitting on the same
position, and I had it for free, then there's always this question of, did I, you know,
or I bought it for a nickel, a coin or a penny, the question is, was it fair? And that's a very
hard question to answer, right? Did you acquire the Bitcoin that you own fairly? And if you roll
the clock back, you know, you could have bought it for a nickel or a dime, but that was when it
was a million times more likely to fail, right? When the risk was greater, the cost was lower.
And then over time, the risk became lower and the cost became greater. And the real critical thing
was to allow the marketplace absent any powerful interested actor, right? If Satoshi had held a
million coins and then stayed engaged for 10 more years, tweaking things in the background,
there'd still be that question. But what we've got is really a beautiful thing. We've got a
we've got a chain reaction in cyberspace or an ideology spreading virally in the world
that has seasoned in a fair ethical fashion. Sometimes it's a very violent, brutal fashion
with all the volatility, right? And there's been a lot of, you know, a lot of sound and fury along
the way. How do you psychoanalyze? How do you deal from a financial, from a human perspective
with the volatility? You mentioned you could have gotten it for a nickel and the risk was great.
Where's the risk today? What's your sense? You know, we're 13 years into this entire activity.
I think the risk has never been lower. If you look at all the risks, right? The risks in the
early years are, is the engineering protocol proper? Like one megabyte block size, 10 minute
clock frequency cryptography is first, will it be hacked or will it crash? 730,000 blocks and it
hasn't crashed. Will it be hacked? Hasn't been hacked. But you know, it's a Lindy thing, right?
You wait 13 years to see if it'll be hacked. But on the other hand, with a billion dollars,
it's not as interesting a target as it is with a hundred billion. And when it gets to be worth
a trillion, then it's a bigger target. So the risk has been bleeding off over time as the network
monetized. I think the second question is, will it be banned? You couldn't know. It literally could
have been banned many times early on. In fact, in 2013, I tweeted on that subject, I thought it would
be banned. I made a very infamous tweet. I thought it was going to be banned. In 2014, the IRS
designated it as property and gave it property tax treatment, okay? So they could have given
it a tax treatment where you had to pay tax on the unrealized capital gains every year and it
probably would have crushed it to death, right? So it could have been in any number of places
banned by a government, but in fact, it was legitimized as property. And then the question
is, would it be hacked or would it be copied? Would it be something better than that? And it
was copied 15,000 times. And you know the story of all those. And they either diverged to be
something totally different and not comparable or someone trying to copy a non-sovereign bearer
instrument store of value found that their networks crashed to be 1% of what Bitcoin is. So now we're
sitting at a point where all those risks are out of the way. I would say that year one of
institutional adoption is it started August 2020. That's when MicroStrategy bought $250 million
worth of Bitcoin and we put that out on the wire. We were the first publicly traded company to
actually buy Bitcoin. I don't think you could have found a $5 million purchase from a public
company before we did that. So that was kind of like a gun going off. And then in the next 12
months, Tesla bought Bitcoin, Square bought Bitcoin. And I'd say now we're in year two
of institutional adoption. And there are about 24, should be 24 publicly traded Bitcoin miners
by the end of this quarter. So you're looking at 36 publicly traded companies and you've got
at least in the range of $50 billion of Bitcoin on the balance sheet of publicly traded companies
and hundreds of billions of dollars of market cap of Bitcoin exposed companies.
So I would say the asset, decade one was entrepreneurial, experimental.
Decade two is a rotation from entrepreneurs to institutions and is becoming institutionalized.
So maybe decade one you go from zero to a trillion and in decade two you go from one trillion to
a hundred trillion. What about governments, government adoption, institutional adoption?
Are governments important in this? Maybe making it some governments incorporating it into as a
currency into their banks, all that kind of stuff. Is that important? And if it is, when will it
happen? It's not essential for the success of the asset class, but I think it's inevitable in various
degrees over time. But the most likely thing to happen next is large acquisitions by institutional
investors of Bitcoin as a digital gold, where they're just swapping out gold for digital gold
and thinking of it like that. And the government entities most likely to be involved with that
would be sovereign wealth funds. If you look at all the sovereign wealth funds that are holding
big tech stock equities, the Swiss, the Norwegians, the Middle Easterners,
if you can hold big tech, then holding digital gold would be not far removed from that. That's
a non-controversial adoption. I think there are opportunities for governments that are
much more profound. If a government started to adopt Bitcoin as a treasury reserve asset,
that's much bigger than just an asset investment. That's 100x bigger. And you could imagine that's
like a trillion dollar opportunity. Any government that wanted to adopt it as a treasury reserve asset
would probably generate trillions of dollars, a trillion or more of value. And then the thing
that people think about is, well, will oil ever be priced in Bitcoin or any other export commodity?
I think there's like $1.8 trillion or more of export commodities in the world. And right now,
they're all priced in dollars. I think that this is a colorful thing, but it's not really that
relevant. You could sell all that stuff in dollars. The relevant decision that any institution makes,
whether they're a nonprofit, a university, a corporation, or a government,
is what's your treasury reserve asset? And if your treasury reserve asset is the peso,
and if the peso is losing 20% or 30% of its value a year, then your balance sheet is collapsing
within five years. And if the treasury reserve asset is dollars and currency derivatives and
US treasuries, then you're getting your seven. Right now, it's probably 15% or more
monetary inflation. We're running double the historic average. You could argue triple,
somewhere between double and triple, depending upon what your metric is. So do I think it'll
happen? I think that they're conservative, but they have to be shocked. And I think there is a
shock. The late Russian sanctions are a big shock. When the West sees $300 billion worth
of Russian gold and currency derivatives, I think you got the famous quote by Putin that
we have to rethink our treasury strategies. And that pushes everybody toward a commodity strategy.
What commodities do I want to hold? I think that's got a lot of people thinking. I think it's got
the Chinese thinking. Everybody wants to be the reserve currency, right? So if I buy $50 billion
worth of dollars every year, then I buy $500 billion over a decade, and I probably pay $250
billion of inflation cost on the backs of my citizens in a decade. So inflation could be one
of the sources of shock. And you wonder if there is a switch to Bitcoin, whether it will be a bang
or a whimper. Like what is the nature of the shock or the transition? I think that the year 2022 is
pretty catalytic for digital assets in general and for Bitcoin in particular. The Canadian trucker
crisis, I think, educated hundreds of millions of people and made them start questioning their
property rights and their banks. I think the Ukraine war was a second shock. But I think
that the Russian sanctions was a third shock. I think hyperinflation in the rest of the world is
a fourth shock. And then persistent inflation in the US is a fifth shock. So I think it's a perfect
storm. And if you put all these events together, what do they signify? They signify the rational
conclusion for any person thinking about this is, I'm not sure if I can trust my property.
I don't know if I have property rights. I don't know if I can trust the bank.
And if I'm politically at odds with the leader of my own country, I'm going to lose my property.
And if I'm politically at odds with the owner of another country, I'm still going to lose my
property. And when push comes to shove, the banks will freeze my assets and seize them.
And I think that that is playing out in front of everybody in the world,
such that your logical response would be, I'm going to convert my weak currency to a strong
currency. I'll convert my peso and lira to the dollar. I'm going to convert my weak property
to strong property. I'm going to sell my building downtown Moscow. And I'd rather own
a building in New York City. I'd rather own in a powerful nation than be stuck with a building
in Nigeria or a building in Argentina or whatever. So I'm going to sell my weak properties by strong
properties. I'm going to convert my physical assets to digital assets. I'd rather own a
digital building than own a physical building. Because if I had a billion dollar building in
Moscow, who can I rent that to? But if I have a billion dollar digital building, I can rent it to
anybody in any city in the world, anybody with money. And the maintenance cost is almost nothing,
and I can hold it for 100 years. So it's an indestructible building.
And then finally, I want to move from having my assets in a bank with a counterparty
to self-custody assets. And this is not just Ukraine, but this is like the story in Turkey,
Lebanon, Syria, Afghanistan, Iraq, South America. You don't really want to be sitting with $10
million in a bank in Istanbul. The bank's going to freeze your money, convert it to lira, devalue
the lira, and then feed it back to you over 17 years, right?
So self-custody assets would be layer one Bitcoin?
Self-custody assets, it's like, if I got my own hardware wallet, and I've either got
your highest form of self-custody would be Bitcoin on your own hardware wallet or Bitcoin
in your own self-custody. And the other thing people think about is how do I get crypto dollars
like Tether, like some stable coin. Like I'd rather, if you had a choice, would you rather
have your money in a bank in a war zone in dollars or have your money in a stable coin
on your mobile phone in dollars, right? I mean, you take the latter risk rather than
the former risk. In a war zone, definitely, yeah.
And you can see that happening. Like we've gone from 5 billion in stable coins to 200 billion
in the last 24 months. So I do think there's massive demand for crypto dollars in the form
of a US dollar asset. And everybody in the world would say, yeah, I want that.
Well, unless you're just an extreme patriot, but most people in the world would say, I
want that. And then a lesser group of people would say, I think I want to be able to carry
my property in the palm of my hand so I have self-custody of it.
So the Bitcoin price has gone through quite a roller coaster. What do you think is the
high point it's going to hit? I think it'll go forever, right? I mean,
I think the Bitcoin is going to climb in a serpentine fashion. It's going to advance
and come back and it's going to keep climbing. I think that the volatility
attracts all the capital into the marketplace. And so the volatility makes it the most interesting
thing in the financial universe. It also generates massive yield and massive returns for traders.
And that attracts capital. Like we're talking about the difference between 5% return and 500%
return. So the fast money is attracted by the volatility. The volatility has been decreasing
year by year by year. I think that it's stabilizing. I don't think we'll see as much
volatility in the future as we have in the past. I think that if we look at Bitcoin and model it as
digital gold, the market cap goes to between 10 and 20 trillion. But gold is, remember,
gold is defective property. Gold is dead money. You have a billion dollars of gold that sits in
a vault for a decade. It's very hard to mortgage the gold. It's also very hard to rent the gold.
You can't loan the gold. No one's going to create a business with your gold.
So gold doesn't generate much of a yield. So for that reason, most people wouldn't store
a billion dollars for a decade in gold. They would buy a billion dollars of commercial real estate
property. And the reason why is because I can rent it and generate a yield on it that's in
excess of the maintenance cost. So if you consider digital property, that's 100 to 200 trillion
addressable market. So I would think it goes from 10 trillion to 100 trillion as people start to
think of it as digital property. What does that mean in terms of price per coin?
At 500,000, that's a 10 trillion dollar asset. At 5 million, that's a 100 trillion dollar asset.
So I think it crosses a million. It can go even higher.
Yeah, I think it keeps going up forever. I mean, there's no reason it couldn't go to 10 million
a coin, right? Because digital property isn't the highest form, right?
Gold was that low frequency money. Property is a mid frequency money. But when I start to
program it faster, it starts to look like digital energy. And then it doesn't just replace property.
Then you're starting to replace bonds. It's 100 trillion in bonds, there's 50 to 100 trillion
in other currency derivatives. And these are all conventional use cases, right? I think that
there's 350 trillion to 500 trillion dollars worth of currency derivatives in the world.
And when I say that, I mean things that are valued based upon fiat cash flows.
Any commercial real estate, any bond, any sovereign debt, any currency itself,
any derivatives to those things, they're all derivatives. And they're all defective.
And they're all defective because of this persistent 7% to 14%
lapse, which we call inflation or monetary expansion. Can we switch,
so I'm just going to talk about the energy side of it, like the innovative piece.
Yeah. Let's just start with this idea that
I've got a hotel worth a billion dollars with a thousand rooms. When it becomes a dematerialized
hotel. I love that word so much, by the way, dematerialized hotel.
We're crossing the fountain blow here. Imagine the fountain blow is dematerialized.
The problem with a physical hotel is I got to hire real people moving subject to the speed of sound
and physics laws and Newton's laws. And I can rent it to people in Miami beach.
Mm-hmm. But if it was a digital hotel,
I could rent the room to people in Paris, London, and New York every night.
And I can run it with robots. And as soon as I do that, I can rent it by the room hour.
And I can rent it by the room minute. And so I start to chop my hotel up into
100,000 room hours that I sell to the highest bidder anywhere in the world. And you can see
all of a sudden the yield, the rent, and the income of the property is dramatically increased.
I can also see the maintenance cost of the property falls. I get on Moore's law,
and I'm operating in cyberspace. So I got rid of Newton's laws. I got rid of all the friction and
all those problems. I tapped into the benefits of cyberspace. I created a global property.
I started monetizing it at different frequencies. And of course, now I can mortgage it to anybody
in the world. You're not going to be able to get a mortgage on a Turkish building from someone
in South Africa. You have to have to find someone that's local to the culture you're in.
So when you start to move from analog property to digital property, it's not just a little bit
better. It's a lot better. And what I just described, Lex, is the DeFi vision. It's the
beauty of DeFi flash loans, money moving at high velocity. At some point, if the hotel is
dematerialized, then what's the difference between renting a hotel room and loaning a block of stock?
Right? I'm just finding the highest best use of the thing. It feels like the magic really emerges
though when you build a lot, a market of layer two and layer three technologies on top of that.
It's like, maybe you can correct me if I'm wrong, but for all these hotels and all these kinds of
ideas, it's always touching humans at some point. And you know, consumers or humans, business
owners and so on. And so you have to create interface. You have to create services that
make all that super efficient, super fun to use, pleasant, effective, all those kinds of things.
And so you have to build in a whole economy on top of that.
Yeah. And I happen to think that won't be done by the crypto industry at all. I think that'll be
done by centralized applications. I think it'll be, you know, the citadels of the world, the high
speed traders of the world, the New Yorkers. I think it'll be Binance, FTX, and Coinbase as a
layer three exchange that will give you the yield and will give you the loan and the best terms.
Because ultimately you have to jump these compliance hoops. It comes like BlockFi can give
you yield, but they have to do it in a compliant way with the United States jurisdiction.
So ultimately, those applications to use that digital property and either generate a loan,
give you a loan on it, or give you yield on it are going to come from companies. But the difference,
the fundamental difference is it could be companies anywhere in the world. So if a company in
Singapore comes up with a better offering, right, then the capital is going to start to flow in
to Singapore. I can't send 10 city blocks of LA to Singapore to rent during a festival,
but I can send 10 blocks of Bitcoin to Singapore. So you've got a truly global market that's
functioning in this asset. And as a second order asset, for example, maybe you're an American
citizen and you own 10 Bitcoin and someone in Singapore will generate 27% yield in the Bitcoin,
but legally, you can't send the money to them or the Bitcoin to them. It doesn't matter, because
the fact that that exists means that someone in Hong Kong will borrow the 10 Bitcoin from somebody
in New York, and then they will put on the trade in Singapore. And that will create a demand for
Bitcoin, which will drive up the price of Bitcoin, which will result in an effective tax-free yield
for the person in the US that's not even in the jurisdiction. And that's going to create
a tax-free yield for the person in the jurisdiction. So there's nothing that's going on in Singapore
to drive up the price of your land in LA. But there is something going on everywhere in the
world to drive up the price of property in cyberspace if there's only one digital Manhattan.
And so there's a dynamic there, which is profound because it's global. But now let's go to the next
additional idea, which is let's just loan the money fast on a global network, and let's just
rent the hotel room fast in cyberspace. But let's move to maybe a more innovative idea.
The first generation of internet brought a lot of productivity, but there's also just a lot of
flaws in it. For example, Twitter is full of garbage. Instagram DMs are full of garbage. Your
YouTube is full of scams. Every 15 minutes, there's a Michael Saylor Bitcoin giveaway spun up on
YouTube. My Office 365 inbox is full of garbage, millions of spam messages. I'm running four
different email filters. My company spends million dollars a year to fight denial of service attacks
and all sorts of other security things. There are denial of service attacks everywhere against
everybody in cyberspace all the time. It's extreme. And we're all beset with hostility,
right? You've been a victim of it in Twitter. You go on Twitter and people post stuff they would
never say to your face. And then if you look, you find out that the account was created like
three days ago, and it's not even a real person. So we're beset with phishing attacks and scams
and spam bots and garbage. And why? And the answer is because the first generation of
internet was digital information, and there's no energy. There's no conservation of energy
in cyberspace. The thing that makes the universe work is conservation of energy. Like, if I went
to a hotel room, I'd have to post a credit card. And then if I smash the place up, there'd be
economic consequences. Maybe there'd be criminal consequences. There might be reputational
consequences. You know, a lamp might fall on me. But in the worst case, I can only smash up one
hotel room. Now, imagine I could actually write a Python script to send myself to every hotel room
in the world every minute, not post a credit card and smash them all up anonymously, right?
The thing that makes the universe work is friction, speed of sound, speed of light, and the
fact that ultimately it's conservative. You're either energy or you're matter. But once you've
used the energy, it's gone, and you can't do infinite everything. That's missing in cyberspace
right now. And if you look at all of the moral hazards and all of the product defects that we
have in all of these products, most of them, 99% of them, could be cured if we introduced
conservation of energy into cyberspace. And that's what you can do with high-speed digital
property, high-speed Bitcoin. And by high-speed, I mean not 20 transactions a day. I mean 20,000
transactions a day. So how do you do that? Well, I let everybody on Twitter post 1,000 or 10,000
Satoshis via lightning wallet, a lightning badge, give me an orange check. If you put up 20 bucks
once in your life, you could give 300 million people an orange check. Right now, you don't have
a blue check, Lex. You're a famous person. I don't know why you don't have a blue check. Have you
ever applied for a blue check? No. There are 360,000 people on Twitter with a blue check.
There are 300 million people on Twitter. So the conventional way to verify accounts is elitist,
archaic. Yeah, how does it work? How do you get a blue check? You got to apply and wait six months,
and you have to post three articles in the public mainstream media that illustrates you're a person
of interest. Interesting. Generally, they would grant them to CEOs of public companies. The whole
idea is to verify that you are who you say you are. But the question is, why isn't everybody
verified? And there's a couple of threads on that. One is, some people don't want to be doxxed.
They want to be anonymous. Sure. But there are even anonymous people that should be verified.
Right. Because otherwise, you're subjecting their entire following to phishing attacks and scams and
hostility. But the other- What's the orange verification? So this idea, can you actually
elaborate a little bit more if you put up 20 bucks? Yeah, I think everybody on Twitter ought to be
able to get an orange check if they could come up with like $10. And what is the power of that orange
check? What does that verify exactly? You basically post a security deposit for your
safe passage through cyberspace. So the way it would work is, if you've got $10 once in your life,
you can basically show that you're credit worthy. And that's your pledge to me that you're going to
act responsibly. So you put the 10 or the $20 into the lightning wallet, you get an orange check.
Then Twitter just gives you a setting where I can say, the only people that could DM me are orange
checks. The only people that can post on my tweets are orange checks. So instead of locking out the
public and just letting your followers comment, you lock out all the unverified. And that means
people that don't want to post $10 security deposit can't comment. Once you've done those
two things, then you're in position to monetize malice, monetize motion or malice for that matter.
But let's just say, for the sake of argument, you post something and 9700 bots spin up and pitch
their whatever scam. Right now, you sit and you go report, report, report, report, report, report,
and if you spend an hour, you get through half of them. You waste an hour of your life. They just
spend up another $97 because they've got a Python script spending it up, so it's hopeless.
But on the other hand, if you report them and they really are a bot, Twitter's got a method to
actually delete the account. They know that they're bots. The problem is not they don't know
how to delete the account. The problem is there are no consequences when they delete the account.
So if there are consequences, Twitter could give, they could just seize the $10 or seize the $20
because it's a bot. It's a malicious criminal act or whatever. It is a violation of the platform
rules. You end up seizing $10,000, give half the money to the reporter and half the money to the
Twitter platform, and- That's a really powerful idea, but that's tying it, that's adding friction
akin to the kind of friction you have in the physical world. You're tying, you have consequences.
You have real consequences. It's putting conservation of energy. Conservation of energy.
There's no friction. There's no nothing on this earth. Right? I mean, you can't walk out of this
earth, right? I mean, you can't walk across the room without friction, right? So friction is not
bad, right? Unnecessary friction is bad. So in this particular case, you're introducing
conservation of energy. And in essence, you're introducing the concept of consequence or truth
into cyberspace. And that means if you do want to spin up 10 million fake-less Freedmen's, right?
It's going to cost you a hundred million dollars to spin up 10 million fake Lexus.
But the thing is you could do that with the dollar, but you're saying that it's more tied
to physical reality when you do that with Bitcoin. Yeah. Well, let's follow up on that idea a bit
more. If you did do it with the dollar, then the question is how do 6 billion people deposit the
dollars, right? Because what you're doing is, yeah, could you do it with a credit card? Like,
how do you send dollars? You have to dox yourself. It's not easy. So you're talking about inputting
a credit card transaction, doxing yourself, and now you've just eliminated the 2 billion people
that don't have credit cards or don't have banks. You've also got a problem with everybody that
wants to remain anonymous. But you've also got this other problem, which is credit cards are
expensive transactions, low frequency, slow settlement. So do you really want to pay two and
a half percent every time you actually show a $20 deposit? And maybe you could do a Kluge version
of this for a subset of people. It's like it's 10% as good if you did it with conventional payment
rails. But what you can't do is the next idea, which is I want the orange badge to be used to
give me safe passage through cyberspace, tripping across every platform. So how do I solve the
denial of service attacks against a website? I publish a website. You hit it with a million
requests. OK, now how do I deal with that? Well, I can lock you out and I can make it a zero trust
website. And then you have to be coming at me through a trusted firewall with a trusted credential.
But that's a pretty draconian thing. Or I could put it behind a lightning wall. A lightning wall
would be, I just challenge you, Lex, you want to browse my website, you have to show me your
100,000 satoshis. Do you have 100,000 satoshis? Click. OK, now you click away a hundred times
or a thousand times. And after a thousand times, I'm like, well, now, Lex, you're getting offensive
over to take a satoshi from you or 10 satoshis, a microtransaction. You want to hit me a million
times? I'm taking all your satoshis and locking you out. What you want to do is you want to go
through 200 websites a day. And what you want every time you cross a domain, you need to be
able to, in a split second, prove that you've got some asset. And now when you cross back,
when you exit domain, you want to fetch your asset back. So how do I, in a friction-free fashion,
browse through dozens or hundreds of websites, post a security deposit for safe passage and then
get it back? You couldn't afford to pay a credit card fee each time. When you think about 2.5% as
a transaction fee, it means you trade the money 40 times and it's gone. It's gone.
Yeah. So you can't do this kind of hopping around through the internet with this kind of
verification that grounds you to a physical reality. It's a really, really interesting idea.
Why hasn't that been done?
I think you need two things. You need an idea like a digital asset, like Bitcoin,
that's a bearer instrument for final settlement. And then you need a high-speed transaction network
like Lightning, where the transaction cost might be a 20th of a penny or less. And if you roll the
clock back 24 months, I don't think you had the Lightning network in a stable point. It's really
just the past 12 months. It's an idea you could think about this year. And I think you need to
be aware of Bitcoin as something other than like a scary speculative asset. So I really think we're
just the beginning.
The embryonic stage. I have to ask Michael Saylor, you said before, there's no second best to Bitcoin.
What would be the second best? Traditionally, there's Ethereum with smart contracts, Cardano
with proof of stake, Polkadot with interoperability between blockchains. Dogecoin has the incredible
power of the meme. Privacy with Monero, I just can keep going. There's the
there's, of course, after the block size wars, the different offshoots of Bitcoin.
I think if you decompose or segment the crypto market, you've got crypto property. Bitcoin is
the king of that. And other Bitcoin forks that wanted to be a bearer instrument store of value
would be a property, a Bitcoin cash or Litecoin, something like that. Then you've got crypto
currencies. I don't think I don't think Bitcoin's a currency because a currency I define in nation
states since a currency is a digital asset that you can transfer as a, you know, in a transaction
without incurring a taxable obligation. So that means has to be a stable dollar or a stable euro
or a stable yen, a stable coin. So I think that crypto currencies, Tether, Circle, most famous.
Then you've got crypto platforms, you know, and Ethereum is the most famous of the crypto platforms,
the platform upon which, you know, with smart contract functionality, etc. And then I think
you've got just crypto securities. It's just like my favorite whatever meme coin. And I love it
because I love it. And it's attached to my game or my company or my persona or my whatever.
I think if you if you, you know, push me and said, what's the second most popular
push me and said, what's the second best? I would say the world wants two things.
It wants crypto property as a savings account and it wants cryptocurrency as a checking account.
And that means that the that the most popular thing really is going to be a stable coin dollar.
Right. And there's a maybe a fight right now. It might be Tether. Right. But a stable dollar,
because I feel like the market opportunity, it's not clear that there'll be one that will win.
The class of stable dollars is probably a one to ten trillion dollar market easily.
I think that in a crypto platform space, Ethereum will compete with Solana and
Binance Smart Chain and the like.
Are there certain characteristics of any of them that kind of stand out to you?
Don't you think the competition is based on a set of features?
There's also so the set of features that that cryptocurrency provides,
but also the community that it provides. So do you think the community matters and sort
of the adoption, the dynamic of the adoption, both across the developers and the investors?
If I'm looking at them, I mean, the first question is, is what's the regulatory risk?
How likely is it to be deemed a property versus security? And the second is,
is what's the competitive risk? And the third is what's the speed and the performance and
the, you know, all those things, you know, lead to the question of what's the security risk?
How likely is it to crash and burn and how stable or unstable is it? And then there's the
marketing risk. I mean, there are different teams behind each of these things and communities behind
them. I think that the big cloud looming over the crypto industry is regulatory treatment of
cryptocurrencies and regulatory treatment of crypto securities and crypto platforms.
And I think that won't be determined until the end of the first Biden administration.
For example, there are people that would like only US FDIC insured banks to issue
cryptocurrencies. They want JP Morgan to issue a crypto dollar backed one to one.
But then in the US right now, we have Circle and we have other companies that are licensed
entities that are backed by cash and cash equivalents, but they're not FDIC insured banks.
There's also a debate in Congress about whether state chartered banks should be able to issue
these things. And then we have Tether and others that are outside of the US jurisdiction.
They're probably not backed by cash and cash equivalents. They're backed by stuff
and we don't know what stuff. And then finally you have, you know, UST and DAI, which are
algorithmic stable coins that are even more innovative further outside the compliance
framework. So if you ask who's going to win, the question is really, I don't know, will the market
decide or will the regulators decide? If the regulators get out of the way and the market
fall out, well then it's an interesting discussion. And then I think that all bets are off if the
regulators get more heavy handed with this. And I think you could have the same discussion with
crypto properties. Like the DeFi exchanges and the crypto exchanges, the SEC would like to regulate
the crypto exchanges. They'd like to regulate the DeFi exchanges. That means they may regulate the
crypto platforms and at what rate and in what fashion. And so I think that I could give you
an opinion if it was limited to competition and the current regulatory regime, but I think that
the regulations are so fast moving and it's so uncertain that it's, you can't make a decision
without considering the potential actions of the regulators.
I hope the regulators get out of the way. Can you steal me on the case
that Dogecoin is I guess the second best cryptocurrency if you don't consider Bitcoin
a cryptocurrency, but instead a crypto property. I would classify it as crypto property because
the US dollar is a currency. So unless your crypto asset is pegged algorithmically or stably to the
value of the dollar is not a currency, it's a property or it's an asset.
So then can you steal me on the case that Dogecoin is the best cryptocurrency then?
Because Bitcoin is not even in that list.
The debate is going to be whether it's property or security. And there's a debate whether it's
decentralized enough. So let's assume it was decentralized. Well, it's increasing at not quite
five, what, 5% a year inflation rate, but it's not 5% exponentially. It's like a plus 5 million,
5% something captain is less. I forget the exact number, but it's an inflationary property. It's
got a lower inflation rate than the US dollar. And it's got a much lower inflation rate than
than many other fiat currencies. So I think you could say that.
But don't you see the power of meme, the power of ideas, the power of
fun or whatever mechanism is used to captivate a community?
I do, but there are meme stocks. It doesn't absolve you of your ethical and securities
liabilities if you're promoting it. So I don't have a problem with people buying a stock.
The way I divide the world is there's investment, there's saving,
and there's speculation and there's trading. So Bitcoin is an asset for saving. If you want to
save money for 100 years, you don't really want to take on execution risk or the like. So you're
just buying something to hold forever. For you to actually endorse something as a property,
like if you said to me, Mike, what should I buy for the next 100 years? I say, well,
some amount of real estate, some amount of scarce collectibles, some amount of Bitcoin,
right? You can run your company, right? But running your company is an investment.
So the savings are properties. If you said, what should I invest in? I'd say, well,
here's a list of good companies, private companies, you can start your own company,
that's an investment, right? If you said, what should I trade? Well, I'm trading as like a
proprietary thing. I don't have any special insight into that. If you're a good trader,
you know you are. If you said to me, what should you speculate in? We talk about meme stocks
and meme coins and it's kind of sits up there. It sits right in the same space with what horse
should you bet on and what sports team should you gamble on and should you bet on black six
times in a row and double down each time. I mean, it's fun, but at the end of the day,
it's a speculation, right? You can't build a civilization on it. It's not an institutional
asset. And in fact, where I'd leave it, right, is Bitcoin is clearly digital, which makes it
an institutional grade investable asset for a public company, a public figure, a public investor,
or anybody that's risk adverse. I think that the top 100 other cryptos are like
venture capital investments. And if you're a VC and if you're a qualified technical investor and
you have a pool of capital and you can take that kind of risk, then you can parse through that and
form opinions. It's just orders of magnitude more risky because of competition, because of ambition,
and because of regulation. And if you take the meme coins, it's like, you know,
when some rapper comes out with a meme coin, it's like, maybe it'll peak when I hear about it,
right? I mean, SHIB was created as a coin such that it had so many zeros after the decimal point
that when you looked at it on the exchanges, it always showed 0000. And it wasn't until like six
months after it got popular that they started expanding the display so you could see whether
the price had changed. That's speculation. You've been, maybe you can correct me, but you've been
critical of Elon Musk in the past in the crypto space. Where do you stand on Elon's effect on
Bitcoin and cryptocurrency in general these days? I believe that Bitcoin is a massive breakthrough
for the human race that will cure half the problems in the world and generate hundreds
of trillions of dollars of economic value to the civilization. And I believe that it's in an early
stage where many people don't understand it, and they're afraid of it, and there's FUD,
and there's uncertainty, there's doubt, and there's fear. And it's a very noisy crypto world,
and there's 15,000 other cryptos that are seeking relevance. And I think most of the FUD
is actually fueled by the other crypto entrepreneurs. So the environmental FUD
and the other types of uncertainty that surround Bitcoin, generally they're not coming from
legitimate environmentalists. They don't come from legitimate critics. They actually are guerrilla
marketing campaigns that are being financed and fueled by other crypto entrepreneurs
because they have an interest in doing so. So if I look at the constructive path forward,
first, I think it'd be very constructive for corporations to embrace Bitcoin and build
applications on top of it. You don't need to fix it. There's nothing wrong with it, right? Like
when you put it on a layer two and a layer three, it moves a billion times a second at the speed
of light. So every beautiful, cool DeFi application, every crypto application,
everything you could imagine you might want to do, you can do with a legitimate company
and a legitimate website or mobile application sitting on top of Bitcoin or Lightning,
if you want to. So I think that to the extent that people do that, that's going to be better
for the world. If you consider what holds people back, I think it's just misperceptions
about what Bitcoin is. So I'm a big fan of just educating people. If you're not going to
commercialize it, then just educate people on what it is. So for example, Bitcoin is the most
efficient use of energy in the world by far, right? Most people don't, they don't necessarily
perceive that or realize that. But if you were to take any metric, energy intensity,
you put like $2 billion worth of electricity in the network every year and it's worth $850 billion.
There is no industry in the real world, right, that is that energy efficient. Not only that
energy efficient, it's also the most sustainable industry. We do surveys, 58% of Bitcoin mining
energy is sustainable. So there's a very good story. In fact, every other industry, planes,
trains, automobiles, construction, food, medicine, everything else is less clean, less efficient.
So the basic debate was-
I wouldn't say there is a debate. I would just say that to the extent that the Bitcoin community
with Elon, it was just this environmental uncertainty that he fueled in a couple of his
tweets, right? Which I think just is very distracting. Well, that was one of them.
But I think it's like the Bitcoin maximalists, but generally the crypto community, what you call
the crypto entrepreneurs are, it's also they're using it for, I mean, for investment, for
speculation, and therefore get very passionate about people's kind of celebrities, including you,
like famous people, saying positive stuff about any one particular crypto thing you can buy in
Coinbase. And so they might be unhappy with Elon Musk that he's promoting Bitcoin and then not,
and then promoting Dogecoin, then not. There's so much emotion tied up in the communication
on this topic. And I think that's where a lot of the-
Look, I don't have a criticism of Elon Musk. He's free to do whatever he wishes to do. In fact,
Elon Musk is the second largest supporter of Bitcoin in the world. So I think that the Bitcoin
community tends to eat its own quite a bit. It tends to be very, very self-critical. And instead
of saying, well, Elon is more supportive of Bitcoin than the other 10,000 people in the world,
with serious amounts of money, they focus upon-
Yeah, this is strange. Eating your own is just-
That's right. I mean, I think he's free to do what he wants to do. And I think he's done a lot
of good for Bitcoin in putting it on the balance sheet of Tesla and holding it. And I think that
sent a very powerful message. Do you have advice for young people? So you've had a heck of a life.
You've done quite a lot of things before MIT, but starting with MIT. Is there advice here for
young people in high school and college, how to have a career they can be proud of,
how to have a life they can be proud of? I was asked by somebody for quick advice
for his young children. He had twins when they enter adulthood. He said, give me your advice
for them in a letter. I'm going to give it to them when they turn 21 or something. I was at a party,
and then he handed me this sheet of paper. I thought, oh, he wants me to write it down right
now. So I sat down, I started writing, and I figured, well, what would you want to tell someone
at age 21? You wrote it down.
So I wrote it down. And then I tweeted it, and it's sitting on Twitter, but I tell you what I
said. I said, my advice if you're entering adulthood, focus your energy, guard your time,
train your mind, train your body, think for yourself, curate your friends,
curate your environment, keep your promises, stay cheerful and constructive, and upgrade the world.
Like that was the 10.
Upgrade the world. That's an interesting choice of words. Upgrade the world. Upgrade the world.
It's like an engineering training.
Focus your energy. It's a very, yeah, it's a very engineering-themed,
very engineering-themed, keep your promises too. That's an interesting one.
I think most people suffer because they just, they don't focus. You got to figure out,
I think the big risk in this world is there's too much of everything.
Yeah.
Like you can sit and watch chess videos a hundred hours a week, and you'll never get
through all the chess videos. There's too much of every possible thing, too much of every good thing.
So figuring out what you want to do and then everything will suck up your time. There's
a hundred streaming channels to binge watch on. So you got to guard your time and then
train your body, train your mind, and control who's around you, control what surrounds you.
So ultimately in a world where there's too much of everything, then you're successful.
It's like those laser eyes. It's like those laser eyes. You have to focus
on just a few of those things.
Yeah. I mean, I got a thousand opinions we could talk about and I could pursue a thousand things,
but I don't expect to be successful. And I'm not sure that my opinion in any of the 999 is any more
valid than the leader of thought in that area. So how about if I just focus upon one thing
and then deliver the best I can in the one thing. That's the laser eye message.
The rest get you distracted.
Well, how do you achieve that? Do you find yourself,
given the way you are in life, having to say no a lot, or just focus comes
naturally when you just ignore everything around you? So how do you achieve that focus?
I think it helps if people know what you're focused on.
So everything about you just radiates that people know. People know this is-
If they know what you're focused on, then you won't get so many other things coming your way.
If you, you know, if you dolly or if you flirt with 27 different things,
then you're going to get approached by people in each of the 27 communities, right?
You mentioned getting a PhD and giving your roots at MIT. Do you think there's all kinds of
journeys you can take to educate yourself? Do you think a PhD or school is still worth it?
Or is there other paths through life that-
Is it worth it if you have to pay for it? Is it worth it if you spend the time on it?
Yeah. The time and the money is a big cost.
I think-
Time probably the bigger one, right?
It seems clear to me that the world wants more specialists. It wants you to be an expert
and to focus on one area. And it's punishing generalists, jack of all trades, especially
people that are generalists in the physical realm. Because if you're a specialist in the digital
realm, you might very well- You're the person with 700,000 followers on Twitter and you show
them how to tie knots. Or, you know, you're the banjo player, you know, with 1.8 million followers.
And when everybody types banjo, it's you, right? And so the world wants people that do something
well. And then it wants to stamp out 18 million copies of them. And so that argues in favor of
focus. Now, I mean, the definition of a PhD is someone with enough of an education that they're
capable of or have made. I guess to get a PhD, technically, you have to have done a dissertation
where you made a seminal contribution to the body of human knowledge, right? And if you haven't done
that, technically, you know, you have a master's degree, but you're not a doctor. So if you're
interested in any of the academic disciplines that a PhD would be granted for, then I can see
that being a reasonable pursuit. But there are many people that are specialists. You know,
the agitator? Yeah, yeah, yeah. He's the world's greatest chess commentator. And I've watched his
career, and he's got progressively better, and he's really good. He's gonna love hearing this.
Yeah, if the agitator hears this, I'm a big fan of the agitator. I have to cut myself off,
right? Because otherwise you'll watch the entire Paul Morphy saga for your weekend. But the point
really is YouTube is full of experts who are specialists in something. And they rise to the
top of their profession, and Twitter is too, and the internet is. So I would advocate that you
figure out what you're passionate about, and what you're good at, and you do focus on it.
Especially if the thing that you're doing can be automated. The problem is, you know, back to that
500,000 algebra teacher type comment. The problem is, if it is possible to be automated, then over
time, someone's probably gonna automate it. And that squeezes the state space of everybody else.
It's like after the lockdowns, it used to be there are all these local bands that played in bars,
and everybody went to the bar to see the local band. And then during the lockdown, you would
have like these six super groups, and they would all get 500,000 or a million followers. And all
these smaller local bands just got no attention at all. Well, the interesting thing is one of those
500,000 algebra teachers is likely to be part of the automation. So it's like, it's an opportunity
for you to think, where's my field, my discipline evolving into? I talked to a bunch of librarians,
just happened to be friends with librarians. And that's, libraries will probably be evolving,
and it's up to you as a librarian to be one of the few that remain in the rubble.
If you're going to give commentary on Shakespeare plays, I want you to basically do it for every
Shakespeare play. Like I want you to be the Shakespeare dude, because once, just like Lex,
you're like... I don't know what kind of...
You're the deep thinking podcaster, right? You're the podcaster that goes after the deep
intellectual conversations. And once I get comfortable with you, and I like you,
then I start binge watching Lex. But if you changed your format through 16 different formats,
so that you could compete with 16 different other personalities on YouTube, you probably wouldn't
beat any of them, right? You would probably just kind of sink into the... You're the number two
or number three guy. You're not the number one guy in the format. And I think that the algorithm,
the Twitter algorithm and the YouTube algorithm, they really reward the person that's focused
on message, consistent. The world wants somebody they can trust that's consistent and reliable,
and they kind of want to know what they're getting into, because... And this is taken for granted
maybe, but there's 10 million people vying for every hour of your time. And so the fact that
anybody gives you any time at all is a huge privilege, right? And you should be thanking
them and you should respect their time. It's interesting. Everything you said is very interesting.
But of course, from my perspective, and probably from your perspective, my actual life has nothing
to do with... It's just being focused on stuff. And in my case, it's like focus on doing the thing I
really enjoy doing, and being myself, and not caring about anything else. I don't care about
views or likes or attention. And just maintaining that focus is the way, from an individual
perspective, you live that life. But yeah, it does seem that the world and technology is rewarding
the specialization and creating bigger and bigger platforms for the different specializations. And
that lifts all boats, actually, because the specializations get better and better and better
at teaching people to do specific things, and they educate themselves, and it's just... Everybody
gets more and more knowledgeable and more and more empowered. The reward for authenticity
more than offsets the specificity with which you pursue your mission. Another way to say it is,
like, nobody wants to read advertising. If you were to spend a hundred million dollars advertising
your thing, I probably wouldn't want to watch it. We see the death of that. And so the commercial
shows are losing their audiences, and the authentic specialists or the authentic artists
are gaining their audience. And that's a beautiful thing. Speaking of deep thinking,
you're just a human. Your life ends. You've accumulated so much wisdom, so much money,
but the ride ends. Do you think about that? Do you ponder your death, your mortality? Are you
afraid of it? When I go, all my assets will flow into a foundation, and the foundation's mission
is to make education free for everybody forever. And if I'm able to contribute to the creation of
a more perfect monetary system, then maybe that foundation will go on forever.
Right. The idea, the foundation of the idea. Each of the foundations.
It's not clear we're on the S-curve of immortal life yet. That's a biological
question, and you ask that on some of your other interviews a lot. I think that we are on the
threshold of immortal life for ideas, or immortal life for certain institutions
or computer programs. So if we can fix the money, then you can create a technically perfected
endowment. And then the question really is, what are your ideas? What do you want to leave behind?
And so if it's a park, then you endow the park, right? If it's free education, you endow that.
If it's some other ethical idea, right?
Does it make you sad that there's something that you've endowed, some very powerful idea
of digital energy that you put out into the world, you help put it into the world,
and your mind, your conscious mind will no longer be there to experience it. It's just gone forever.
SFX I rather think that the thing that Satoshi taught us is,
you should do your part during some phase of the journey, and then you should get out of the way.
I think Steve Jobs said something similar to that effect in a very famous speech one day,
which is, death is a natural part of life, and it makes way for the next generation.
And I think the goal is, you upgrade the world, right? You leave it a better place,
but you get out of the way. And I think when that breaks down, you know, bad things happen.
I think nature cleanses itself. There's a cycle of life.
And speaking of one of great people who did also get out of the way is George Washington. So
hopefully, when you get out of the way, nobody's bleeding you to death in hope of helping you.
What do you think, to do a bit of a callback, what do you think is the meaning of this whole thing?
What's the meaning of life? Why are we here? We talked about the rise of human civilization.
It seems like we're engineers at heart. We build cool stuff, better and better use of energy,
channeling energy to be productive. Why? What's it all for?
You're getting metaphysical on me.
Very. There's a beautiful boat to the left of us. Like, why do we do that? This boat that sailed
the ocean. Then we build models of it to celebrate great engineering of the past.
To engineer is divine. You can make lots of arguments as to why we're here. We're here
to entertain ourself or we're here to create something that's beautiful or something that's
functional. I think if you're an engineer, you entertain yourself by creating something that's
both beautiful and functional. So I think all three of those things, it's entertaining, but
it's ethical. You got to admire the first person that built a bridge, crossing a chasm, or the
first person to work out the problem of how to get running water to a village. The first person
to figure out how to dam up a river or mastered agriculture. The guy that figured out how to grow
fruit on trees or created orchards, and maybe one day had like 10 fruit trees, he's pretty
proud of himself. So that's functional. There is also something to that, just like you said,
that's just beautiful. It does get you closer to, like you said, the divine. When you step
back and look at the entirety of it, a collective of humans using a beautiful invention or creation
or just something about this instrument is creating a beautiful piece of music. That seems
just right. That's what we're here for. Whatever the divine is, it seems like we're here for that.
And I, of course, love talking to you because from the engineering perspective, the function
is ultimately the mechanism towards the beauty. Isn't there something beautiful about making
the world a better place for people that you love, your friends, your family, or yourself?
When you think about the entire arc of human existence and you roll the clock back 500,000
years and you think about every struggle of everyone that came before us and everything
they had to overcome in order to put you here right now, you got to admire that, right? You
got to respect that. That's a heck of a gift they gave us, but it's also a heck of a responsibility.
Don't screw it up. If I dropped you 500,000 years ago and I said, figure out steel refining,
or figure out silicon chips, fab reproduction, or whatever it is.
Fly or fire.
And so now we're here, and I guess the way you repay them is you fix everything in front of
your face you can, right? And that means to someone like Elon, it means get us off the planet,
right? To someone like me, it's like, I think, you know, fix the energy in the system.
And that gives me hope. Michael, this is an incredible conversation. You're an incredible
human. It's a huge honor you would sit down with me. Thank you so much for talking to me.
Yeah, thanks for having me, Lex.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Michael Saylor. To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description. And now,
let me leave you with a few words from Francis Bacon. Money is a great servant, but a bad master.
Thank you for listening, and hope to see you next time.